<?xml-model href="scene.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<scene id="I">
    <head>NIGHT</head>
    <stage>(A lofty-arched, narrow, Gothic chamber. FAUST, in a chair at his desk,
        restless.)</stage>
    <sp>
        <speaker>FAUST</speaker>
        <lg>
            <earthly><l>I've studied now Philosophy</l>
            <l>And Jurisprudence, Medicine,—</l>
            <l>And even, alas! Theology,—</l></earthly>
            <earthly><l>From end to end, with labor keen;</l>
            <l>And here, poor fool! with all my lore</l>
            <l>I stand, no wiser than before:</l></earthly>
            <earthly><l>I'm Magister—yea, Doctor—hight,</l>
            <l>And straight or cross-wise, wrong or right,</l>
            <l>These ten years long, with many woes,</l>
            <l>I've led my scholars by the nose,—</l>
            <l>And see, that nothing can be known!</l></earthly>
            <earthly><l>That knowledge cuts me to the bone.</l></earthly>
            <divine><l>I'm cleverer, true, than those fops of teachers,</l>
            <l>Doctors and Magisters, Scribes and Preachers;</l>
            <l>Neither scruples nor doubts come now to smite me,</l>
            <l>Nor Hell nor Devil can longer affright me.</l></divine>
        </lg>
        <lg>
            <earthly><l>For this, all pleasure am I foregoing;</l>
            <l>I do not pretend to aught worth knowing,</l>
            <l>I do not pretend I could be a teacher</l>
            <l>To help or convert a fellow-creature.</l></earthly>
            <divine><l>Then, too, I've neither lands nor gold,</l>
            <l>Nor the world's least pomp or honor hold—</l>
            <l>No dog would endure such a curst existence!</l></divine>
            <divine><l>Wherefore, from Magic I seek assistance,</l>
            <l>That many a secret perchance I reach</l>
            <l>Through spirit-power and spirit-speech,</l>
            <l>And thus the bitter task forego</l>
            <l>Of saying the things I do not know,—</l>
            <l>That I may detect the inmost force</l>
            <l>Which binds the world, and guides its course;</l></divine>
            <divine><l>Its germs, productive powers explore,</l>
            <l>And rummage in empty words no more!</l></divine>
        </lg>
        <lg>
            <divine><l>O full and splendid Moon, whom I</l>
            <l>Have, from this desk, seen climb the sky</l>
            <l>So many a midnight,—would thy glow</l>
            <l>For the last time beheld my woe!</l></divine>
            <divine><l>Ever thine eye, most mournful friend,</l>
            <l>O'er books and papers saw me bend;</l>
            <l>But would that I, on mountains grand,</l>
            <l>Amid thy blessed light could stand,</l>
            <l>With spirits through mountain-caverns hover,</l>
            <l>Float in thy twilight the meadows over,</l>
            <l>And, freed from the fumes of lore that swathe me,</l>
            <l>To health in thy dewy fountains bathe me!</l></divine>
        </lg>
        <lg>
            <earthly><l>Ah, me! this dungeon still I see.</l></earthly>
            <earthly><l>This drear, accursed masonry,</l>
            <l>Where even the welcome daylight strains</l>
            <l>But duskly through the painted panes.</l></earthly>
            <divine><l>Hemmed in by many a toppling heap</l>
            <l>Of books worm-eaten, gray with dust,</l>
            <l>Which to the vaulted ceiling creep,</l>
            <l>Against the smoky paper thrust,—</l>
            <l>With glasses, boxes, round me stacked,</l>
            <l>And instruments together hurled,</l>
            <l>Ancestral lumber, stuffed and packed—</l>
            <l>Such is my world: and what a world!</l></divine>
        </lg>
        <lg>
            <earthly><l>And do I ask, wherefore my heart</l>
            <l>Falters, oppressed with unknown needs?</l></earthly>
            <divine><l>Why some inexplicable smart</l>
            <l>All movement of my life impedes?</l></divine>
            <earthly><l>Alas! in living Nature's stead,</l>
            <l>Where God His human creature set,</l>
            <l>In smoke and mould the fleshless dead</l>
            <l>And bones of beasts surround me yet!</l></earthly>
        </lg>
        <lg>
            <divine><l>Fly! Up, and seek the broad, free land!</l></divine>
            <divine><l>And this one Book of Mystery</l>
            <l>From Nostradamus' very hand,</l>
            <l>Is't not sufficient company?</l></divine>
            <divine><l>When I the starry courses know,</l>
            <l>And Nature's wise instruction seek,</l>
            <l>With light of power my soul shall glow,</l>
            <l>As when to spirits spirits speak.</l></divine>
            <divine><l>Tis vain, this empty brooding here,</l>
            <l>Though guessed the holy symbols be:</l>
            <l>Ye, Spirits, come—ye hover near—</l>
            <l>Oh, if you hear me, answer me!</l></divine>
        </lg>
        <stage>(He opens the Book, and perceives the sign of the Macrocosm.)</stage>
        <lg>
            <divine><l>Ha! what a sudden rapture leaps from this</l>
            <l>I view, through all my senses swiftly flowing!</l></divine>
            <divine><l>I feel a youthful, holy, vital bliss</l>
            <l>In every vein and fibre newly glowing.</l></divine>
            <divine><l>Was it a God, who traced this sign,</l>
            <l>With calm across my tumult stealing,</l>
            <l>My troubled heart to joy unsealing,</l>
            <l>With impulse, mystic and divine,</l>
            <l>The powers of Nature here, around my path, revealing?</l></divine>
            <divine><l>Am I a God?—so clear mine eyes!</l></divine>
            <divine><l>In these pure features I behold</l>
            <l>Creative Nature to my soul unfold.</l></divine>
            <divine><l>What says the sage, now first I recognize:</l>
            <l>"The spirit-world no closures fasten;</l>
            <l>Thy sense is shut, thy heart is dead:</l>
            <l>Disciple, up! untiring, hasten</l>
            <l>To bathe thy breast in morning-red!"</l></divine>
        </lg>
        <stage>(He contemplates the sign.)</stage>
        <lg>
            <divine><l>How each the Whole its substance gives,</l>
            <l>Each in the other works and lives!</l></divine>
            <divine><l>Like heavenly forces rising and descending,</l>
            <l>Their golden urns reciprocally lending,</l>
            <l>With wings that winnow blessing</l>
            <l>From Heaven through Earth I see them pressing,</l>
            <l>Filling the All with harmony unceasing!</l></divine>
            <divine><l>How grand a show! but, ah! a show alone.</l></divine>
            <divine><l>Thee, boundless Nature, how make thee my own?</l></divine>
            <divine><l>Where you, ye beasts? Founts of all Being, shining,</l>
            <l>Whereon hang Heaven's and Earth's desire,</l>
            <l>Whereto our withered hearts aspire,—</l>
            <l>Ye flow, ye feed: and am I vainly pining?</l></divine>
        </lg>
        <stage>(He turns the leaves impatiently, and perceives the sign of the
            Earth-Spirit.)</stage>
        <lg>
            <divine><l>How otherwise upon me works this sign!</l></divine>
            <earthly><l>Thou, Spirit of the Earth, art nearer:</l>
            <l>Even now my powers are loftier, clearer;</l>
            <l>I glow, as drunk with new-made wine:</l>
            <l>New strength and heart to meet the world incite me,</l>
            <l>The woe of earth, the bliss of earth, invite me,</l>
            <l>And though the shock of storms may smite me,</l>
            <l>No crash of shipwreck shall have power to fright me!</l></earthly>
            <earthly><l>Clouds gather over me—</l>
            <l>The moon conceals her light—</l>
            <l>The lamp's extinguished!—</l></earthly>
            <earthly><l>Mists rise,—red, angry rays are darting</l>
            <l>Around my head!—There falls</l>
            <l>A horror from the vaulted roof,</l>
            <l>And seizes me!</l></earthly>
            <divine><l>I feel thy presence, Spirit I invoke!</l>
            <l>Reveal thyself!</l></divine>
            <divine><l>Ha! in my heart what rending stroke!</l></divine>
            <earthly><l>With new impulsion</l>
            <l>My senses heave in this convulsion!</l></earthly>
            <divine><l>I feel thee draw my heart, absorb, exhaust me:</l>
            <l>Thou must! thou must! and though my life it cost me!</l></divine>
        </lg>
        <stage>(He seizes the book, and mysteriously pronounces the sign of the Spirit. A ruddy flame flashes: the Spirit appears in the flame.)</stage>
    </sp>
    <sp>
        <speaker>SPIRIT</speaker>
        <lg>
            <l>Who calls me?</l>
        </lg>
    </sp>
    <sp>
        <speaker>FAUST</speaker>
        <stage>(with averted head)</stage>
        <lg>
            <earthly><l>Terrible to see!</l></earthly>
        </lg>
    </sp>
    <sp>
        <speaker>SPIRIT</speaker>
        <lg>
            <l>Me hast thou long with might attracted,</l>
            <l>Long from my sphere thy food exacted,</l>
            <l>And now—</l>
        </lg>
    </sp>
    <sp>
        <speaker>FAUST</speaker>
        <lg>
            <earthly><l>Woe! I endure not thee!</l></earthly>
        </lg>
    </sp>
    <sp>
        <speaker>SPIRIT</speaker>
        <lg>
            <l>To view me is thine aspiration,</l>
            <l>My voice to hear, my countenance to see;</l>
            <l>Thy powerful yearning moveth me,</l>
            <l>Here am I!—what mean perturbation</l>
            <l>Thee, superhuman, shakes? Thy soul's high calling, where?</l>
            <l>Where is the breast, which from itself a world did bear,</l>
            <l>And shaped and cherished—which with joy expanded,</l>
            <l>To be our peer, with us, the Spirits, banded?</l>
            <l>Where art thou, Faust, whose voice has pierced to me,</l>
            <l>Who towards me pressed with all thine energy?</l>
            <l>He art thou, who, my presence breathing, seeing,</l>
            <l>Trembles through all the depths of being,</l>
            <l>A writhing worm, a terror-stricken form?</l>
        </lg>
    </sp>
    <sp>
        <speaker>FAUST</speaker>
        <lg>
            <divine><l>Thee, form of flame, shall I then fear?</l></divine>
            <divine><l>Yes, I am Faust: I am thy peer!</l></divine>
        </lg>
    </sp>
    <sp>
        <speaker>SPIRIT</speaker>
        <lg>
            <l>In the tides of Life, in Action's storm,</l>
            <l>A fluctuant wave,</l>
            <l>A shuttle free,</l>
            <l>Birth and the Grave,</l>
            <l>An eternal sea,</l>
            <l>A weaving, flowing</l>
            <l>Life, all-glowing,</l>
            <l>Thus at Time's humming loom 'tis my hand prepares</l>
            <l>The garment of Life which the Deity wears!</l>
        </lg>
    </sp>
    <sp>
        <speaker>FAUST</speaker>
        <lg>
            <divine><l>Thou, who around the wide world wendest,</l>
            <l>Thou busy Spirit, how near I feel to thee!</l></divine>
        </lg>
    </sp>
    <sp>
        <speaker>SPIRIT</speaker>
        <lg>
            <l>Thou'rt like the Spirit which thou comprehendest,</l>
            <l>Not me!</l>
        </lg>
        <stage>(Disappears.)</stage>
    </sp>
    <sp>
        <speaker>FAUST</speaker>
        <stage>(overwhelmed)</stage>
        <lg>
            <divine><l>Not thee!</l></divine>
            <earthly><l>Whom then?</l></earthly>
            <divine><l>I, image of the Godhead!</l></divine>
            <divine><l>Not even like thee!</l></divine>
        </lg>
        <stage>(A knock.)</stage>
        <lg>
            <earthly><l>O Death!—I know it—'tis my Famulus!</l></earthly>
            <earthly><l>My fairest luck finds no fruition:</l>
            <l>In all the fullness of my vision</l>
            <l>The soulless sneak disturbs me thus!</l></earthly>
        </lg>
        <stage>(Enter WAGNER, in dressing-gown and night-cap, a lamp in his hand. FAUST turns
            impatiently.)</stage>
    </sp>
    <sp>
        <speaker>WAGNER</speaker>
        <lg>
            <l>Pardon, I heard your declamation;</l>
            <l>'Twas sure an old Greek tragedy you read?</l>
            <l>In such an art I crave some preparation,</l>
            <l>Since now it stands one in good stead.</l>
            <l>I've often heard it said, a preacher</l>
            <l>Might learn, with a comedian for a teacher.</l>
        </lg>
    </sp>
    <sp>
        <speaker>FAUST</speaker>
        <lg>
            <earthly><l>Yes, when the priest comedian is by nature,</l>
            <l>As haply now and then the case may be.</l></earthly>
        </lg>
    </sp>
    <sp>
        <speaker>WAGNER</speaker>
        <lg>
            <l>Ah, when one studies thus, a prisoned creature,</l>
            <l>That scarce the world on holidays can see,—</l>
            <l>Scarce through a glass, by rare occasion,</l>
            <l>How shall one lead it by persuasion?</l>
        </lg>
    </sp>
    <sp>
        <speaker>FAUST</speaker>
        <lg>
            <divine><l>You'll ne'er attain it, save you know the feeling,</l>
            <l>Save from the soul it rises clear,</l>
            <l>Serene in primal strength, compelling</l>
            <l>The hearts and minds of all who hear.</l></divine>
            <earthly><l>You sit forever gluing, patching;</l>
            <l>You cook the scraps from others' fare;</l>
            <l>And from your heap of ashes hatching</l>
            <l>A starveling flame, ye blow it bare!</l></earthly>
            <earthly><l>Take children's, monkeys' gaze admiring,</l>
            <l>If such your taste, and be content;</l>
            <l>But ne'er from heart to heart you'll speak inspiring,</l>
            <l>Save your own heart is eloquent!</l></earthly>
        </lg>
    </sp>
    <sp>
        <speaker>WAGNER</speaker>
        <lg>
            <l>Yet through delivery orators succeed;</l>
            <l>I feel that I am far behind, indeed.</l>
        </lg>
    </sp>
    <sp>
        <speaker>FAUST</speaker>
        <lg>
            <divine><l>Seek thou the honest recompense!</l></divine>
            <divine><l>Beware, a tinkling fool to be!</l></divine>
            <divine><l>With little art, clear wit and sense</l>
            <l>Suggest their own delivery;</l>
            <l>And if thou'rt moved to speak in earnest,</l>
            <l>What need, that after words thou yearnest?</l></divine>
            <divine><l>Yes, your discourses, with their glittering show,</l>
            <l>Where ye for men twist shredded thought like paper,</l>
            <l>Are unrefreshing as the winds that blow</l>
            <l>The rustling leaves through chill autumnal vapor!</l></divine>
        </lg>
    </sp>
    <sp>
        <speaker>WAGNER</speaker>
        <lg>
            <l>Ah, God! but Art is long,</l>
            <l>And Life, alas! is fleeting.</l>
            <l>And oft, with zeal my critic-duties meeting,</l>
            <l>In head and breast there's something wrong.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
            <l>How hard it is to compass the assistance</l>
            <l>Whereby one rises to the source!</l>
            <l>And, haply, ere one travels half the course</l>
            <l>Must the poor devil quit existence.</l>
        </lg>
    </sp>
    <sp>
        <speaker>FAUST</speaker>
        <lg>
            <divine><l>Is parchment, then, the holy fount before thee,</l>
            <l>A draught wherefrom thy thirst forever slakes?</l></divine>
            <divine><l>No true refreshment can restore thee,</l>
            <l>Save what from thine own soul spontaneous breaks.</l></divine>
        </lg>
    </sp>
    <sp>
        <speaker>WAGNER</speaker>
        <lg>
            <l>Pardon! a great delight is granted</l>
            <l>When, in the spirit of the ages planted,</l>
            <l>We mark how, ere our times, a sage has thought,</l>
            <l>And then, how far his work, and grandly, we have brought.</l>
        </lg>
    </sp>
    <sp>
        <speaker>FAUST</speaker>
        <lg>
            <divine><l>O yes, up to the stars at last!</l></divine>
            <divine><l>Listen, my friend: the ages that are past</l>
            <l>Are now a book with seven seals protected:</l>
            <l>What you the Spirit of the Ages call</l>
            <l>Is nothing but the spirit of you all,</l>
            <l>Wherein the Ages are reflected.</l></divine>
            <divine><l>So, oftentimes, you miserably mar it!</l></divine>
            <divine><l>At the first glance who sees it runs away.</l></divine>
            <divine><l>An offal-barrel and a lumber-garret,</l>
            <l>Or, at the best, a Punch-and-Judy play,</l>
            <l>With maxims most pragmatical and hitting,</l>
            <l>As in the mouths of puppets are befitting!</l></divine>
        </lg>
    </sp>
    <sp>
        <speaker>WAGNER</speaker>
        <lg>
            <l>But then, the world—the human heart and brain!</l>
            <l>Of these one covets some slight apprehension.</l>
        </lg>
    </sp>
    <sp>
        <speaker>FAUST</speaker>
        <lg>
            <earthly><l>Yes, of the kind which men attain!</l></earthly>
            <divine><l>Who dares the child's true name in public mention?</l></divine>
            <divine><l>The few, who thereof something really learned,</l>
            <l>Unwisely frank, with hearts that spurned concealing,</l>
            <l>And to the mob laid bare each thought and feeling,</l>
            <l>Have evermore been crucified and burned.</l></divine>
            <divine><l>I pray you, Friend, 'tis now the dead of night;</l>
            <l>Our converse here must be suspended.</l></divine>
        </lg>
    </sp>
    <sp>
        <speaker>WAGNER</speaker>
        <lg>
            <l>I would have shared your watches with delight,</l>
            <l>That so our learned talk might be extended.</l>
            <l>To-morrow, though, I'll ask, in Easter leisure,</l>
            <l>This and the other question, at your pleasure.</l>
            <l>Most zealously I seek for erudition:</l>
            <l>Much do I know—but to know all is my ambition.</l>
        </lg>
        <stage>[Exit.</stage>
    </sp>
    <sp>
        <speaker>FAUST</speaker>
        <stage>(solus)</stage>
        <lg>
            <earthly><l>That brain, alone, not loses hope, whose choice is</l>
            <l>To stick in shallow trash forevermore,—</l>
            <l>Which digs with eager hand for buried ore,</l>
            <l>And, when it finds an angle-worm, rejoices!</l></earthly>
        </lg>
        <lg>
            <divine><l>Dare such a human voice disturb the flow,</l>
            <l>Around me here, of spirit-presence fullest?</l></divine>
            <earthly><l>And yet, this once my thanks I owe</l>
            <l>To thee, of all earth's sons the poorest, dullest!</l></earthly>
            <earthly><l>For thou hast torn me from that desperate state</l>
            <l>Which threatened soon to overwhelm my senses:</l>
            <l>The apparition was so giant-great,</l>
            <l>It dwarfed and withered all my soul's pretences!</l></earthly>
        </lg>
        <lg>
            <divine><l>I, image of the Godhead, who began—</l>
            <l>Deeming Eternal Truth secure in nearness—</l></divine>
            <divine><l>Ye choirs, have ye begun the sweet, consoling chant,</l>
            <l>Which, through the night of Death, the angels ministrant</l>
            <l>Sang, God's new Covenant repeating?</l></divine>
        </lg>
    </sp>
    <sp>
        <speaker>CHORUS OF WOMEN</speaker>
        <lg>
            <l>With spices and precious</l>
            <l>Balm, we arrayed him;</l>
            <l>Faithful and gracious,</l>
            <l>We tenderly laid him:</l>
            <l>Linen to bind him</l>
            <l>Cleanlily wound we:</l>
            <l>Ah! when we would find him,</l>
            <l>Christ no more found we!</l>
        </lg>
    </sp>
    <sp>
        <speaker>CHORUS OF ANGELS</speaker>
        <lg>
            <l>Christ is ascended!</l>
            <l>Bliss hath invested him,—</l>
            <l>Woes that molested him,</l>
            <l>Trials that tested him,</l>
            <l>Gloriously ended!</l>
        </lg>
    </sp>
    <sp>
        <speaker>FAUST</speaker>
        <lg>
            <divine><l>Why, here in dust, entice me with your spell,</l>
            <l>Ye gentle, powerful sounds of Heaven?</l></divine>
            <divine><l>Peal rather there, where tender natures dwell.</l></divine>
            <divine><l>Your messages I hear, but faith has not been given;</l>
            <l>The dearest child of Faith is Miracle.</l></divine>
            <earthly><l>I venture not to soar to yonder regions</l>
            <l>Whence the glad tidings hither float;</l>
            <l>And yet, from childhood up familiar with the note,</l>
            <l>To Life it now renews the old allegiance.</l></earthly>
            <earthly><l>Once Heavenly Love sent down a burning kiss</l>
            <l>Upon my brow, in Sabbath silence holy;</l>
            <l>And, filled with mystic presage, chimed the church-bell slowly,</l>
            <l>And prayer dissolved me in a fervent bliss.</l></earthly>
            <earthly><l>A sweet, uncomprehended yearning</l>
            <l>Drove forth my feet through woods and meadows free,</l>
            <l>And while a thousand tears were burning,</l>
            <l>I felt a world arise for me.</l></earthly>
            <earthly><l>These chants, to youth and all its sports appealing,</l>
            <l>Proclaimed the Spring's rejoicing holiday;</l>
            <l>And Memory holds me now, with childish feeling,</l>
            <l>Back from the last, the solemn way.</l></earthly>
            <earthly><l>Sound on, ye hymns of Heaven, so sweet and mild!</l></earthly>
            <earthly><l>My tears gush forth: the Earth takes back her child!</l></earthly>
        </lg>
    </sp>
    <sp>
        <speaker>CHORUS OF DISCIPLES</speaker>
        <lg>
            <l>Has He, victoriously,</l>
            <l>Burst from the vaulted</l>
            <l>Grave, and all-gloriously</l>
            <l>Now sits exalted?</l>
            <l>Is He, in glow of birth,</l>
            <l>Rapture creative near?</l>
            <l>Ah! to the woe of earth</l>
            <l>Still are we native here.</l>
            <l>We, his aspiring</l>
            <l>Followers, Him we miss;</l>
            <l>Weeping, desiring,</l>
            <l>Master, Thy bliss!</l>
        </lg>
    </sp>
    <sp>
        <speaker>CHORUS OF ANGELS</speaker>
        <lg>
            <l>Christ is arisen,</l>
            <l>Out of Corruption's womb:</l>
            <l>Burst ye the prison,</l>
            <l>Break from your gloom!</l>
            <l>Praising and pleading him,</l>
            <l>Lovingly needing him,</l>
            <l>Brotherly feeding him,</l>
            <l>Preaching and speeding him,</l>
            <l>Blessing, succeeding Him,</l>
            <l>Thus is the Master near,—</l>
            <l>Thus is He here!</l>
        </lg>
    </sp>
</scene>
