<Play>
<Title> Faust</Title>

<Author>Johann Wolfgang Von Goethe</Author>

<Speaker>DEDICATION</Speaker>
<l>Again ye come, ye hovering Forms! I find ye,</l>
<l>As early to my clouded sight ye shone!</l>
<l>Shall I attempt, this once, to seize and bind ye?</l>
<l>Still o&apos;er my heart is that illusion thrown?</l>
<l>Ye crowd more near! Then, be the reign assigned ye,</l>
<l>And sway me from your misty, shadowy zone!</l>
<l>My bosom thrills, with youthful passion shaken,</l>
<l>From magic airs that round your march awaken.</l>

<l>Of joyous days ye bring the blissful vision;</l>
<l>The dear, familiar phantoms rise again,</l>
<l>And, like an old and half-extinct tradition,</l>
<l>First Love returns, with Friendship in his train.</l>
<l>Renewed is Pain: with mournful repetition</l>
<l>Life tracks his devious, labyrinthine chain,</l>
<l>And names the Good, whose cheating fortune tore them</l>
<l>From happy hours, and left me to deplore them.</l>

<l>They hear no longer these succeeding measures,</l>
<l>The souls, to whom my earliest songs I sang:</l>

<l>Dispersed the friendly troop, with all its pleasures,</l>
<l>And still, alas! the echoes first that rang!</l>
<l>I bring the unknown multitude my treasures;</l>
<l>Their very plaudits give my heart a pang,</l>
<l>And those beside, whose joy my Song so flattered,</l>
<l>If still they live, wide through the world are scattered.</l>

<l>And grasps me now a long-unwonted yearning</l>
<l>For that serene and solemn Spirit-Land:</l>
<l>My song, to faint Aeolian murmurs turning,</l>
<l>Sways like a harp-string by the breezes fanned.</l>
<l>I thrill and tremble; tear on tear is burning,</l>
<l>And the stern heart is tenderly unmanned.</l>
<l>What I possess, I see far distant lying,</l>
<l>And what I lost, grows real and undying.</l>

<l>PRELUDE AT THE THEATRE</l>


<l>MANAGER ==== DRAMATIC POET ==== MERRY-ANDREW</l>


<Speaker>MANAGER</Speaker>

<l>You two, who oft a helping hand</l>
<l>Have lent, in need and tribulation.</l>
<l>Come, let me know your expectation</l>
<l>Of this, our enterprise, in German land!</l>
<l>I wish the crowd to feel itself well treated,</l>
<l>Especially since it lives and lets me live;</l>
<l>The posts are set, the booth of boards completed.</l>
<l>And each awaits the banquet I shall give.</l>
<l>Already there, with curious eyebrows raised,</l>
<l>They sit sedate, and hope to be amazed.</l>
<l>I know how one the People&apos;s taste may flatter,</l>
<l>Yet here a huge embarrassment I feel:</l>
<l>What they&apos;re accustomed to, is no great matter,</l>
<l>But then, alas! they&apos;ve read an awful deal.</l>
<l>How shall we plan, that all be fresh and new,—</l>
<l>Important matter, yet attractive too?</l>
<l>For &apos;tis my pleasure-to behold them surging,</l>
<l>When to our booth the current sets apace,</l>
<l>And with tremendous, oft-repeated urging,</l>
<l>Squeeze onward through the narrow gate of grace:</l>
<l>By daylight even, they push and cram in</l>
<l>To reach the seller&apos;s box, a fighting host,</l>
<l>And as for bread, around a baker&apos;s door, in famine,</l>
<l>To get a ticket break their necks almost.</l>
<l>This miracle alone can work the Poet</l>
<l>On men so various: now, my friend, pray show it.</l>


<Speaker>POET</Speaker>


<l>Speak not to me of yonder motley masses,</l>
<l>Whom but to see, puts out the fire of Song!</l>
<l>Hide from my view the surging crowd that passes,</l>
<l>And in its whirlpool forces us along!</l>
<l>No, lead me where some heavenly silence glasses</l>
<l>The purer joys that round the Poet throng,—</l>
<l>Where Love and Friendship still divinely fashion</l>
<l>The bonds that bless, the wreaths that crown his passion!</l>
<l>Ah, every utterance from the depths of feeling</l>
<l>The timid lips have stammeringly expressed,—</l>
<l>Now failing, now, perchance, success revealing,—</l>
<l>Gulps the wild Moment in its greedy breast;</l>
<l>Or oft, reluctant years its warrant sealing,</l>
<l>Its perfect stature stands at last confessed!</l>
<l>What dazzles, for the Moment spends its spirit:</l>
<l>What&apos;s genuine, shall Posterity inherit.</l>


<Speaker>MERRY-ANDREW</Speaker>


<l>Posterity! Don&apos;t name the word to me!</l>
<l>If I should choose to preach Posterity,</l>
<l>Where would you get contemporary fun?</l>
<l>That men will have it, there&apos;s no blinking:</l>
<l>A fine young fellow&apos;s presence, to my thinking,</l>
<l>Is something worth, to every one.</l>
<l>Who genially his nature can outpour,</l>
<l>Takes from the People&apos;s moods no irritation;</l>
<l>The wider circle he acquires, the more</l>
<l>Securely works his inspiration.</l>
<l>Then pluck up heart, and give us sterling coin!</l>
<l>Let Fancy be with her attendants fitted,—</l>
<l>Sense, Reason, Sentiment, and Passion join,—</l>
<l>But have a care, lest Folly be omitted!</l>

<Speaker>MANAGER</Speaker>

<l>Chiefly, enough of incident prepare!</l>
<l>They come to look, and they prefer to stare.</l>
<l>Reel off a host of threads before their faces,</l>
<l>So that they gape in stupid wonder: then</l>
<l>By sheer diffuseness you have won their graces,</l>
<l>And are, at once, most popular of men.</l>
<l>Only by mass you touch the mass; for any</l>
<l>Will finally, himself, his bit select:</l>
<l>Who offers much, brings something unto many,</l>
<l>And each goes home content with the effect,</l>
<l>If you&apos;ve a piece, why, just in pieces give it:</l>
<l>A hash, a stew, will bring success, believe it!</l>
<l>&apos;Tis easily displayed, and easy to invent.</l>
<l>What use, a Whole compactly to present?</l>
<l>Your hearers pick and pluck, as soon as they receive it!</l>

<Speaker>POET</Speaker>

<l>You do not feel, how such a trade debases;</l>
<l>How ill it suits the Artist, proud and true!</l>
<l>The botching work each fine pretender traces</l>
<l>Is, I perceive, a principle with you.</l>

<Speaker>MANAGER</Speaker>

<l>Such a reproach not in the least offends;</l>
<l>A man who some result intends</l>
<l>Must use the tools that best are fitting.</l>
<l>Reflect, soft wood is given to you for splitting,</l>
<l>And then, observe for whom you write!</l>
<l>If one comes bored, exhausted quite,</l>
<l>Another, satiate, leaves the banquet&apos;s tapers,</l>
<l>And, worst of all, full many a wight</l>
<l>Is fresh from reading of the daily papers.</l>
<l>Idly to us they come, as to a masquerade,</l>
<l>Mere curiosity their spirits warming:</l>
<l>The ladies with themselves, and with their finery, aid,</l>
<l>Without a salary their parts performing.</l>
<l>What dreams are yours in high poetic places?</l>
<l>You&apos;re pleased, forsooth, full houses to behold?</l>
<l>Draw near, and view your patrons&apos; faces!</l>
<l>The half are coarse, the half are cold.</l>
<l>One, when the play is out, goes home to cards;</l>
<l>A wild night on a wench&apos;s breast another chooses:</l>
<l>Why should you rack, poor, foolish bards,</l>
<l>For ends like these, the gracious Muses?</l>
<l>I tell you, give but more—more, ever more, they ask:</l>
<l>Thus shall you hit the mark of gain and glory.</l>
<l>Seek to confound your auditory!</l>
<l>To satisfy them is a task.—</l>
<l>What ails you now? Is&apos;t suffering, or pleasure?</l>

<Speaker>POET</Speaker>

<l>Go, find yourself a more obedient slave!</l>
<l>What! shall the Poet that which Nature gave,</l>
<l>The highest right, supreme Humanity,</l>
<l>Forfeit so wantonly, to swell your treasure?</l>
<l>Whence o&apos;er the heart his empire free?</l>
<l>The elements of Life how conquers he?</l>
<l>Is&apos;t not his heart&apos;s accord, urged outward far and dim,</l>
<l>To wind the world in unison with him?</l>
<l>When on the spindle, spun to endless distance,</l>
<l>By Nature&apos;s listless hand the thread is twirled,</l>
<l>And the discordant tones of all existence</l>
<l>In sullen jangle are together hurled,</l>
<l>Who, then, the changeless orders of creation</l>
<l>Divides, and kindles into rhythmic dance?</l>
<l>Who brings the One to join the general ordination,</l>
<l>Where it may throb in grandest consonance?</l>
<l>Who bids the storm to passion stir the bosom?</l>
<l>In brooding souls the sunset burn above?</l>
<l>Who scatters every fairest April blossom</l>
<l>Along the shining path of Love?</l>
<l>Who braids the noteless leaves to crowns, requiting</l>
<l>Desert with fame, in Action&apos;s every field?</l>
<l>Who makes Olympus sure, the Gods uniting?</l>
<l>The might of Man, as in the Bard revealed.</l>

<Speaker>MERRY-ANDREW</Speaker>

<l>So, these fine forces, in conjunction,</l>
<l>Propel the high poetic function,</l>
<l>As in a love-adventure they might play!</l>
<l>You meet by accident; you feel, you stay,</l>
<l>And by degrees your heart is tangled;</l>
<l>Bliss grows apace, and then its course is jangled;</l>
<l>You&apos;re ravished quite, then comes a touch of woe,</l>
<l>And there&apos;s a neat romance, completed ere you know!</l>
<l>Let us, then, such a drama give!</l>
<l>Grasp the exhaustless life that all men live!</l>
<l>Each shares therein, though few may comprehend:</l>
<l>Where&apos;er you touch, there&apos;s interest without end.</l>
<l>In motley pictures little light,</l>
<l>Much error, and of truth a glimmering mite,</l>
<l>Thus the best beverage is supplied,</l>
<l>Whence all the world is cheered and edified.</l>
<l>Then, at your play, behold the fairest flower</l>
<l>Of youth collect, to hear the revelation!</l>
<l>Each tender soul, with sentimental power,</l>
<l>Sucks melancholy food from your creation;</l>
<l>And now in this, now that, the leaven works.</l>
<l>For each beholds what in his bosom lurks.</l>
<l>They still are moved at once to weeping or to laughter,</l>
<l>Still wonder at your flights, enjoy the show they see:</l>
<l>A mind, once formed, is never suited after;</l>
<l>One yet in growth will ever grateful be.</l>

<Speaker>POET</Speaker>

<l>Then give me back that time of pleasures,</l>
<l>While yet in joyous growth I sang,—</l>
<l>When, like a fount, the crowding measures</l>
<l>Uninterrupted gushed and sprang!</l>
<l>Then bright mist veiled the world before me,</l>
<l>In opening buds a marvel woke,</l>
<l>As I the thousand blossoms broke,</l>
<l>Which every valley richly bore me!</l>
<l>I nothing had, and yet enough for youth—</l>
<l>Joy in Illusion, ardent thirst for Truth.</l>
<l>Give, unrestrained, the old emotion,</l>
<l>The bliss that touched the verge of pain,</l>
<l>The strength of Hate, Love&apos;s deep devotion,—</l>
<l>O, give me back my youth again!</l>

<Speaker>MERRY ANDREW</Speaker>

<l>Youth, good my friend, you certainly require</l>
<l>When foes in combat sorely press you;</l>
<l>When lovely maids, in fond desire,</l>
<l>Hang on your bosom and caress you;</l>
<l>When from the hard-won goal the wreath</l>
<l>Beckons afar, the race awaiting;</l>
<l>When, after dancing out your breath,</l>
<l>You pass the night in dissipating:—</l>
<l>But that familiar harp with soul</l>
<l>To play,—with grace and bold expression,</l>
<l>And towards a self-erected goal</l>
<l>To walk with many a sweet digression,—</l>
<l>This, aged Sirs, belongs to you,</l>
<l>And we no less revere you for that reason:</l>
<l>Age childish makes, they say, but &apos;tis not true;</l>
<l>We&apos;re only genuine children still, in Age&apos;s season!</l>


<Speaker>MANAGER</Speaker>

<l>The words you&apos;ve bandied are sufficient;</l>
<l>&apos;Tis deeds that I prefer to see:</l>
<l>In compliments you&apos;re both proficient,</l>
<l>But might, the while, more useful be.</l>
<l>What need to talk of Inspiration?</l>
<l>&apos;Tis no companion of Delay.</l>
<l>If Poetry be your vocation,</l>
<l>Let Poetry your will obey!</l>
<l>Full well you know what here is wanting;</l>
<l>The crowd for strongest drink is panting,</l>
<l>And such, forthwith, I&apos;d have you brew.</l>
<l>What&apos;s left undone to-day, To-morrow will not do.</l>
<l>Waste not a day in vain digression:</l>
<l>With resolute, courageous trust</l>
<l>Seize every possible impression,</l>
<l>And make it firmly your possession;</l>
<l>You&apos;ll then work on, because you must.</l>
<l>Upon our German stage, you know it,</l>
<l>Each tries his hand at what he will;</l>
<l>So, take of traps and scenes your fill,</l>
<l>And all you find, be sure to show it!</l>
<l>Use both the great and lesser heavenly light,—</l>
<l>Squander the stars in any number,</l>
<l>Beasts, birds, trees, rocks, and all such lumber,</l>
<l>Fire, water, darkness, Day and Night!</l>
<l>Thus, in our booth&apos;s contracted sphere,</l>
<l>The circle of Creation will appear,</l>
<l>And move, as we deliberately impel,</l>
<l>From Heaven, across the World, to Hell!</l>

<l>PROLOGUE IN HEAVEN</l>


<l>THE LORD === THE HEAVENLY HOST</l>
<Speaker>Afterwards</Speaker>
<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>(The THREE ARCHANGELS come forward.)</l>


<Speaker>RAPHAEL</Speaker>

<l>The sun-orb sings, in emulation,</l>
<l>&apos;Mid brother-spheres, his ancient round:</l>
<l>His path predestined through Creation</l>
<l>He ends with step of thunder-sound.</l>
<l>The angels from his visage splendid</l>
<l>Draw power, whose measure none can say;</l>
<l>The lofty works, uncomprehended,</l>
<l>Are bright as on the earliest day.</l>


<Speaker>GABRIEL</Speaker>

<l>And swift, and swift beyond conceiving,</l>
<l>The splendor of the world goes round,</l>
<l>Day&apos;s Eden-brightness still relieving</l>
<l>The awful Night&apos;s intense profound:</l>
<l>The ocean-tides in foam are breaking,</l>
<l>Against the rocks&apos; deep bases hurled,</l>
<l>And both, the spheric race partaking,</l>
<l>Eternal, swift, are onward whirled!</l>


<Speaker>MICHAEL</Speaker>

<l>And rival storms abroad are surging</l>
<l>From sea to land, from land to sea.</l>
<l>A chain of deepest action forging</l>
<l>Round all, in wrathful energy.</l>
<l>There flames a desolation, blazing</l>
<l>Before the Thunder&apos;s crashing way:</l>
<l>Yet, Lord, Thy messengers are praising</l>
<l>The gentle movement of Thy Day.</l>


<Speaker>THE THREE</Speaker>

<l>Though still by them uncomprehended,</l>
<l>From these the angels draw their power,</l>
<l>And all Thy works, sublime and splendid,</l>
<l>Are bright as in Creation&apos;s hour.</l>


<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Since Thou, O Lord, deign&apos;st to approach again</l>
<l>And ask us how we do, in manner kindest,</l>
<l>And heretofore to meet myself wert fain,</l>
<l>Among Thy menials, now, my face Thou findest.</l>
<l>Pardon, this troop I cannot follow after</l>
<l>With lofty speech, though by them scorned and spurned:</l>
<l>My pathos certainly would move Thy laughter,</l>
<l>If Thou hadst not all merriment unlearned.</l>
<l>Of suns and worlds I&apos;ve nothing to be quoted;</l>
<l>How men torment themselves, is all I&apos;ve noted.</l>
<l>The little god o&apos; the world sticks to the same old way,</l>
<l>And is as whimsical as on Creation&apos;s day.</l>
<l>Life somewhat better might content him,</l>
<l>But for the gleam of heavenly light which Thou hast lent</l>
<Speaker>him</Speaker>
<l>He calls it Reason—thence his power&apos;s increased,</l>
<l>To be far beastlier than any beast.</l>
<l>Saving Thy Gracious Presence, he to me</l>
<l>A long-legged grasshopper appears to be,</l>
<l>That springing flies, and flying springs,</l>
<l>And in the grass the same old ditty sings.</l>
<l>Would he still lay among the grass he grows in!</l>
<l>Each bit of dung he seeks, to stick his nose in.</l>


<Speaker>THE LORD</Speaker>

<l>Hast thou, then, nothing more to mention?</l>
<l>Com&apos;st ever, thus, with ill intention?</l>
<l>Find&apos;st nothing right on earth, eternally?</l>


<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>No, Lord! I find things, there, still bad as they can be.</l>
<l>Man&apos;s misery even to pity moves my nature;</l>
<l>I&apos;ve scarce the heart to plague the wretched creature.</l>


<Speaker>THE LORD</Speaker>

<l>Know&apos;st Faust?</l>


<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>The Doctor Faust?</l>


<Speaker>THE LORD</Speaker>

<l>My servant, he!</l>


<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Forsooth! He serves you after strange devices:</l>
<l>No earthly meat or drink the fool suffices:</l>
<l>His spirit&apos;s ferment far aspireth;</l>
<l>Half conscious of his frenzied, crazed unrest,</l>
<l>The fairest stars from Heaven he requireth,</l>
<l>From Earth the highest raptures and the best,</l>
<l>And all the Near and Far that he desireth</l>
<l>Fails to subdue the tumult of his breast.</l>


<Speaker>THE LORD</Speaker>

<l>Though still confused his service unto Me,</l>
<l>I soon shall lead him to a clearer morning.</l>
<l>Sees not the gardener, even while buds his tree,</l>
<l>Both flower and fruit the future years adorning?</l>


<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>What will you bet? There&apos;s still a chance to gain him,</l>
<l>If unto me full leave you give,</l>
<l>Gently upon my road to train him!</l>


<Speaker>THE LORD</Speaker>

<l>As long as he on earth shall live,</l>
<l>So long I make no prohibition.</l>
<l>While Man&apos;s desires and aspirations stir,</l>
<l>He cannot choose but err.</l>


<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>My thanks! I find the dead no acquisition,</l>
<l>And never cared to have them in my keeping.</l>
<l>I much prefer the cheeks where ruddy blood is leaping,</l>
<l>And when a corpse approaches, close my house:</l>
<l>It goes with me, as with the cat the mouse.</l>


<Speaker>THE LORD</Speaker>

<l>Enough! What thou hast asked is granted.</l>
<l>Turn off this spirit from his fountain-head;</l>
<l>To trap him, let thy snares be planted,</l>
<l>And him, with thee, be downward led;</l>
<l>Then stand abashed, when thou art forced to say:</l>
<l>A good man, through obscurest aspiration,</l>
<l>Has still an instinct of the one true way.</l>


<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Agreed! But &apos;tis a short probation.</l>
<l>About my bet I feel no trepidation.</l>
<l>If I fulfill my expectation,</l>
<l>You&apos;ll let me triumph with a swelling breast:</l>
<l>Dust shall he eat, and with a zest,</l>
<l>As did a certain snake, my near relation.</l>


<Speaker>THE LORD</Speaker>

<l>Therein thou&apos;rt free, according to thy merits;</l>
<l>The like of thee have never moved My hate.</l>
<l>Of all the bold, denying Spirits,</l>
<l>The waggish knave least trouble doth create.</l>
<l>Man&apos;s active nature, flagging, seeks too soon the level;</l>
<l>Unqualified repose he learns to crave;</l>
<l>Whence, willingly, the comrade him I gave,</l>
<l>Who works, excites, and must create, as Devil.</l>
<l>But ye, God&apos;s sons in love and duty,</l>
<l>Enjoy the rich, the ever-living Beauty!</l>
<l>Creative Power, that works eternal schemes,</l>
<l>Clasp you in bonds of love, relaxing never,</l>
<l>And what in wavering apparition gleams</l>
<l>Fix in its place with thoughts that stand forever!</l>


<l>(Heaven closes: the ARCHANGELS separate.)</l>


<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES (solus</Speaker>

<l>I like, at times, to hear The Ancient&apos;s word,</l>
<l>And have a care to be most civil:</l>
<l>It&apos;s really kind of such a noble Lord</l>
<l>So humanly to gossip with the Devil!</l>

<l>FIRST PART OF THE TRAGEDY</l>




<Scene> I </Scene>



<Speaker>NIGHT</Speaker>

<l>(A lofty-arched, narrow, Gothic chamber. FAUST, in a chair at his</l>
<l>desk, restless.)</l>


<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>I&apos;ve studied now Philosophy</l>
<l>And Jurisprudence, Medicine,—</l>
<l>And even, alas! Theology,—</l>
<l>From end to end, with labor keen;</l>
<l>And here, poor fool! with all my lore</l>
<l>I stand, no wiser than before:</l>
<l>I&apos;m Magister—yea, Doctor—hight,</l>
<l>And straight or cross-wise, wrong or right,</l>
<l>These ten years long, with many woes,</l>
<l>I&apos;ve led my scholars by the nose,—</l>
<l>And see, that nothing can be known!</l>
<l>That knowledge cuts me to the bone.</l>
<l>I&apos;m cleverer, true, than those fops of teachers,</l>
<l>Doctors and Magisters, Scribes and Preachers;</l>
<l>Neither scruples nor doubts come now to smite me,</l>
<l>Nor Hell nor Devil can longer affright me.</l>

<l>For this, all pleasure am I foregoing;</l>
<l>I do not pretend to aught worth knowing,</l>
<l>I do not pretend I could be a teacher</l>
<l>To help or convert a fellow-creature.</l>
<l>Then, too, I&apos;ve neither lands nor gold,</l>
<l>Nor the world&apos;s least pomp or honor hold—</l>
<l>No dog would endure such a curst existence!</l>
<l>Wherefore, from Magic I seek assistance,</l>
<l>That many a secret perchance I reach</l>
<l>Through spirit-power and spirit-speech,</l>
<l>And thus the bitter task forego</l>
<l>Of saying the things I do not know,—</l>
<l>That I may detect the inmost force</l>
<l>Which binds the world, and guides its course;</l>
<l>Its germs, productive powers explore,</l>
<l>And rummage in empty words no more!</l>

<l>O full and splendid Moon, whom I</l>
<l>Have, from this desk, seen climb the sky</l>
<l>So many a midnight,—would thy glow</l>
<l>For the last time beheld my woe!</l>
<l>Ever thine eye, most mournful friend,</l>
<l>O&apos;er books and papers saw me bend;</l>
<l>But would that I, on mountains grand,</l>
<l>Amid thy blessed light could stand,</l>
<l>With spirits through mountain-caverns hover,</l>
<l>Float in thy twilight the meadows over,</l>
<l>And, freed from the fumes of lore that swathe me,</l>
<l>To health in thy dewy fountains bathe me!</l>

<l>Ah, me! this dungeon still I see.</l>
<l>This drear, accursed masonry,</l>
<l>Where even the welcome daylight strains</l>
<l>But duskly through the painted panes.</l>
<l>Hemmed in by many a toppling heap</l>
<l>Of books worm-eaten, gray with dust,</l>
<l>Which to the vaulted ceiling creep,</l>
<l>Against the smoky paper thrust,—</l>
<l>With glasses, boxes, round me stacked,</l>
<l>And instruments together hurled,</l>
<l>Ancestral lumber, stuffed and packed—</l>
<l>Such is my world: and what a world!</l>

<l>And do I ask, wherefore my heart</l>
<l>Falters, oppressed with unknown needs?</l>
<l>Why some inexplicable smart</l>
<l>All movement of my life impedes?</l>
<l>Alas! in living Nature&apos;s stead,</l>
<l>Where God His human creature set,</l>
<l>In smoke and mould the fleshless dead</l>
<l>And bones of beasts surround me yet!</l>

<l>Fly! Up, and seek the broad, free land!</l>
<l>And this one Book of Mystery</l>
<l>From Nostradamus&apos; very hand,</l>
<l>Is&apos;t not sufficient company?</l>
<l>When I the starry courses know,</l>
<l>And Nature&apos;s wise instruction seek,</l>
<l>With light of power my soul shall glow,</l>
<l>As when to spirits spirits speak.</l>
<l>Tis vain, this empty brooding here,</l>
<l>Though guessed the holy symbols be:</l>
<l>Ye, Spirits, come—ye hover near—</l>
<l>Oh, if you hear me, answer me!</l>

<l>(He opens the Book, and perceives the sign of the Macrocosm.)</l>

<l>Ha! what a sudden rapture leaps from this</l>
<l>I view, through all my senses swiftly flowing!</l>
<l>I feel a youthful, holy, vital bliss</l>
<l>In every vein and fibre newly glowing.</l>
<l>Was it a God, who traced this sign,</l>
<l>With calm across my tumult stealing,</l>
<l>My troubled heart to joy unsealing,</l>
<l>With impulse, mystic and divine,</l>
<l>The powers of Nature here, around my path, revealing?</l>
<l>Am I a God?—so clear mine eyes!</l>
<l>In these pure features I behold</l>
<l>Creative Nature to my soul unfold.</l>
<l>What says the sage, now first I recognize:</l>
<l>&quot;The spirit-world no closures fasten;</l>
<l>Thy sense is shut, thy heart is dead:</l>
<l>Disciple, up! untiring, hasten</l>
<l>To bathe thy breast in morning-red!&quot;</l>

<l>(He contemplates the sign.)</l>

<l>How each the Whole its substance gives,</l>
<l>Each in the other works and lives!</l>
<l>Like heavenly forces rising and descending,</l>
<l>Their golden urns reciprocally lending,</l>
<l>With wings that winnow blessing</l>
<l>From Heaven through Earth I see them pressing,</l>
<l>Filling the All with harmony unceasing!</l>
<l>How grand a show! but, ah! a show alone.</l>
<l>Thee, boundless Nature, how make thee my own?</l>
<l>Where you, ye beasts? Founts of all Being, shining,</l>
<l>Whereon hang Heaven&apos;s and Earth&apos;s desire,</l>
<l>Whereto our withered hearts aspire,—</l>
<l>Ye flow, ye feed: and am I vainly pining?</l>

<l>(He turns the leaves impatiently, and perceives the sign of the</l>
<l>Earth-Spirit.)</l>

<l>How otherwise upon me works this sign!</l>
<l>Thou, Spirit of the Earth, art nearer:</l>
<l>Even now my powers are loftier, clearer;</l>
<l>I glow, as drunk with new-made wine:</l>
<l>New strength and heart to meet the world incite me,</l>
<l>The woe of earth, the bliss of earth, invite me,</l>
<l>And though the shock of storms may smite me,</l>
<l>No crash of shipwreck shall have power to fright me!</l>
<l>Clouds gather over me—</l>
<l>The moon conceals her light—</l>
<l>The lamp&apos;s extinguished!—</l>
<l>Mists rise,—red, angry rays are darting</l>
<l>Around my head!—There falls</l>
<l>A horror from the vaulted roof,</l>
<l>And seizes me!</l>
<l>I feel thy presence, Spirit I invoke!</l>
<l>Reveal thyself!</l>
<l>Ha! in my heart what rending stroke!</l>
<l>With new impulsion</l>
<l>My senses heave in this convulsion!</l>
<l>I feel thee draw my heart, absorb, exhaust me:</l>
<l>Thou must! thou must! and though my life it cost me!</l>

<l>(He seizes the book, and mysteriously pronounces the sign of</l>
<l>the Spirit. A ruddy flame flashes: the Spirit appears in</l>
<l>the flame.)</l>


<Speaker>SPIRIT</Speaker>

<l>Who calls me?</l>


<l>FAUST (with averted head)</l>

<l>Terrible to see!</l>

<Speaker>SPIRIT</Speaker>

<l>Me hast thou long with might attracted,</l>
<l>Long from my sphere thy food exacted,</l>
<l>And now—</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Woe! I endure not thee!</l>


<Speaker>SPIRIT</Speaker>

<l>To view me is thine aspiration,</l>
<l>My voice to hear, my countenance to see;</l>
<l>Thy powerful yearning moveth me,</l>
<l>Here am I!—what mean perturbation</l>
<l>Thee, superhuman, shakes? Thy soul&apos;s high calling, where?</l>
<l>Where is the breast, which from itself a world did bear,</l>
<l>And shaped and cherished—which with joy expanded,</l>
<l>To be our peer, with us, the Spirits, banded?</l>
<l>Where art thou, Faust, whose voice has pierced to me,</l>
<l>Who towards me pressed with all thine energy?</l>
<l>He art thou, who, my presence breathing, seeing,</l>
<l>Trembles through all the depths of being,</l>
<l>A writhing worm, a terror-stricken form?</l>


<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Thee, form of flame, shall I then fear?</l>
<l>Yes, I am Faust: I am thy peer!</l>


<Speaker>SPIRIT</Speaker>

<l>In the tides of Life, in Action&apos;s storm,</l>
<l>A fluctuant wave,</l>
<l>A shuttle free,</l>
<l>Birth and the Grave,</l>
<l>An eternal sea,</l>
<l>A weaving, flowing</l>
<l>Life, all-glowing,</l>
<l>Thus at Time&apos;s humming loom &apos;tis my hand prepares</l>
<l>The garment of Life which the Deity wears!</l>


<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Thou, who around the wide world wendest,</l>
<l>Thou busy Spirit, how near I feel to thee!</l>


<Speaker>SPIRIT</Speaker>

<l>Thou&apos;rt like the Spirit which thou comprehendest,</l>
<l>Not me!</l>

<Speaker>(Disappears</Speaker>


<Speaker>FAUST (overwhelmed</Speaker>

<l>Not thee!</l>
<l>Whom then?</l>
<l>I, image of the Godhead!</l>
<l>Not even like thee!</l>

<l>(A knock).</l>

<l>O Death!—I know it—&apos;tis my Famulus!</l>
<l>My fairest luck finds no fruition:</l>
<l>In all the fullness of my vision</l>
<l>The soulless sneak disturbs me thus!</l>

<l>(Enter WAGNER, in dressing-gown and night-cap, a lamp in</l>
<l>his hand. FAUST turns impatiently.)</l>


<Speaker>WAGNER</Speaker>

<l>Pardon, I heard your declamation;</l>
<l>&apos;Twas sure an old Greek tragedy you read?</l>
<l>In such an art I crave some preparation,</l>
<l>Since now it stands one in good stead.</l>
<l>I&apos;ve often heard it said, a preacher</l>
<l>Might learn, with a comedian for a teacher.</l>


<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Yes, when the priest comedian is by nature,</l>
<l>As haply now and then the case may be.</l>


<Speaker>WAGNER</Speaker>

<l>Ah, when one studies thus, a prisoned creature,</l>
<l>That scarce the world on holidays can see,—</l>
<l>Scarce through a glass, by rare occasion,</l>
<l>How shall one lead it by persuasion?</l>


<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>You&apos;ll ne&apos;er attain it, save you know the feeling,</l>
<l>Save from the soul it rises clear,</l>
<l>Serene in primal strength, compelling</l>
<l>The hearts and minds of all who hear.</l>
<l>You sit forever gluing, patching;</l>
<l>You cook the scraps from others&apos; fare;</l>
<l>And from your heap of ashes hatching</l>
<l>A starveling flame, ye blow it bare!</l>
<l>Take children&apos;s, monkeys&apos; gaze admiring,</l>
<l>If such your taste, and be content;</l>
<l>But ne&apos;er from heart to heart you&apos;ll speak inspiring,</l>
<l>Save your own heart is eloquent!</l>


<Speaker>WAGNER</Speaker>

<l>Yet through delivery orators succeed;</l>
<l>I feel that I am far behind, indeed.</l>


<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Seek thou the honest recompense!</l>
<l>Beware, a tinkling fool to be!</l>
<l>With little art, clear wit and sense</l>
<l>Suggest their own delivery;</l>
<l>And if thou&apos;rt moved to speak in earnest,</l>
<l>What need, that after words thou yearnest?</l>
<l>Yes, your discourses, with their glittering show,</l>
<l>Where ye for men twist shredded thought like paper,</l>
<l>Are unrefreshing as the winds that blow</l>
<l>The rustling leaves through chill autumnal vapor!</l>


<Speaker>WAGNER</Speaker>

<l>Ah, God! but Art is long,</l>
<l>And Life, alas! is fleeting.</l>
<l>And oft, with zeal my critic-duties meeting,</l>
<l>In head and breast there&apos;s something wrong.</l>

<l>How hard it is to compass the assistance</l>
<l>Whereby one rises to the source!</l>
<l>And, haply, ere one travels half the course</l>
<l>Must the poor devil quit existence.</l>


<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Is parchment, then, the holy fount before thee,</l>
<l>A draught wherefrom thy thirst forever slakes?</l>
<l>No true refreshment can restore thee,</l>
<l>Save what from thine own soul spontaneous breaks.</l>


<Speaker>WAGNER</Speaker>

<l>Pardon! a great delight is granted</l>
<l>When, in the spirit of the ages planted,</l>
<l>We mark how, ere our times, a sage has thought,</l>
<l>And then, how far his work, and grandly, we have brought.</l>


<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>O yes, up to the stars at last!</l>
<l>Listen, my friend: the ages that are past</l>
<l>Are now a book with seven seals protected:</l>
<l>What you the Spirit of the Ages call</l>
<l>Is nothing but the spirit of you all,</l>
<l>Wherein the Ages are reflected.</l>
<l>So, oftentimes, you miserably mar it!</l>
<l>At the first glance who sees it runs away.</l>
<l>An offal-barrel and a lumber-garret,</l>
<l>Or, at the best, a Punch-and-Judy play,</l>
<l>With maxims most pragmatical and hitting,</l>
<l>As in the mouths of puppets are befitting!</l>


<Speaker>WAGNER</Speaker>

<l>But then, the world—the human heart and brain!</l>
<l>Of these one covets some slight apprehension.</l>


<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Yes, of the kind which men attain!</l>
<l>Who dares the child&apos;s true name in public mention?</l>
<l>The few, who thereof something really learned,</l>
<l>Unwisely frank, with hearts that spurned concealing,</l>
<l>And to the mob laid bare each thought and feeling,</l>
<l>Have evermore been crucified and burned.</l>
<l>I pray you, Friend, &apos;tis now the dead of night;</l>
<l>Our converse here must be suspended.</l>


<Speaker>WAGNER</Speaker>

<l>I would have shared your watches with delight,</l>
<l>That so our learned talk might be extended.</l>
<l>To-morrow, though, I&apos;ll ask, in Easter leisure,</l>
<l>This and the other question, at your pleasure.</l>
<l>Most zealously I seek for erudition:</l>
<l>Much do I know—but to know all is my ambition.</l>

<stage>[Exit</stage>


<Speaker>FAUST (solus</Speaker>

<l>That brain, alone, not loses hope, whose choice is</l>
<l>To stick in shallow trash forevermore,—</l>
<l>Which digs with eager hand for buried ore,</l>
<l>And, when it finds an angle-worm, rejoices!</l>

<l>Dare such a human voice disturb the flow,</l>
<l>Around me here, of spirit-presence fullest?</l>
<l>And yet, this once my thanks I owe</l>
<l>To thee, of all earth&apos;s sons the poorest, dullest!</l>
<l>For thou hast torn me from that desperate state</l>
<l>Which threatened soon to overwhelm my senses:</l>
<l>The apparition was so giant-great,</l>
<l>It dwarfed and withered all my soul&apos;s pretences!</l>

<l>I, image of the Godhead, who began—</l>
<l>Deeming Eternal Truth secure in nearness—</l>
<l>Ye choirs, have ye begun the sweet, consoling chant,</l>
<l>Which, through the night of Death, the angels ministrant</l>
<l>Sang, God&apos;s new Covenant repeating?</l>


<l>CHORUS OF WOMEN</l>

<l>With spices and precious</l>
<l>Balm, we arrayed him;</l>
<l>Faithful and gracious,</l>
<l>We tenderly laid him:</l>
<l>Linen to bind him</l>
<l>Cleanlily wound we:</l>
<l>Ah! when we would find him,</l>
<l>Christ no more found we!</l>


<l>CHORUS OF ANGELS</l>

<l>Christ is ascended!</l>
<l>Bliss hath invested him,—</l>
<l>Woes that molested him,</l>
<l>Trials that tested him,</l>
<l>Gloriously ended!</l>


<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Why, here in dust, entice me with your spell,</l>
<l>Ye gentle, powerful sounds of Heaven?</l>
<l>Peal rather there, where tender natures dwell.</l>
<l>Your messages I hear, but faith has not been given;</l>
<l>The dearest child of Faith is Miracle.</l>
<l>I venture not to soar to yonder regions</l>
<l>Whence the glad tidings hither float;</l>
<l>And yet, from childhood up familiar with the note,</l>
<l>To Life it now renews the old allegiance.</l>
<l>Once Heavenly Love sent down a burning kiss</l>
<l>Upon my brow, in Sabbath silence holy;</l>
<l>And, filled with mystic presage, chimed the church-bell slowly,</l>
<l>And prayer dissolved me in a fervent bliss.</l>
<l>A sweet, uncomprehended yearning</l>
<l>Drove forth my feet through woods and meadows free,</l>
<l>And while a thousand tears were burning,</l>
<l>I felt a world arise for me.</l>
<l>These chants, to youth and all its sports appealing,</l>
<l>Proclaimed the Spring&apos;s rejoicing holiday;</l>
<l>And Memory holds me now, with childish feeling,</l>
<l>Back from the last, the solemn way.</l>
<l>Sound on, ye hymns of Heaven, so sweet and mild!</l>
<l>My tears gush forth: the Earth takes back her child!</l>


<l>CHORUS OF DISCIPLES</l>

<l>Has He, victoriously,</l>
<l>Burst from the vaulted</l>
<l>Grave, and all-gloriously</l>
<l>Now sits exalted?</l>
<l>Is He, in glow of birth,</l>
<l>Rapture creative near?</l>
<l>Ah! to the woe of earth</l>
<l>Still are we native here.</l>
<l>We, his aspiring</l>
<l>Followers, Him we miss;</l>
<l>Weeping, desiring,</l>
<l>Master, Thy bliss!</l>
<l>CHORUS OF ANGELS</l>

<l>Christ is arisen,</l>
<l>Out of Corruption&apos;s womb:</l>
<l>Burst ye the prison,</l>
<l>Break from your gloom!</l>
<l>Praising and pleading him,</l>
<l>Lovingly needing him,</l>
<l>Brotherly feeding him,</l>
<l>Preaching and speeding him,</l>
<l>Blessing, succeeding Him,</l>
<l>Thus is the Master near,—</l>
<l>Thus is He here!</l>

<Scene> II </Scene>
<l>BEFORE THE CITY-GATE</l>

<l>(Pedestrians of all kinds come forth.)</l>

<Speaker>SEVERAL APPRENTICES</Speaker>

<l>Why do you go that way?</l>

<Speaker>OTHERS</Speaker>

<l>We&apos;re for the Hunters&apos; lodge, to-day.</l>

<Speaker>THE FIRST</Speaker>

<l>We&apos;ll saunter to the Mill, in yonder hollow.</l>

<Speaker>AN APPRENTICE</Speaker>

<l>Go to the River Tavern, I should say.</l>

<Speaker>SECOND APPRENTICE</Speaker>

<l>But then, it&apos;s not a pleasant way.</l>

<Speaker>THE OTHERS</Speaker>

<l>And what will you?</l>

<Speaker>A THIRD</Speaker>

<l>As goes the crowd, I follow.</l>
<Speaker>A FOURTH</Speaker>

<l>Come up to Burgdorf? There you&apos;ll find good cheer,</l>
<l>The finest lasses and the best of beer,</l>
<l>And jolly rows and squabbles, trust me!</l>

<Speaker>A FIFTH</Speaker>

<l>You swaggering fellow, is your hide</l>
<l>A third time itching to be tried?</l>
<l>I won&apos;t go there, your jolly rows disgust me!</l>

<Speaker>SERVANT-GIRL</Speaker>

<l>No,—no! I&apos;ll turn and go to town again.</l>

<Speaker>ANOTHER</Speaker>

<l>We&apos;ll surely find him by those poplars yonder.</l>

<Speaker>THE FIRST</Speaker>

<l>That&apos;s no great luck for me, &apos;tis plain.</l>
<l>You&apos;ll have him, when and where you wander:</l>
<l>His partner in the dance you&apos;ll be,—</l>
<l>But what is all your fun to me?</l>

<Speaker>THE OTHER</Speaker>

<l>He&apos;s surely not alone to-day:</l>
<l>He&apos;ll be with Curly-head, I heard him say.</l>

<Speaker>A STUDENT</Speaker>

<l>Deuce! how they step, the buxom wenches!</l>
<l>Come, Brother! we must see them to the benches.</l>
<l>A strong, old beer, a pipe that stings and bites,</l>
<l>A girl in Sunday clothes,—these three are my delights.</l>

<Speaker>CITIZEN&apos;S DAUGHTER</Speaker>

<l>Just see those handsome fellows, there!</l>
<l>It&apos;s really shameful, I declare;—</l>
<l>To follow servant-girls, when they</l>
<l>Might have the most genteel society to-day!</l>

<l>SECOND STUDENT (to the First)</l>

<l>Not quite so fast! Two others come behind,—</l>
<l>Those, dressed so prettily and neatly.</l>
<l>My neighbor&apos;s one of them, I find,</l>
<l>A girl that takes my heart, completely.</l>
<l>They go their way with looks demure,</l>
<l>But they&apos;ll accept us, after all, I&apos;m sure.</l>

<Speaker>THE FIRST</Speaker>

<l>No, Brother! not for me their formal ways.</l>
<l>Quick! lest our game escape us in the press:</l>
<l>The hand that wields the broom on Saturdays</l>
<l>Will best, on Sundays, fondle and caress.</l>

<Speaker>CITIZEN</Speaker>

<l>He suits me not at all, our new-made Burgomaster!</l>
<l>Since he&apos;s installed, his arrogance grows faster.</l>
<l>How has he helped the town, I say?</l>
<l>Things worsen,—what improvement names he?</l>
<l>Obedience, more than ever, claims he,</l>
<l>And more than ever we must pay!</l>

<Speaker>BEGGAR (sings</Speaker>

<l>Good gentlemen and lovely ladies,</l>
<l>So red of cheek and fine of dress,</l>
<l>Behold, how needful here your aid is,</l>
<l>And see and lighten my distress!</l>
<l>Let me not vainly sing my ditty;</l>
<l>He&apos;s only glad who gives away:</l>
<l>A holiday, that shows your pity,</l>
<l>Shall be for me a harvest-day!</l>
<Speaker>ANOTHER CITIZEN</Speaker>

<l>On Sundays, holidays, there&apos;s naught I take delight in,</l>
<l>Like gossiping of war, and war&apos;s array,</l>
<l>When down in Turkey, far away,</l>
<l>The foreign people are a-fighting.</l>
<l>One at the window sits, with glass and friends,</l>
<l>And sees all sorts of ships go down the river gliding:</l>
<l>And blesses then, as home he wends</l>
<l>At night, our times of peace abiding.</l>

<Speaker>THIRD CITIZEN</Speaker>

<l>Yes, Neighbor! that&apos;s my notion, too:</l>
<l>Why, let them break their heads, let loose their passions,</l>
<l>And mix things madly through and through,</l>
<l>So, here, we keep our good old fashions!</l>

<l>OLD WOMAN (to the Citizen&apos;s Daughter)</l>

<l>Dear me, how fine! So handsome, and so young!</l>
<l>Who wouldn&apos;t lose his heart, that met you?</l>
<l>Don&apos;t be so proud! I&apos;ll hold my tongue,</l>
<l>And what you&apos;d like I&apos;ll undertake to get you.</l>

<Speaker>CITIZEN&apos;S DAUGHTER</Speaker>

<l>Come, Agatha! I shun the witch&apos;s sight</l>
<l>Before folks, lest there be misgiving:</l>
<l>&apos;Tis true, she showed me, on Saint Andrew&apos;s Night,</l>
<l>My future sweetheart, just as he were living.</l>

<Speaker>THE OTHER</Speaker>

<l>She showed me mine, in crystal clear,</l>
<l>With several wild young blades, a soldier-lover:</l>
<l>I seek him everywhere, I pry and peer,</l>
<l>And yet, somehow, his face I can&apos;t discover.</l>

<Speaker>SOLDIERS</Speaker>

<l>Castles, with lofty</l>
<l>Ramparts and towers,</l>
<l>Maidens disdainful</l>
<l>In Beauty&apos;s array,</l>
<l>Both shall be ours!</l>
<l>Bold is the venture,</l>
<l>Splendid the pay!</l>
<l>Lads, let the trumpets</l>
<l>For us be suing,—</l>
<l>Calling to pleasure,</l>
<l>Calling to ruin.</l>
<l>Stormy our life is;</l>
<l>Such is its boon!</l>
<l>Maidens and castles</l>
<l>Capitulate soon.</l>
<l>Bold is the venture,</l>
<l>Splendid the pay!</l>
<l>And the soldiers go marching,</l>
<l>Marching away!</l>
<l>FAUST AND WAGNER</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Released from ice are brook and river</l>
<l>By the quickening glance of the gracious Spring;</l>
<l>The colors of hope to the valley cling,</l>
<l>And weak old Winter himself must shiver,</l>
<l>Withdrawn to the mountains, a crownless king:</l>
<l>Whence, ever retreating, he sends again</l>
<l>Impotent showers of sleet that darkle</l>
<l>In belts across the green o&apos; the plain.</l>
<l>But the sun will permit no white to sparkle;</l>
<l>Everywhere form in development moveth;</l>
<l>He will brighten the world with the tints he loveth,</l>
<l>And, lacking blossoms, blue, yellow, and red,</l>
<l>He takes these gaudy people instead.</l>
<l>Turn thee about, and from this height</l>
<l>Back on the town direct thy sight.</l>
<l>Out of the hollow, gloomy gate,</l>
<l>The motley throngs come forth elate:</l>
<l>Each will the joy of the sunshine hoard,</l>
<l>To honor the Day of the Risen Lord!</l>
<l>They feel, themselves, their resurrection:</l>
<l>From the low, dark rooms, scarce habitable;</l>
<l>From the bonds of Work, from Trade&apos;s restriction;</l>
<l>From the pressing weight of roof and gable;</l>
<l>From the narrow, crushing streets and alleys;</l>
<l>From the churches&apos; solemn and reverend night,</l>
<l>All come forth to the cheerful light.</l>
<l>How lively, see! the multitude sallies,</l>
<l>Scattering through gardens and fields remote,</l>
<l>While over the river, that broadly dallies,</l>
<l>Dances so many a festive boat;</l>
<l>And overladen, nigh to sinking,</l>
<l>The last full wherry takes the stream.</l>
<l>Yonder afar, from the hill-paths blinking,</l>
<l>Their clothes are colors that softly gleam.</l>
<l>I hear the noise of the village, even;</l>
<l>Here is the People&apos;s proper Heaven;</l>
<l>Here high and low contented see!</l>
<l>Here I am Man,—dare man to be!</l>

<Speaker>WAGNER</Speaker>

<l>To stroll with you, Sir Doctor, flatters;</l>
<l>&apos;Tis honor, profit, unto me.</l>
<l>But I, alone, would shun these shallow matters,</l>
<l>Since all that&apos;s coarse provokes my enmity.</l>
<l>This fiddling, shouting, ten-pin rolling</l>
<l>I hate,—these noises of the throng:</l>
<l>They rave, as Satan were their sports controlling.</l>
<l>And call it mirth, and call it song!</l>

<l>PEASANTS, UNDER THE LINDEN-TREE</l>
<l>(Dance and Song.)</l>
<l>All for the dance the shepherd dressed,</l>
<l>In ribbons, wreath, and gayest vest</l>
<l>Himself with care arraying:</l>
<l>Around the linden lass and lad</l>
<l>Already footed it like mad:</l>
<l>Hurrah! hurrah!</l>
<l>Hurrah—tarara-la!</l>
<l>The fiddle-bow was playing.</l>

<l>He broke the ranks, no whit afraid,</l>
<l>And with his elbow punched a maid,</l>
<l>Who stood, the dance surveying:</l>
<l>The buxom wench, she turned and said:</l>
<l>&quot;Now, you I call a stupid-head!&quot;</l>
<l>Hurrah! hurrah!</l>
<l>Hurrah—tarara-la!</l>
<l>&quot;Be decent while you&apos;re staying!&quot;</l>

<l>Then round the circle went their flight,</l>
<l>They danced to left, they danced to right:</l>
<l>Their kirtles all were playing.</l>
<l>They first grew red, and then grew warm,</l>
<l>And rested, panting, arm in arm,—</l>
<l>Hurrah! hurrah!</l>
<l>Hurrah—tarara-la!</l>
<l>And hips and elbows straying.</l>

<l>Now, don&apos;t be so familiar here!</l>
<l>How many a one has fooled his dear,</l>
<l>Waylaying and betraying!</l>

<l>And yet, he coaxed her soon aside,</l>
<l>And round the linden sounded wide.</l>
<l>Hurrah! hurrah!</l>
<l>Hurrah—tarara-la!</l>
<l>And the fiddle-bow was playing.</l>
<Speaker>OLD PEASANT</Speaker>

<l>Sir Doctor, it is good of you,</l>
<l>That thus you condescend, to-day,</l>
<l>Among this crowd of merry folk,</l>
<l>A highly-learned man, to stray.</l>
<l>Then also take the finest can,</l>
<l>We fill with fresh wine, for your sake:</l>
<l>I offer it, and humbly wish</l>
<l>That not alone your thirst is slake,—</l>
<l>That, as the drops below its brink,</l>
<l>So many days of life you drink!</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>I take the cup you kindly reach,</l>
<l>With thanks and health to all and each.</l>

<l>(The People gather in a circle about him.)</l>

<Speaker>OLD PEASANT</Speaker>

<l>In truth, &apos;tis well and fitly timed,</l>
<l>That now our day of joy you share,</l>
<l>Who heretofore, in evil days,</l>
<l>Gave us so much of helping care.</l>
<l>Still many a man stands living here,</l>
<l>Saved by your father&apos;s skillful hand,</l>
<l>That snatched him from the fever&apos;s rage</l>
<l>And stayed the plague in all the land.</l>
<l>Then also you, though but a youth,</l>
<l>Went into every house of pain:</l>
<l>Many the corpses carried forth,</l>
<l>But you in health came out again.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>No test or trial you evaded:</l>
<l>A Helping God the helper aided.</l>

<Speaker>ALL</Speaker>

<l>Health to the man, so skilled and tried.</l>
<l>That for our help he long may abide!</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>To Him above bow down, my friends,</l>
<l>Who teaches help, and succor sends!</l>

<l>(He goes on with WAGNER.)</l>

<Speaker>WAGNER</Speaker>

<l>With what a feeling, thou great man, must thou</l>
<l>Receive the people&apos;s honest veneration!</l>
<l>How lucky he, whose gifts his station</l>
<l>With such advantages endow!</l>
<l>Thou&apos;rt shown to all the younger generation:</l>
<l>Each asks, and presses near to gaze;</l>
<l>The fiddle stops, the dance delays.</l>
<l>Thou goest, they stand in rows to see,</l>
<l>And all the caps are lifted high;</l>
<l>A little more, and they would bend the knee</l>
<l>As if the Holy Host came by.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>A few more steps ascend, as far as yonder stone!—</l>
<l>Here from our wandering will we rest contented.</l>
<l>Here, lost in thought, I&apos;ve lingered oft alone,</l>
<l>When foolish fasts and prayers my life tormented.</l>
<l>Here, rich in hope and firm in faith,</l>
<l>With tears, wrung hands and sighs, I&apos;ve striven,</l>
<l>The end of that far-spreading death</l>
<l>Entreating from the Lord of Heaven!</l>
<l>Now like contempt the crowd&apos;s applauses seem:</l>
<l>Couldst thou but read, within mine inmost spirit,</l>
<l>How little now I deem,</l>
<l>That sire or son such praises merit!</l>
<l>My father&apos;s was a sombre, brooding brain,</l>
<l>Which through the holy spheres of Nature groped and wandered,</l>
<l>And honestly, in his own fashion, pondered</l>
<l>With labor whimsical, and pain:</l>
<l>Who, in his dusky work-shop bending,</l>
<l>With proved adepts in company,</l>
<l>Made, from his recipes unending,</l>
<l>Opposing substances agree.</l>
<l>There was a Lion red, a wooer daring,</l>
<l>Within the Lily&apos;s tepid bath espoused,</l>
<l>And both, tormented then by flame unsparing,</l>
<l>By turns in either bridal chamber housed.</l>
<l>If then appeared, with colors splendid,</l>
<l>The young Queen in her crystal shell,</l>
<l>This was the medicine—the patients&apos; woes soon ended,</l>
<l>And none demanded: who got well?</l>
<l>Thus we, our hellish boluses compounding,</l>
<l>Among these vales and hills surrounding,</l>
<l>Worse than the pestilence, have passed.</l>
<l>Thousands were done to death from poison of my giving;</l>
<l>And I must hear, by all the living,</l>
<l>The shameless murderers praised at last!</l>

<Speaker>WAGNER</Speaker>

<l>Why, therefore, yield to such depression?</l>
<l>A good man does his honest share</l>
<l>In exercising, with the strictest care,</l>
<l>The art bequeathed to his possession!</l>
<l>Dost thou thy father honor, as a youth?</l>
<l>Then may his teaching cheerfully impel thee:</l>
<l>Dost thou, as man, increase the stores of truth?</l>
<l>Then may thine own son afterwards excel thee.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>O happy he, who still renews</l>
<l>The hope, from Error&apos;s deeps to rise forever!</l>
<l>That which one does not know, one needs to use;</l>
<l>And what one knows, one uses never.</l>
<l>But let us not, by such despondence, so</l>
<l>The fortune of this hour embitter!</l>
<l>Mark how, beneath the evening sunlight&apos;s glow,</l>
<l>The green-embosomed houses glitter!</l>
<l>The glow retreats, done is the day of toil;</l>
<l>It yonder hastes, new fields of life exploring;</l>
<l>Ah, that no wing can lift me from the soil,</l>
<l>Upon its track to follow, follow soaring!</l>
<l>Then would I see eternal Evening gild</l>
<l>The silent world beneath me glowing,</l>
<l>On fire each mountain-peak, with peace each valley filled,</l>
<l>The silver brook to golden rivers flowing.</l>
<l>The mountain-chain, with all its gorges deep,</l>
<l>Would then no more impede my godlike motion;</l>
<l>And now before mine eyes expands the ocean</l>
<l>With all its bays, in shining sleep!</l>
<l>Yet, finally, the weary god is sinking;</l>
<l>The new-born impulse fires my mind,—</l>
<l>I hasten on, his beams eternal drinking,</l>
<l>The Day before me and the Night behind,</l>
<l>Above me heaven unfurled, the floor of waves beneath me,—</l>
<l>A glorious dream! though now the glories fade.</l>
<l>Alas! the wings that lift the mind no aid</l>
<l>Of wings to lift the body can bequeath me.</l>
<l>Yet in each soul is born the pleasure</l>
<l>Of yearning onward, upward and away,</l>
<l>When o&apos;er our heads, lost in the vaulted azure,</l>
<l>The lark sends down his flickering lay,—</l>
<l>When over crags and piny highlands</l>
<l>The poising eagle slowly soars,</l>
<l>And over plains and lakes and islands</l>
<l>The crane sails by to other shores.</l>

<Speaker>WAGNER</Speaker>

<l>I&apos;ve had, myself, at times, some odd caprices,</l>
<l>But never yet such impulse felt, as this is.</l>
<l>One soon fatigues, on woods and fields to look,</l>
<l>Nor would I beg the bird his wing to spare us:</l>
<l>How otherwise the mental raptures bear us</l>
<l>From page to page, from book to book!</l>
<l>Then winter nights take loveliness untold,</l>
<l>As warmer life in every limb had crowned you;</l>
<l>And when your hands unroll some parchment rare and old,</l>
<l>All Heaven descends, and opens bright around you!</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>One impulse art thou conscious of, at best;</l>
<l>O, never seek to know the other!</l>
<l>Two souls, alas! reside within my breast,</l>
<l>And each withdraws from, and repels, its brother.</l>
<l>One with tenacious organs holds in love</l>
<l>And clinging lust the world in its embraces;</l>
<l>The other strongly sweeps, this dust above,</l>
<l>Into the high ancestral spaces.</l>
<l>If there be airy spirits near,</l>
<l>&apos;Twixt Heaven and Earth on potent errands fleeing,</l>
<l>Let them drop down the golden atmosphere,</l>
<l>And bear me forth to new and varied being!</l>
<l>Yea, if a magic mantle once were mine,</l>
<l>To waft me o&apos;er the world at pleasure,</l>
<l>I would not for the costliest stores of treasure—</l>
<l>Not for a monarch&apos;s robe—the gift resign.</l>

<Speaker>WAGNER</Speaker>

<l>Invoke not thus the well-known throng,</l>
<l>Which through the firmament diffused is faring,</l>
<l>And danger thousand-fold, our race to wrong.</l>
<l>In every quarter is preparing.</l>
<l>Swift from the North the spirit-fangs so sharp</l>
<l>Sweep down, and with their barbéd points assail you;</l>
<l>Then from the East they come, to dry and warp</l>
<l>Your lungs, till breath and being fail you:</l>
<l>If from the Desert sendeth them the South,</l>
<l>With fire on fire your throbbing forehead crowning,</l>
<l>The West leads on a host, to cure the drouth</l>
<l>Only when meadow, field, and you are drowning.</l>
<l>They gladly hearken, prompt for injury,—</l>
<l>Gladly obey, because they gladly cheat us;</l>
<l>From Heaven they represent themselves to be,</l>
<l>And lisp like angels, when with lies they meet us.</l>
<l>But, let us go! &apos;Tis gray and dusky all:</l>
<l>The air is cold, the vapors fall.</l>
<l>At night, one learns his house to prize:—</l>
<l>Why stand you thus, with such astonished eyes?</l>
<l>What, in the twilight, can your mind so trouble?</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Seest thou the black dog coursing there, through corn and</l>
<Speaker>stubble</Speaker>

<Speaker>WAGNER</Speaker>

<l>Long since: yet deemed him not important in the least.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Inspect him close: for what tak&apos;st thou the beast?</l>

<Speaker>WAGNER</Speaker>

<l>Why, for a poodle who has lost his master,</l>
<l>And scents about, his track to find.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Seest thou the spiral circles, narrowing faster,</l>
<l>Which he, approaching, round us seems to wind?</l>
<l>A streaming trail of fire, if I see rightly,</l>
<l>Follows his path of mystery.</l>

<Speaker>WAGNER</Speaker>

<l>It may be that your eyes deceive you slightly;</l>
<l>Naught but a plain black poodle do I see.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>It seems to me that with enchanted cunning</l>
<l>He snares our feet, some future chain to bind.</l>

<Speaker>WAGNER</Speaker>

<l>I see him timidly, in doubt, around us running,</l>
<l>Since, in his master&apos;s stead, two strangers doth he find.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>The circle narrows: he is near!</l>

<Speaker>WAGNER</Speaker>

<l>A dog thou seest, and not a phantom, here!</l>
<l>Behold him stop—upon his belly crawl—His</l>
<l>tail set wagging: canine habits, all!</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Come, follow us! Come here, at least!</l>

<Speaker>WAGNER</Speaker>

<l>&apos;Tis the absurdest, drollest beast.</l>
<l>Stand still, and you will see him wait;</l>
<l>Address him, and he gambols straight;</l>
<l>If something&apos;s lost, he&apos;ll quickly bring it,—</l>
<l>Your cane, if in the stream you fling it.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>No doubt you&apos;re right: no trace of mind, I own,</l>
<l>Is in the beast: I see but drill, alone.</l>

<Speaker>WAGNER</Speaker>

<l>The dog, when he&apos;s well educated,</l>
<l>Is by the wisest tolerated.</l>
<l>Yes, he deserves your favor thoroughly,—</l>
<l>The clever scholar of the students, he!</l>

<l>(They pass in the city-gate.)</l>

<Scene> III </Scene>
<Speaker>THE STUDY</Speaker>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>(Entering, with the poodle.)</l>

<l>Behind me, field and meadow sleeping,</l>
<l>I leave in deep, prophetic night,</l>
<l>Within whose dread and holy keeping</l>
<l>The better soul awakes to light.</l>
<l>The wild desires no longer win us,</l>
<l>The deeds of passion cease to chain;</l>
<l>The love of Man revives within us,</l>
<l>The love of God revives again.</l>
<l>Be still, thou poodle; make not such racket and riot!</l>
<l>Why at the threshold wilt snuffing be?</l>
<l>Behind the stove repose thee in quiet!</l>
<l>My softest cushion I give to thee.</l>
<l>As thou, up yonder, with running and leaping</l>
<l>Amused us hast, on the mountain&apos;s crest,</l>
<l>So now I take thee into my keeping,</l>
<l>A welcome, but also a silent, guest.</l>

<l>Ah, when, within our narrow chamber</l>
<l>The lamp with friendly lustre glows,</l>
<l>Flames in the breast each faded ember,</l>
<l>And in the heart, itself that knows.</l>
<l>Then Hope again lends sweet assistance,</l>
<l>And Reason then resumes her speech:</l>
<l>One yearns, the rivers of existence,</l>
<l>The very founts of Life, to reach.</l>
<l>Snarl not, poodle! To the sound that rises,</l>
<l>The sacred tones that my soul embrace,</l>
<l>This bestial noise is out of place.</l>
<l>We are used to see, that Man despises</l>
<l>What he never comprehends,</l>
<l>And the Good and the Beautiful vilipends,</l>
<l>Finding them often hard to measure:</l>
<l>Will the dog, like man, snarl his displeasure?</l>

<l>But ah! I feel, though will thereto be stronger,</l>
<l>Contentment flows from out my breast no longer.</l>
<l>Why must the stream so soon run dry and fail us,</l>
<l>And burning thirst again assail us?</l>
<l>Therein I&apos;ve borne so much probation!</l>
<l>And yet, this want may be supplied us;</l>
<l>We call the Supernatural to guide us;</l>
<l>We pine and thirst for Revelation,</l>
<l>Which nowhere worthier is, more nobly sent,</l>
<l>Than here, in our New Testament.</l>
<l>I feel impelled, its meaning to determine,—</l>
<l>With honest purpose, once for all,</l>
<l>The hallowed Original</l>
<l>To change to my beloved German.</l>
<l>(He opens a volume, and commences.)</l>
<l>&apos;Tis written: &quot;In the Beginning was the Word.&quot;</l>
<l>Here am I balked: who, now can help afford?</l>
<l>The Word?—impossible so high to rate it;</l>
<l>And otherwise must I translate it.</l>
<l>If by the Spirit I am truly taught.</l>
<l>Then thus: &quot;In the Beginning was the Thought&quot;</l>
<l>This first line let me weigh completely,</l>
<l>Lest my impatient pen proceed too fleetly.</l>
<l>Is it the Thought which works, creates, indeed?</l>
<l>&quot;In the Beginning was the Power,&quot; I read.</l>
<l>Yet, as I write, a warning is suggested,</l>
<l>That I the sense may not have fairly tested.</l>
<l>The Spirit aids me: now I see the light!</l>
<l>&quot;In the Beginning was the Act,&quot; I write.</l>

<l>If I must share my chamber with thee,</l>
<l>Poodle, stop that howling, prithee!</l>
<l>Cease to bark and bellow!</l>
<l>Such a noisy, disturbing fellow</l>
<l>I&apos;ll no longer suffer near me.</l>
<l>One of us, dost hear me!</l>
<l>Must leave, I fear me.</l>
<l>No longer guest-right I bestow;</l>
<l>The door is open, art free to go.</l>
<l>But what do I see in the creature?</l>
<l>Is that in the course of nature?</l>
<l>Is&apos;t actual fact? or Fancy&apos;s shows?</l>
<l>How long and broad my poodle grows!</l>
<l>He rises mightily:</l>
<l>A canine form that cannot be!</l>
<l>What a spectre I&apos;ve harbored thus!</l>
<l>He resembles a hippopotamus,</l>
<l>With fiery eyes, teeth terrible to see:</l>
<l>O, now am I sure of thee!</l>
<l>For all of thy half-hellish brood</l>
<l>The Key of Solomon is good.</l>

<l>SPIRITS (in the corridor)</l>

<l>Some one, within, is caught!</l>
<l>Stay without, follow him not!</l>
<l>Like the fox in a snare,</l>
<l>Quakes the old hell-lynx there.</l>
<l>Take heed—look about!</l>
<l>Back and forth hover,</l>
<l>Under and over,</l>
<l>And he&apos;ll work himself out.</l>
<l>If your aid avail him,</l>
<l>Let it not fail him;</l>
<l>For he, without measure,</l>
<l>Has wrought for our pleasure.</l>
<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>First, to encounter the beast,</l>
<l>The Words of the Four be addressed:</l>
<l>Salamander, shine glorious!</l>
<l>Wave, Undine, as bidden!</l>
<l>Sylph, be thou hidden!</l>
<l>Gnome, be laborious!</l>
<l>Who knows not their sense</l>
<l>(These elements),—</l>
<l>Their properties</l>
<l>And power not sees,—</l>
<l>No mastery he inherits</l>
<l>Over the Spirits.</l>

<l>Vanish in flaming ether,</l>
<Speaker>Salamander</Speaker>
<l>Flow foamingly together,</l>
<Speaker>Undine</Speaker>
<l>Shine in meteor-sheen,</l>
<Speaker>Sylph</Speaker>
<l>Bring help to hearth and shelf.</l>
<l>Incubus! Incubus!</l>
<l>Step forward, and finish thus!</l>
<l>Of the Four, no feature</l>
<l>Lurks in the creature.</l>
<l>Quiet he lies, and grins disdain:</l>
<l>Not yet, it seems, have I given him pain.</l>
<l>Now, to undisguise thee,</l>
<l>Hear me exorcise thee!</l>
<l>Art thou, my gay one,</l>
<l>Hell&apos;s fugitive stray-one?</l>
<l>The sign witness now,</l>
<l>Before which they bow,</l>
<l>The cohorts of Hell!</l>

<l>With hair all bristling, it begins to swell.</l>

<l>Base Being, hearest thou?</l>
<l>Knowest and fearest thou</l>
<l>The One, unoriginate,</l>
<l>Named inexpressibly,</l>
<l>Through all Heaven impermeate,</l>
<l>Pierced irredressibly!</l>
<l>Behind the stove still banned,</l>
<l>See it, an elephant, expand!</l>
<l>It fills the space entire,</l>
<l>Mist-like melting, ever faster.</l>
<l>&apos;Tis enough: ascend no higher,—</l>
<l>Lay thyself at the feet of the Master!</l>
<l>Thou seest, not vain the threats I bring thee:</l>
<l>With holy fire I&apos;ll scorch and sting thee!</l>
<l>Wait not to know</l>
<l>The threefold dazzling glow!</l>
<l>Wait not to know</l>
<l>The strongest art within my hands!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>(while the vapor is dissipating, steps forth from behind the</l>
<l>stove, in the costume of a Travelling Scholar.)</l>
<l>Why such a noise? What are my lord&apos;s commands?</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>This was the poodle&apos;s real core,</l>
<l>A travelling scholar, then? The casus is diverting.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>The learned gentleman I bow before:</l>
<l>You&apos;ve made me roundly sweat, that&apos;s certain!</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>What is thy name?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>A question small, it seems,</l>
<l>For one whose mind the Word so much despises;</l>
<l>Who, scorning all external gleams,</l>
<l>The depths of being only prizes.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>With all you gentlemen, the name&apos;s a test,</l>
<l>Whereby the nature usually is expressed.</l>
<l>Clearly the latter it implies</l>
<l>In names like Beelzebub, Destroyer, Father of Lies.</l>
<l>Who art thou, then?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Part of that Power, not understood,</l>
<l>Which always wills the Bad, and always works the Good.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>What hidden sense in this enigma lies?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>I am the Spirit that Denies!</l>
<l>And justly so: for all things, from the Void</l>
<l>Called forth, deserve to be destroyed:</l>
<l>&apos;Twere better, then, were naught created.</l>
<l>Thus, all which you as Sin have rated,—</l>
<l>Destruction,—aught with Evil blent,—</l>
<l>That is my proper element.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Thou nam&apos;st thyself a part, yet show&apos;st complete to me?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>The modest truth I speak to thee.</l>
<l>If Man, that microcosmic fool, can see</l>
<l>Himself a whole so frequently,</l>
<l>Part of the Part am I, once All, in primal Night,—</l>
<l>Part of the Darkness which brought forth the Light,</l>
<l>The haughty Light, which now disputes the space,</l>
<l>And claims of Mother Night her ancient place.</l>
<l>And yet, the struggle fails; since Light, howe&apos;er it weaves,</l>
<l>Still, fettered, unto bodies cleaves:</l>
<l>It flows from bodies, bodies beautifies;</l>
<l>By bodies is its course impeded;</l>
<l>And so, but little time is needed,</l>
<l>I hope, ere, as the bodies die, it dies!</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>I see the plan thou art pursuing:</l>
<l>Thou canst not compass general ruin,</l>
<l>And hast on smaller scale begun.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>And truly &apos;tis not much, when all is done.</l>
<l>That which to Naught is in resistance set,—</l>
<l>The Something of this clumsy world,—has yet,</l>
<l>With all that I have undertaken,</l>
<l>Not been by me disturbed or shaken:</l>
<l>From earthquake, tempest, wave, volcano&apos;s brand,</l>
<l>Back into quiet settle sea and land!</l>
<l>And that damned stuff, the bestial, human brood,—</l>
<l>What use, in having that to play with?</l>
<l>How many have I made away with!</l>
<l>And ever circulates a newer, fresher blood.</l>
<l>It makes me furious, such things beholding:</l>
<l>From Water, Earth, and Air unfolding,</l>
<l>A thousand germs break forth and grow,</l>
<l>In dry, and wet, and warm, and chilly;</l>
<l>And had I not the Flame reserved, why, really,</l>
<l>There&apos;s nothing special of my own to show!</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>So, to the actively eternal</l>
<l>Creative force, in cold disdain</l>
<l>You now oppose the fist infernal,</l>
<l>Whose wicked clench is all in vain!</l>
<l>Some other labor seek thou rather,</l>
<l>Queer Son of Chaos, to begin!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Well, we&apos;ll consider: thou canst gather</l>
<l>My views, when next I venture in.</l>
<l>Might I, perhaps, depart at present?</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Why thou shouldst ask, I don&apos;t perceive.</l>
<l>Though our acquaintance is so recent,</l>
<l>For further visits thou hast leave.</l>
<l>The window&apos;s here, the door is yonder;</l>
<l>A chimney, also, you behold.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>I must confess that forth I may not wander,</l>
<l>My steps by one slight obstacle controlled,—</l>
<l>The wizard&apos;s-foot, that on your threshold made is.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>The pentagram prohibits thee?</l>
<l>Why, tell me now, thou Son of Hades,</l>
<l>If that prevents, how cam&apos;st thou in to me?</l>
<l>Could such a spirit be so cheated?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Inspect the thing: the drawing&apos;s not completed.</l>
<l>The outer angle, you may see,</l>
<l>Is open left—the lines don&apos;t fit it.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Well,—Chance, this time, has fairly hit it!</l>
<l>And thus, thou&apos;rt prisoner to me?</l>
<l>It seems the business has succeeded.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>The poodle naught remarked, as after thee he speeded;</l>
<l>But other aspects now obtain:</l>
<l>The Devil can&apos;t get out again.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Try, then, the open window-pane!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>For Devils and for spectres this is law:</l>
<l>Where they have entered in, there also they withdraw.</l>
<l>The first is free to us; we&apos;re governed by the second.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>In Hell itself, then, laws are reckoned?</l>
<l>That&apos;s well! So might a compact be</l>
<l>Made with you gentlemen—and binding,—surely?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>All that is promised shall delight thee purely;</l>
<l>No skinflint bargain shalt thou see.</l>
<l>But this is not of swift conclusion;</l>
<l>We&apos;ll talk about the matter soon.</l>
<l>And now, I do entreat this boon—</l>
<l>Leave to withdraw from my intrusion.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>One moment more I ask thee to remain,</l>
<l>Some pleasant news, at least, to tell me.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Release me, now! I soon shall come again;</l>
<l>Then thou, at will, mayst question and compel me.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>I have not snares around thee cast;</l>
<l>Thyself hast led thyself into the meshes.</l>
<l>Who traps the Devil, hold him fast!</l>
<l>Not soon a second time he&apos;ll catch a prey so precious.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>An&apos;t please thee, also I&apos;m content to stay,</l>
<l>And serve thee in a social station;</l>
<l>But stipulating, that I may</l>
<l>With arts of mine afford thee recreation.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Thereto I willingly agree,</l>
<l>If the diversion pleasant be.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>My friend, thou&apos;lt win, past all pretences,</l>
<l>More in this hour to soothe thy senses,</l>
<l>Than in the year&apos;s monotony.</l>
<l>That which the dainty spirits sing thee,</l>
<l>The lovely pictures they shall bring thee,</l>
<l>Are more than magic&apos;s empty show.</l>
<l>Thy scent will be to bliss invited;</l>
<l>Thy palate then with taste delighted,</l>
<l>Thy nerves of touch ecstatic glow!</l>
<l>All unprepared, the charm I spin:</l>
<l>We&apos;re here together, so begin!</l>

<Speaker>SPIRITS</Speaker>

<l>Vanish, ye darking</l>
<l>Arches above him!</l>
<l>Loveliest weather,</l>
<l>Born of blue ether,</l>
<l>Break from the sky!</l>
<l>O that the darkling</l>
<l>Clouds had departed!</l>
<l>Starlight is sparkling,</l>
<l>Tranquiller-hearted</l>
<l>Suns are on high.</l>
<l>Heaven&apos;s own children</l>
<l>In beauty bewildering,</l>
<l>Waveringly bending,</l>
<l>Pass as they hover;</l>
<l>Longing unending</l>
<l>Follows them over.</l>
<l>They, with their glowing</l>
<l>Garments, out-flowing,</l>
<l>Cover, in going,</l>
<l>Landscape and bower,</l>
<l>Where, in seclusion,</l>
<l>Lovers are plighted,</l>
<l>Lost in illusion.</l>
<l>Bower on bower!</l>
<l>Tendrils unblighted!</l>
<l>Lo! in a shower</l>
<l>Grapes that o&apos;ercluster</l>
<l>Gush into must, or</l>
<l>Flow into rivers</l>
<l>Of foaming and flashing</l>
<l>Wine, that is dashing</l>
<l>Gems, as it boundeth</l>
<l>Down the high places,</l>
<l>And spreading, surroundeth</l>
<l>With crystalline spaces,</l>
<l>In happy embraces,</l>
<l>Blossoming forelands,</l>
<l>Emerald shore-lands!</l>
<l>And the winged races</l>
<l>Drink, and fly onward—</l>
<l>Fly ever sunward</l>
<l>To the enticing</l>
<l>Islands, that flatter,</l>
<l>Dipping and rising</l>
<l>Light on the water!</l>
<l>Hark, the inspiring</l>
<l>Sound of their quiring!</l>
<l>See, the entrancing</l>
<l>Whirl of their dancing!</l>
<l>All in the air are</l>
<l>Freer and fairer.</l>
<l>Some of them scaling</l>
<l>Boldly the highlands,</l>
<l>Others are sailing,</l>
<l>Circling the islands;</l>
<l>Others are flying;</l>
<l>Life-ward all hieing,—</l>
<l>All for the distant</l>
<l>Star of existent</l>
<l>Rapture and Love!</l>
<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>He sleeps! Enough, ye fays! your airy number</l>
<l>Have sung him truly into slumber:</l>
<l>For this performance I your debtor prove.—</l>
<l>Not yet art thou the man, to catch the Fiend and hold him!—</l>
<l>With fairest images of dreams infold him,</l>
<l>Plunge him in seas of sweet untruth!</l>
<l>Yet, for the threshold&apos;s magic which controlled him,</l>
<l>The Devil needs a rat&apos;s quick tooth.</l>
<l>I use no lengthened invocation:</l>
<l>Here rustles one that soon will work my liberation.</l>

<l>The lord of rats and eke of mice,</l>
<l>Of flies and bed-bugs, frogs and lice,</l>
<l>Summons thee hither to the door-sill,</l>
<l>To gnaw it where, with just a morsel</l>
<l>Of oil, he paints the spot for thee:—</l>
<l>There com&apos;st thou, hopping on to me!</l>
<l>To work, at once! The point which made me craven</l>
<l>Is forward, on the ledge, engraven.</l>
<l>Another bite makes free the door:</l>
<l>So, dream thy dreams, O Faust, until we meet once more!</l>

<Speaker>FAUST (awaking</Speaker>

<l>Am I again so foully cheated?</l>
<l>Remains there naught of lofty spirit-sway,</l>
<l>But that a dream the Devil counterfeited,</l>
<l>And that a poodle ran away?</l>

<Scene> IV </Scene>
<Speaker>THE STUDY</Speaker>

<Speaker>FAUST MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>A knock? Come in! Again my quiet broken?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>&apos;Tis I!</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Come in!</l>
<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Thrice must the words be spoken.</l>
<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Come in, then!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Thus thou pleasest me.</l>
<l>I hope we&apos;ll suit each other well;</l>
<l>For now, thy vapors to dispel,</l>
<l>I come, a squire of high degree,</l>
<l>In scarlet coat, with golden trimming,</l>
<l>A cloak in silken lustre swimming,</l>
<l>A tall cock&apos;s-feather in my hat,</l>
<l>A long, sharp sword for show or quarrel,—</l>
<l>And I advise thee, brief and flat,</l>
<l>To don the self-same gay apparel,</l>
<l>That, from this den released, and free,</l>
<l>Life be at last revealed to thee!</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>This life of earth, whatever my attire,</l>
<l>Would pain me in its wonted fashion.</l>
<l>Too old am I to play with passion;</l>
<l>Too young, to be without desire.</l>
<l>What from the world have I to gain?</l>
<l>Thou shalt abstain—renounce—refrain!</l>
<l>Such is the everlasting song</l>
<l>That in the ears of all men rings,—</l>
<l>That unrelieved, our whole life long,</l>
<l>Each hour, in passing, hoarsely sings.</l>
<l>In very terror I at morn awake,</l>
<l>Upon the verge of bitter weeping,</l>
<l>To see the day of disappointment break,</l>
<l>To no one hope of mine—not one—its promise keeping:—</l>
<l>That even each joy&apos;s presentiment</l>
<l>With wilful cavil would diminish,</l>
<l>With grinning masks of life prevent</l>
<l>My mind its fairest work to finish!</l>
<l>Then, too, when night descends, how anxiously</l>
<l>Upon my couch of sleep I lay me:</l>
<l>There, also, comes no rest to me,</l>
<l>But some wild dream is sent to fray me.</l>
<l>The God that in my breast is owned</l>
<l>Can deeply stir the inner sources;</l>
<l>The God, above my powers enthroned,</l>
<l>He cannot change external forces.</l>
<l>So, by the burden of my days oppressed,</l>
<l>Death is desired, and Life a thing unblest!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>And yet is never Death a wholly welcome guest.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>O fortunate, for whom, when victory glances,</l>
<l>The bloody laurels on the brow he bindeth!</l>
<l>Whom, after rapid, maddening dances,</l>
<l>In clasping maiden-arms he findeth!</l>
<l>O would that I, before that spirit-power,</l>
<l>Ravished and rapt from life, had sunken!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>And yet, by some one, in that nightly hour,</l>
<l>A certain liquid was not drunken.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Eavesdropping, ha! thy pleasure seems to be.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Omniscient am I not; yet much is known to me.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Though some familiar tone, retrieving</l>
<l>My thoughts from torment, led me on,</l>
<l>And sweet, clear echoes came, deceiving</l>
<l>A faith bequeathed from Childhood&apos;s dawn,</l>
<l>Yet now I curse whate&apos;er entices</l>
<l>And snares the soul with visions vain;</l>
<l>With dazzling cheats and dear devices</l>
<l>Confines it in this cave of pain!</l>
<l>Cursed be, at once, the high ambition</l>
<l>Wherewith the mind itself deludes!</l>
<l>Cursed be the glare of apparition</l>
<l>That on the finer sense intrudes!</l>
<l>Cursed be the lying dream&apos;s impression</l>
<l>Of name, and fame, and laurelled brow!</l>
<l>Cursed, all that flatters as possession,</l>
<l>As wife and child, as knave and plow!</l>
<l>Cursed Mammon be, when he with treasures</l>
<l>To restless action spurs our fate!</l>
<l>Cursed when, for soft, indulgent leisures,</l>
<l>He lays for us the pillows straight!</l>
<l>Cursed be the vine&apos;s transcendent nectar,—</l>
<l>The highest favor Love lets fall!</l>
<l>Cursed, also, Hope!—cursed Faith, the spectre!</l>
<l>And cursed be Patience most of all!</l>

<l>CHORUS OF SPIRITS (invisible)</l>

<l>Woe! woe!</l>
<l>Thou hast it destroyed,</l>
<l>The beautiful world,</l>
<l>With powerful fist:</l>
<l>In ruin &apos;tis hurled,</l>
<l>By the blow of a demigod shattered!</l>
<l>The scattered</l>
<l>Fragments into the Void we carry,</l>
<Speaker>Deploring</Speaker>
<l>The beauty perished beyond restoring.</l>
<Speaker>Mightier</Speaker>
<l>For the children of men,</l>
<Speaker>Brightlier</Speaker>
<l>Build it again,</l>
<l>In thine own bosom build it anew!</l>
<l>Bid the new career</l>
<Speaker>Commence</Speaker>
<l>With clearer sense,</l>
<l>And the new songs of cheer</l>
<l>Be sung thereto!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>These are the small dependants</l>
<l>Who give me attendance.</l>
<l>Hear them, to deeds and passion</l>
<l>Counsel in shrewd old-fashion!</l>
<l>Into the world of strife,</l>
<l>Out of this lonely life</l>
<l>That of senses and sap has betrayed thee,</l>
<l>They would persuade thee.</l>
<l>This nursing of the pain forego thee,</l>
<l>That, like a vulture, feeds upon thy breast!</l>
<l>The worst society thou find&apos;st will show thee</l>
<l>Thou art a man among the rest.</l>
<l>But &apos;tis not meant to thrust</l>
<l>Thee into the mob thou hatest!</l>
<l>I am not one of the greatest,</l>
<l>Yet, wilt thou to me entrust</l>
<l>Thy steps through life, I&apos;ll guide thee,—</l>
<l>Will willingly walk beside thee,—</l>
<l>Will serve thee at once and forever</l>
<l>With best endeavor,</l>
<l>And, if thou art satisfied,</l>
<l>Will as servant, slave, with thee abide.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>And what shall be my counter-service therefor?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>The time is long: thou need&apos;st not now insist.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>No—no! The Devil is an egotist,</l>
<l>And is not apt, without a why or wherefore,</l>
<l>&quot;For God&apos;s sake,&quot; others to assist.</l>
<l>Speak thy conditions plain and clear!</l>
<l>With such a servant danger comes, I fear.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Here, an unwearied slave, I&apos;ll wear thy tether,</l>
<l>And to thine every nod obedient be:</l>
<l>When There again we come together,</l>
<l>Then shalt thou do the same for me.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>The There my scruples naught increases.</l>
<l>When thou hast dashed this world to pieces,</l>
<l>The other, then, its place may fill.</l>
<l>Here, on this earth, my pleasures have their sources;</l>
<l>Yon sun beholds my sorrows in his courses;</l>
<l>And when from these my life itself divorces,</l>
<l>Let happen all that can or will!</l>
<l>I&apos;ll hear no more: &apos;tis vain to ponder</l>
<l>If there we cherish love or hate,</l>
<l>Or, in the spheres we dream of yonder,</l>
<l>A High and Low our souls await.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>In this sense, even, canst thou venture.</l>
<l>Come, bind thyself by prompt indenture,</l>
<l>And thou mine arts with joy shalt see:</l>
<l>What no man ever saw, I&apos;ll give to thee.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Canst thou, poor Devil, give me whatsoever?</l>
<l>When was a human soul, in its supreme endeavor,</l>
<l>E&apos;er understood by such as thou?</l>
<l>Yet, hast thou food which never satiates, now,—</l>
<l>The restless, ruddy gold hast thou,</l>
<l>That runs, quicksilver-like, one&apos;s fingers through,—</l>
<l>A game whose winnings no man ever knew,—</l>
<l>A maid that, even from my breast,</l>
<l>Beckons my neighbor with her wanton glances,</l>
<l>And Honor&apos;s godlike zest,</l>
<l>The meteor that a moment dances,—</l>
<l>Show me the fruits that, ere they&apos;re gathered, rot,</l>
<l>And trees that daily with new leafage clothe them!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Such a demand alarms me not:</l>
<l>Such treasures have I, and can show them.</l>
<l>But still the time may reach us, good my friend.</l>
<l>When peace we crave and more luxurious diet.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>When on an idler&apos;s bed I stretch myself in quiet.</l>
<l>There let, at once, my record end!</l>
<l>Canst thou with lying flattery rule me,</l>
<l>Until, self-pleased, myself I see,—</l>
<l>Canst thou with rich enjoyment fool me,</l>
<l>Let that day be the last for me!</l>
<l>The bet I offer.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>
<Speaker>Done</Speaker>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>
<l>And heartily!</l>
<l>When thus I hail the Moment flying:</l>
<l>&quot;Ah, still delay—thou art so fair!&quot;</l>
<l>Then bind me in thy bonds undying,</l>
<l>My final ruin then declare!</l>
<l>Then let the death-bell chime the token.</l>
<l>Then art thou from thy service free!</l>
<l>The clock may stop, the hand be broken,</l>
<l>Then Time be finished unto me!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Consider well: my memory good is rated.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Thou hast a perfect right thereto.</l>
<l>My powers I have not rashly estimated:</l>
<l>A slave am I, whate&apos;er I do—</l>
<l>If thine, or whose? &apos;tis needless to debate it.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Then at the Doctors&apos;-banquet I, to-day,</l>
<l>Will as a servant wait behind thee.</l>
<l>But one thing more! Beyond all risk to bind thee,</l>
<l>Give me a line or two, I pray.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Demand&apos;st thou, Pedant, too, a document?</l>
<l>Hast never known a man, nor proved his word&apos;s intent?</l>
<l>Is&apos;t not enough, that what I speak to-day</l>
<l>Shall stand, with all my future days agreeing?</l>
<l>In all its tides sweeps not the world away,</l>
<l>And shall a promise bind my being?</l>
<l>Yet this delusion in our hearts we bear:</l>
<l>Who would himself therefrom deliver?</l>
<l>Blest he, whose bosom Truth makes pure and fair!</l>
<l>No sacrifice shall he repent of ever.</l>
<l>Nathless a parchment, writ and stamped with care,</l>
<l>A spectre is, which all to shun endeavor.</l>
<l>The word, alas! dies even in the pen,</l>
<l>And wax and leather keep the lordship then.</l>
<l>What wilt from me, Base Spirit, say?—</l>
<l>Brass, marble, parchment, paper, clay?</l>
<l>The terms with graver, quill, or chisel, stated?</l>
<l>I freely leave the choice to thee.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Why heat thyself, thus instantly,</l>
<l>With eloquence exaggerated?</l>
<l>Each leaf for such a pact is good;</l>
<l>And to subscribe thy name thou&apos;lt take a drop of blood.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>If thou therewith art fully satisfied,</l>
<l>So let us by the farce abide.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Blood is a juice of rarest quality.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Fear not that I this pact shall seek to sever?</l>
<l>The promise that I make to thee</l>
<l>Is just the sum of my endeavor.</l>
<l>I have myself inflated all too high;</l>
<l>My proper place is thy estate:</l>
<l>The Mighty Spirit deigns me no reply,</l>
<l>And Nature shuts on me her gate.</l>
<l>The thread of Thought at last is broken,</l>
<l>And knowledge brings disgust unspoken.</l>
<l>Let us the sensual deeps explore,</l>
<l>To quench the fervors of glowing passion!</l>
<l>Let every marvel take form and fashion</l>
<l>Through the impervious veil it wore!</l>
<l>Plunge we in Time&apos;s tumultuous dance,</l>
<l>In the rush and roll of Circumstance!</l>
<l>Then may delight and distress,</l>
<l>And worry and success,</l>
<l>Alternately follow, as best they can:</l>
<l>Restless activity proves the man!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>For you no bound, no term is set.</l>
<l>Whether you everywhere be trying,</l>
<l>Or snatch a rapid bliss in flying,</l>
<l>May it agree with you, what you get!</l>
<l>Only fall to, and show no timid balking.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>But thou hast heard, &apos;tis not of joy we&apos;re talking.</l>
<l>I take the wildering whirl, enjoyment&apos;s keenest pain,</l>
<l>Enamored hate, exhilarant disdain.</l>
<l>My bosom, of its thirst for knowledge sated,</l>
<l>Shall not, henceforth, from any pang be wrested,</l>
<l>And all of life for all mankind created</l>
<l>Shall be within mine inmost being tested:</l>
<l>The highest, lowest forms my soul shall borrow,</l>
<l>Shall heap upon itself their bliss and sorrow,</l>
<l>And thus, my own sole self to all their selves expanded,</l>
<l>I too, at last, shall with them all be stranded!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Believe me, who for many a thousand year</l>
<l>The same tough meat have chewed and tested,</l>
<l>That from the cradle to the bier</l>
<l>No man the ancient leaven has digested!</l>
<l>Trust one of us, this Whole supernal</l>
<l>Is made but for a God&apos;s delight!</l>
<l>He dwells in splendor single and eternal,</l>
<l>But us he thrusts in darkness, out of sight,</l>
<l>And you he dowers with Day and Night.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Nay, but I will!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>A good reply!</l>
<l>One only fear still needs repeating:</l>
<l>The art is long, the time is fleeting.</l>
<l>Then let thyself be taught, say I!</l>
<l>Go, league thyself with a poet,</l>
<l>Give the rein to his imagination,</l>
<l>Then wear the crown, and show it,</l>
<l>Of the qualities of his creation,—</l>
<l>The courage of the lion&apos;s breed,</l>
<l>The wild stag&apos;s speed,</l>
<l>The Italian&apos;s fiery blood,</l>
<l>The North&apos;s firm fortitude!</l>
<l>Let him find for thee the secret tether</l>
<l>That binds the Noble and Mean together.</l>
<l>And teach thy pulses of youth and pleasure</l>
<l>To love by rule, and hate by measure!</l>
<l>I&apos;d like, myself, such a one to see:</l>
<l>Sir Microcosm his name should be.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>What am I, then, if &apos;tis denied my part</l>
<l>The crown of all humanity to win me,</l>
<l>Whereto yearns every sense within me?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Why, on the whole, thou&apos;rt—what thou art.</l>
<l>Set wigs of million curls upon thy head, to raise thee,</l>
<l>Wear shoes an ell in height,—the truth betrays thee,</l>
<l>And thou remainest—what thou art.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>I feel, indeed, that I have made the treasure</l>
<l>Of human thought and knowledge mine, in vain;</l>
<l>And if I now sit down in restful leisure,</l>
<l>No fount of newer strength is in my brain:</l>
<l>I am no hair&apos;s-breadth more in height,</l>
<l>Nor nearer, to the Infinite,</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Good Sir, you see the facts precisely</l>
<l>As they are seen by each and all.</l>
<l>We must arrange them now, more wisely,</l>
<l>Before the joys of life shall pall.</l>
<l>Why, Zounds! Both hands and feet are, truly—</l>
<l>And head and virile forces—thine:</l>
<l>Yet all that I indulge in newly,</l>
<l>Is&apos;t thence less wholly mine?</l>
<l>If I&apos;ve six stallions in my stall,</l>
<l>Are not their forces also lent me?</l>
<l>I speed along, completest man of all,</l>
<l>As though my legs were four-and-twenty.</l>
<l>Take hold, then! let reflection rest,</l>
<l>And plunge into the world with zest!</l>
<l>I say to thee, a speculative wight</l>
<l>Is like a beast on moorlands lean,</l>
<l>That round and round some fiend misleads to evil plight,</l>
<l>While all about lie pastures fresh and green.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Then how shall we begin?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>We&apos;ll try a wider sphere.</l>
<l>What place of martyrdom is here!</l>
<l>Is&apos;t life, I ask, is&apos;t even prudence,</l>
<l>To bore thyself and bore the students?</l>
<l>Let Neighbor Paunch to that attend!</l>
<l>Why plague thyself with threshing straw forever?</l>
<l>The best thou learnest, in the end</l>
<l>Thou dar&apos;st not tell the youngsters—never!</l>
<l>I hear one&apos;s footsteps, hither steering.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>
<l>To see him now I have no heart.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>So long the poor boy waits a hearing,</l>
<l>He must not unconsoled depart.</l>
<l>Thy cap and mantle straightway lend me!</l>
<l>I&apos;ll play the comedy with art.</l>

<l>(He disguises himself.)</l>

<l>My wits, be certain, will befriend me.</l>
<l>But fifteen minutes&apos; time is all I need;</l>
<l>For our fine trip, meanwhile, prepare thyself with speed!</l>

<l>[Exit FAUST.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>(In FAUST&apos;S long mantle.)</l>

<l>Reason and Knowledge only thou despise,</l>
<l>The highest strength in man that lies!</l>
<l>Let but the Lying Spirit bind thee</l>
<l>With magic works and shows that blind thee,</l>
<l>And I shall have thee fast and sure!—</l>
<l>Fate such a bold, untrammelled spirit gave him,</l>
<l>As forwards, onwards, ever must endure;</l>
<l>Whose over-hasty impulse drave him</l>
<l>Past earthly joys he might secure.</l>
<l>Dragged through the wildest life, will I enslave him,</l>
<l>Through flat and stale indifference;</l>
<l>With struggling, chilling, checking, so deprave him</l>
<l>That, to his hot, insatiate sense,</l>
<l>The dream of drink shall mock, but never lave him:</l>
<l>Refreshment shall his lips in vain implore—</l>
<l>Had he not made himself the Devil&apos;s, naught could save him,</l>
<l>Still were he lost forevermore!</l>

<l>(A STUDENT enters.)</l>

<Speaker>STUDENT</Speaker>

<l>A short time, only, am I here,</l>
<l>And come, devoted and sincere,</l>
<l>To greet and know the man of fame,</l>
<l>Whom men to me with reverence name.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Your courtesy doth flatter me:</l>
<l>You see a man, as others be.</l>
<l>Have you, perchance, elsewhere begun?</l>

<Speaker>STUDENT</Speaker>

<l>Receive me now, I pray, as one</l>
<l>Who comes to you with courage good,</l>
<l>Somewhat of cash, and healthy blood:</l>
<l>My mother was hardly willing to let me;</l>
<l>But knowledge worth having I fain would get me.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Then you have reached the right place now.</l>

<Speaker>STUDENT</Speaker>

<l>I&apos;d like to leave it, I must avow;</l>
<l>I find these walls, these vaulted spaces</l>
<l>Are anything but pleasant places.</l>
<l>Tis all so cramped and close and mean;</l>
<l>One sees no tree, no glimpse of green,</l>
<l>And when the lecture-halls receive me,</l>
<l>Seeing, hearing, and thinking leave me.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>All that depends on habitude.</l>
<l>So from its mother&apos;s breasts a child</l>
<l>At first, reluctant, takes its food,</l>
<l>But soon to seek them is beguiled.</l>
<l>Thus, at the breasts of Wisdom clinging,</l>
<l>Thou&apos;lt find each day a greater rapture bringing.</l>

<Speaker>STUDENT</Speaker>

<l>I&apos;ll hang thereon with joy, and freely drain them;</l>
<l>But tell me, pray, the proper means to gain them.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Explain, before you further speak,</l>
<l>The special faculty you seek.</l>

<Speaker>STUDENT</Speaker>

<l>I crave the highest erudition;</l>
<l>And fain would make my acquisition</l>
<l>All that there is in Earth and Heaven,</l>
<l>In Nature and in Science too.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Here is the genuine path for you;</l>
<l>Yet strict attention must be given.</l>

<Speaker>STUDENT</Speaker>

<l>Body and soul thereon I&apos;ll wreak;</l>
<l>Yet, truly, I&apos;ve some inclination</l>
<l>On summer holidays to seek</l>
<l>A little freedom and recreation.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Use well your time! It flies so swiftly from us;</l>
<l>But time through order may be won, I promise.</l>
<l>So, Friend (my views to briefly sum),</l>
<l>First, the collegium logicum.</l>
<l>There will your mind be drilled and braced,</l>
<l>As if in Spanish boots &apos;twere laced,</l>
<l>And thus, to graver paces brought,</l>
<l>&apos;Twill plod along the path of thought,</l>
<l>Instead of shooting here and there,</l>
<l>A will-o&apos;-the-wisp in murky air.</l>
<l>Days will be spent to bid you know,</l>
<l>What once you did at a single blow,</l>
<l>Like eating and drinking, free and strong,—</l>
<l>That one, two, three! thereto belong.</l>
<l>Truly the fabric of mental fleece</l>
<l>Resembles a weaver&apos;s masterpiece,</l>
<l>Where a thousand threads one treadle throws,</l>
<l>Where fly the shuttles hither and thither.</l>
<l>Unseen the threads are knit together.</l>
<l>And an infinite combination grows.</l>
<l>Then, the philosopher steps in</l>
<l>And shows, no otherwise it could have been:</l>
<l>The first was so, the second so,</l>
<l>Therefore the third and fourth are so;</l>
<l>Were not the first and second, then</l>
<l>The third and fourth had never been.</l>
<l>The scholars are everywhere believers,</l>
<l>But never succeed in being weavers.</l>
<l>He who would study organic existence,</l>
<l>First drives out the soul with rigid persistence;</l>
<l>Then the parts in his hand he may hold and class,</l>
<l>But the spiritual link is lost, alas!</l>
<l>Encheiresin natures, this Chemistry names,</l>
<l>Nor knows how herself she banters and blames!</l>

<Speaker>STUDENT</Speaker>

<l>I cannot understand you quite.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Your mind will shortly be set aright,</l>
<l>When you have learned, all things reducing,</l>
<l>To classify them for your using.</l>

<Speaker>STUDENT</Speaker>

<l>I feel as stupid, from all you&apos;ve said,</l>
<l>As if a mill-wheel whirled in my head!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>And after—first and foremost duty—Of</l>
<l>Metaphysics learn the use and beauty!</l>
<l>See that you most profoundly gain</l>
<l>What does not suit the human brain!</l>
<l>A splendid word to serve, you&apos;ll find</l>
<l>For what goes in—or won&apos;t go in—your mind.</l>
<l>But first, at least this half a year,</l>
<l>To order rigidly adhere;</l>
<l>Five hours a day, you understand,</l>
<l>And when the clock strikes, be on hand!</l>
<l>Prepare beforehand for your part</l>
<l>With paragraphs all got by heart,</l>
<l>So you can better watch, and look</l>
<l>That naught is said but what is in the book:</l>
<l>Yet in thy writing as unwearied be,</l>
<l>As did the Holy Ghost dictate to thee!</l>

<Speaker>STUDENT</Speaker>

<l>No need to tell me twice to do it!</l>
<l>I think, how useful &apos;tis to write;</l>
<l>For what one has, in black and white,</l>
<l>One carries home and then goes through it.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Yet choose thyself a faculty!</l>

<Speaker>STUDENT</Speaker>

<l>I cannot reconcile myself to Jurisprudence.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Nor can I therefore greatly blame you students:</l>
<l>I know what science this has come to be.</l>
<l>All rights and laws are still transmitted</l>
<l>Like an eternal sickness of the race,—</l>
<l>From generation unto generation fitted,</l>
<l>And shifted round from place to place.</l>
<l>Reason becomes a sham, Beneficence a worry:</l>
<l>Thou art a grandchild, therefore woe to thee!</l>
<l>The right born with us, ours in verity,</l>
<l>This to consider, there&apos;s, alas! no hurry.</l>

<Speaker>STUDENT</Speaker>

<l>My own disgust is strengthened by your speech:</l>
<l>O lucky he, whom you shall teach!</l>
<l>I&apos;ve almost for Theology decided.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>I should not wish to see you here misguided:</l>
<l>For, as regards this science, let me hint</l>
<l>&apos;Tis very hard to shun the false direction;</l>
<l>There&apos;s so much secret poison lurking in &apos;t,</l>
<l>So like the medicine, it baffles your detection.</l>
<l>Hear, therefore, one alone, for that is best, in sooth,</l>
<l>And simply take your master&apos;s words for truth.</l>
<l>On words let your attention centre!</l>
<l>Then through the safest gate you&apos;ll enter</l>
<l>The temple-halls of Certainty.</l>

<Speaker>STUDENT</Speaker>

<l>Yet in the word must some idea be.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Of course! But only shun too over-sharp a tension,</l>
<l>For just where fails the comprehension,</l>
<l>A word steps promptly in as deputy.</l>
<l>With words &apos;tis excellent disputing;</l>
<l>Systems to words &apos;tis easy suiting;</l>
<l>On words &apos;tis excellent believing;</l>
<l>No word can ever lose a jot from thieving.</l>

<Speaker>STUDENT</Speaker>

<l>Pardon! With many questions I detain you.</l>
<l>Yet must I trouble you again.</l>
<l>Of Medicine I still would fain</l>
<l>Hear one strong word that might explain you.</l>
<l>Three years is but a little space.</l>
<l>And, God! who can the field embrace?</l>
<l>If one some index could be shown,</l>
<l>&apos;Twere easier groping forward, truly.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES (aside</Speaker>

<l>I&apos;m tired enough of this dry tone,—</l>
<l>Must play the Devil again, and fully.</l>

<Speaker>(Aloud</Speaker>

<l>To grasp the spirit of Medicine is easy:</l>
<l>Learn of the great and little world your fill,</l>
<l>To let it go at last, so please ye,</l>
<l>Just as God will!</l>
<l>In vain that through the realms of science you may drift;</l>
<l>Each one learns only—just what learn he can:</l>
<l>Yet he who grasps the Moment&apos;s gift,</l>
<l>He is the proper man.</l>
<l>Well-made you are, &apos;tis not to be denied,</l>
<l>The rest a bold address will win you;</l>
<l>If you but in yourself confide,</l>
<l>At once confide all others in you.</l>
<l>To lead the women, learn the special feeling!</l>
<l>Their everlasting aches and groans,</l>
<l>In thousand tones,</l>
<l>Have all one source, one mode of healing;</l>
<l>And if your acts are half discreet,</l>
<l>You&apos;ll always have them at your feet.</l>
<l>A title first must draw and interest them,</l>
<l>And show that yours all other arts exceeds;</l>
<l>Then, as a greeting, you are free to touch and test them,</l>
<l>While, thus to do, for years another pleads.</l>
<l>You press and count the pulse&apos;s dances,</l>
<l>And then, with burning sidelong glances,</l>
<l>You clasp the swelling hips, to see</l>
<l>If tightly laced her corsets be.</l>

<Speaker>STUDENT</Speaker>

<l>That&apos;s better, now! The How and Where, one sees.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>My worthy friend, gray are all theories,</l>
<l>And green alone Life&apos;s golden tree.</l>

<Speaker>STUDENT</Speaker>

<l>I swear to you, &apos;tis like a dream to me.</l>
<l>Might I again presume, with trust unbounded,</l>
<l>To hear your wisdom thoroughly expounded?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Most willingly, to what extent I may.</l>

<Speaker>STUDENT</Speaker>

<l>I cannot really go away:</l>
<l>Allow me that my album first I reach you,—</l>
<l>Grant me this favor, I beseech you!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<Speaker>Assuredly</Speaker>

<l>(He writes, and returns the book.)</l>

<Speaker>STUDENT (reads</Speaker>

<l>Eritis sicut Deus, scientes bonum et malum.</l>
<l>(Closes the book with reverence, and withdraws)</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Follow the ancient text, and the snake thou wast ordered to trample!</l>
<l>With all thy likeness to God, thou&apos;lt yet be a sorry example!</l>

<l>(FAUST enters.)</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Now, whither shall we go?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>As best it pleases thee.</l>
<l>The little world, and then the great, we&apos;ll see.</l>
<l>With what delight, what profit winning,</l>
<l>Shalt thou sponge through the term beginning!</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Yet with the flowing beard I wear,</l>
<l>Both ease and grace will fail me there.</l>
<l>The attempt, indeed, were a futile strife;</l>
<l>I never could learn the ways of life.</l>
<l>I feel so small before others, and thence</l>
<l>Should always find embarrassments.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>My friend, thou soon shalt lose all such misgiving:</l>
<l>Be thou but self-possessed, thou hast the art of living!</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>How shall we leave the house, and start?</l>
<l>Where hast thou servant, coach and horses?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>We&apos;ll spread this cloak with proper art,</l>
<l>Then through the air direct our courses.</l>
<l>But only, on so bold a flight,</l>
<l>Be sure to have thy luggage light.</l>
<l>A little burning air, which I shall soon prepare us,</l>
<l>Above the earth will nimbly bear us,</l>
<l>And, if we&apos;re light, we&apos;ll travel swift and clear:</l>
<l>I gratulate thee on thy new career!</l>

<Scene> V </Scene>


<l>AUERBACH&apos;S CELLAR IN LEIPZIG</l>


<l>CAROUSAL OF JOLLY COMPANIONS</l>

<Speaker>FROSCH</Speaker>

<l>Is no one laughing? no one drinking?</l>
<l>I&apos;ll teach you how to grin, I&apos;m thinking.</l>
<l>To-day you&apos;re like wet straw, so tame;</l>
<l>And usually you&apos;re all aflame.</l>

<Speaker>BRANDER</Speaker>

<l>Now that&apos;s your fault; from you we nothing see,</l>
<l>No beastliness and no stupidity.</l>

<Speaker>FROSCH</Speaker>

<l>(Pours a glass of wine over BRANDER&apos;S head.)</l>
<l>There&apos;s both together!</l>

<Speaker>BRANDER</Speaker>

<l>Twice a swine!</l>

<Speaker>FROSCH</Speaker>

<l>You wanted them: I&apos;ve given you mine.</l>

<Speaker>SIEBEL</Speaker>

<l>Turn out who quarrels—out the door!</l>
<l>With open throat sing chorus, drink and roar!</l>
<l>Up! holla! ho!</l>

<Speaker>ALTMAYER</Speaker>

<l>Woe&apos;s me, the fearful bellow!</l>
<l>Bring cotton, quick! He&apos;s split my ears, that fellow.</l>

<Speaker>SIEBEL</Speaker>

<l>When the vault echoes to the song,</l>
<l>One first perceives the bass is deep and strong.</l>

<Speaker>FROSCH</Speaker>

<l>Well said! and out with him that takes the least offence!</l>
<l>Ah, tara, lara da!</l>

<Speaker>ALTMAYER</Speaker>

<l>Ah, tara, lara, da!</l>

<Speaker>FROSCH</Speaker>

<l>The throats are tuned, commence!</l>

<Speaker>(Sings</Speaker>

<l>The dear old holy Roman realm,</l>
<l>How does it hold together?</l>

<Speaker>BRANDER</Speaker>

<l>A nasty song! Fie! a political song—</l>
<l>A most offensive song! Thank God, each morning, therefore,</l>
<l>That you have not the Roman realm to care for!</l>
<l>At least, I hold it so much gain for me,</l>
<l>That I nor Chancellor nor Kaiser be.</l>
<l>Yet also we must have a ruling head, I hope,</l>
<l>And so we&apos;ll choose ourselves a Pope.</l>
<l>You know the quality that can</l>
<l>Decide the choice, and elevate the man.</l>

<Speaker>FROSCH</Speaker>
<Speaker>(sings</Speaker>

<l>Soar up, soar up, Dame Nightingale!</l>
<l>Ten thousand times my sweetheart hail!</l>

<Speaker>SIEBEL</Speaker>

<l>No, greet my sweetheart not! I tell you, I&apos;ll resent it.</l>

<Speaker>FROSCH</Speaker>

<l>My sweetheart greet and kiss! I dare you to prevent it!</l>

<Speaker>(Sings</Speaker>

<l>Draw the latch! the darkness makes:</l>
<l>Draw the latch! the lover wakes.</l>
<l>Shut the latch! the morning breaks</l>

<Speaker>SIEBEL</Speaker>

<l>Yes, sing away, sing on, and praise, and brag of her!</l>
<l>I&apos;ll wait my proper time for laughter:</l>
<l>Me by the nose she led, and now she&apos;ll lead you after.</l>
<l>Her paramour should be an ugly gnome,</l>
<l>Where four roads cross, in wanton play to meet her:</l>
<l>An old he-goat, from Blocksberg coming home,</l>
<l>Should his good-night in lustful gallop bleat her!</l>
<l>A fellow made of genuine flesh and blood</l>
<l>Is for the wench a deal too good.</l>
<l>Greet her? Not I: unless, when meeting,</l>
<l>To smash her windows be a greeting!</l>

<l>BRANDER (pounding on the table)</l>

<l>Attention! Hearken now to me!</l>
<l>Confess, Sirs, I know how to live.</l>
<l>Enamored persons here have we,</l>
<l>And I, as suits their quality,</l>
<l>Must something fresh for their advantage give.</l>
<l>Take heed! &apos;Tis of the latest cut, my strain,</l>
<l>And all strike in at each refrain!</l>

<l>(He sings.)</l>

<l>There was a rat in the cellar-nest,</l>
<l>Whom fat and butter made smoother:</l>
<l>He had a paunch beneath his vest</l>
<l>Like that of Doctor Luther.</l>
<l>The cook laid poison cunningly,</l>
<l>And then as sore oppressed was he</l>
<l>As if he had love in his bosom.</l>

<Speaker>CHORUS (shouting</Speaker>

<l>As if he had love in his bosom!</l>

<Speaker>BRANDER</Speaker>

<l>He ran around, he ran about,</l>
<l>His thirst in puddles laving;</l>
<l>He gnawed and scratched the house throughout.</l>
<l>But nothing cured his raving.</l>
<l>He whirled and jumped, with torment mad,</l>
<l>And soon enough the poor beast had,</l>
<l>As if he had love in his bosom.</l>

<Speaker>CHORUS</Speaker>

<l>As if he had love in his bosom!</l>

<Speaker>BRANDER</Speaker>

<l>And driven at last, in open day,</l>
<l>He ran into the kitchen,</l>
<l>Fell on the hearth, and squirming lay,</l>
<l>In the last convulsion twitching.</l>
<l>Then laughed the murderess in her glee:</l>
<l>&quot;Ha! ha! he&apos;s at his last gasp,&quot; said she,</l>
<l>&quot;As if he had love in his bosom!&quot;</l>
<Speaker>CHORUS</Speaker>

<l>As if he had love in his bosom!</l>
<Speaker>SIEBEL</Speaker>

<l>How the dull fools enjoy the matter!</l>
<l>To me it is a proper art</l>
<l>Poison for such poor rats to scatter.</l>

<Speaker>BRANDER</Speaker>

<l>Perhaps you&apos;ll warmly take their part?</l>

<Speaker>ALTMAYER</Speaker>

<l>The bald-pate pot-belly I have noted:</l>
<l>Misfortune tames him by degrees;</l>
<l>For in the rat by poison bloated</l>
<l>His own most natural form he sees.</l>

<l>FAUST AND MEPHISTOPHELES</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Before all else, I bring thee hither</l>
<l>Where boon companions meet together,</l>
<l>To let thee see how smooth life runs away.</l>
<l>Here, for the folk, each day&apos;s a holiday:</l>
<l>With little wit, and ease to suit them,</l>
<l>They whirl in narrow, circling trails,</l>
<l>Like kittens playing with their tails?</l>
<l>And if no headache persecute them,</l>
<l>So long the host may credit give,</l>
<l>They merrily and careless live.</l>

<Speaker>BRANDER</Speaker>

<l>The fact is easy to unravel,</l>
<l>Their air&apos;s so odd, they&apos;ve just returned from travel:</l>
<l>A single hour they&apos;ve not been here.</l>

<Speaker>FROSCH</Speaker>

<l>You&apos;ve verily hit the truth! Leipzig to me is dear:</l>
<l>Paris in miniature, how it refines its people!</l>

<Speaker>SIEBEL</Speaker>

<l>Who are the strangers, should you guess?</l>

<Speaker>FROSCH</Speaker>

<l>Let me alone! I&apos;ll set them first to drinking,</l>
<l>And then, as one a child&apos;s tooth draws, with cleverness,</l>
<l>I&apos;ll worm their secret out, I&apos;m thinking.</l>
<l>They&apos;re of a noble house, that&apos;s very clear:</l>
<l>Haughty and discontented they appear.</l>

<Speaker>BRANDER</Speaker>

<l>They&apos;re mountebanks, upon a revel.</l>

<Speaker>ALTMAYER</Speaker>

<Speaker>Perhaps</Speaker>

<Speaker>FROSCH</Speaker>

<l>Look out, I&apos;ll smoke them now!</l>

<l>MEPHISTOPHELES (to FAUST)</l>

<l>Not if he had them by the neck, I vow,</l>
<l>Would e&apos;er these people scent the Devil!</l>

<l>FAUST Fair greeting, gentlemen!</l>

<Speaker>SIEBEL</Speaker>

<l>Our thanks: we give the same.</l>
<l>(Murmurs, inspecting MEPHISTOPHELES from the side.)</l>
<l>In one foot is the fellow lame?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Is it permitted that we share your leisure?</l>
<l>In place of cheering drink, which one seeks vainly here,</l>
<l>Your company shall give us pleasure.</l>

<Speaker>ALTMAYER</Speaker>

<l>A most fastidious person you appear.</l>

<Speaker>FROSCH</Speaker>

<l>No doubt &apos;twas late when you from Rippach started?</l>
<l>And supping there with Hans occasioned your delay?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>We passed, without a call, to-day.</l>
<l>At our last interview, before we parted</l>
<l>Much of his cousins did he speak, entreating</l>
<l>That we should give to each his kindly greeting.</l>

<l>(He bows to FROSCH.)</l>

<Speaker>ALTMAYER (aside</Speaker>

<l>You have it now! he understands.</l>

<Speaker>SIEBEL</Speaker>

<l>A knave sharp-set!</l>

<Speaker>FROSCH</Speaker>

<l>Just wait awhile: I&apos;ll have him yet.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>If I am right, we heard the sound</l>
<l>Of well-trained voices, singing chorus;</l>
<l>And truly, song must here rebound</l>
<l>Superbly from the arches o&apos;er us.</l>

<Speaker>FROSCH</Speaker>

<l>Are you, perhaps, a virtuoso?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>O no! my wish is great, my power is only so-so.</l>

<Speaker>ALTMAYER</Speaker>

<l>Give us a song!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>If you desire, a number.</l>

<Speaker>SIEBEL</Speaker>

<l>So that it be a bran-new strain!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>We&apos;ve just retraced our way from. Spain,</l>
<l>The lovely land of wine, and song, and slumber.</l>

<Speaker>(Sings</Speaker>

<l>There was a king once reigning,</l>
<l>Who had a big black flea—</l>

<Speaker>FROSCH</Speaker>

<l>Hear, hear! A flea! D&apos;ye rightly take the jest?</l>
<l>I call a flea a tidy guest.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES (sings</Speaker>

<l>There was a king once reigning,</l>
<l>Who had a big black flea,</l>
<l>And loved him past explaining,</l>
<l>As his own son were he.</l>
<l>He called his man of stitches;</l>
<l>The tailor came straightway:</l>
<l>Here, measure the lad for breeches.</l>
<l>And measure his coat, I say!</l>
<Speaker>BRANDER</Speaker>

<l>But mind, allow the tailor no caprices:</l>
<l>Enjoin upon him, as his head is dear,</l>
<l>To most exactly measure, sew and shear,</l>
<l>So that the breeches have no creases!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>In silk and velvet gleaming</l>
<l>He now was wholly drest—</l>
<l>Had a coat with ribbons streaming,</l>
<l>A cross upon his breast.</l>
<l>He had the first of stations,</l>
<l>A minister&apos;s star and name;</l>
<l>And also all his relations</l>
<l>Great lords at court became.</l>

<l>And the lords and ladies of honor</l>
<l>Were plagued, awake and in bed;</l>
<l>The queen she got them upon her,</l>
<l>The maids were bitten and bled.</l>
<l>And they did not dare to brush them,</l>
<l>Or scratch them, day or night:</l>
<l>We crack them and we crush them,</l>
<l>At once, whene&apos;er they bite.</l>

<Speaker>CHORUS (shouting</Speaker>

<l>We crack them and we crush them,</l>
<l>At once, whene&apos;er they bite!</l>
<l>FROSCH Bravo! bravo! that was fine.</l>

<Speaker>SIEBEL</Speaker>

<l>Every flea may it so befall!</l>

<Speaker>BRANDER</Speaker>

<l>Point your fingers and nip them all!</l>

<Speaker>ALTMAYER</Speaker>

<l>Hurrah for Freedom! Hurrah for wine!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>I fain would drink with you, my glass to Freedom clinking,</l>
<l>If &apos;twere a better wine that here I see you drinking.</l>

<Speaker>SIEBEL</Speaker>

<l>Don&apos;t let us hear that speech again!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Did I not fear the landlord might complain,</l>
<l>I&apos;d treat these worthy guests, with pleasure,</l>
<l>To some from out our cellar&apos;s treasure.</l>

<Speaker>SIEBEL</Speaker>

<l>Just treat, and let the landlord me arraign!</l>

<Speaker>FROSCH</Speaker>

<l>And if the wine be good, our praises shall be ample.</l>
<l>But do not give too very small a sample;</l>
<l>For, if its quality I decide,</l>
<l>With a good mouthful I must be supplied.</l>

<Speaker>ALTMAYER (aside</Speaker>

<l>They&apos;re from the Rhine! I guessed as much, before.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Bring me a gimlet here!</l>

<Speaker>BRANDER</Speaker>

<l>What shall therewith be done?</l>
<l>You&apos;ve not the casks already at the door?</l>

<Speaker>ALTMAYER</Speaker>

<l>Yonder, within the landlord&apos;s box of tools, there&apos;s one!</l>

<l>MEPHISTOPHELES (takes the gimlet)</l>

<l>(To FROSCH.)</l>

<l>Now, give me of your taste some intimation.</l>

<Speaker>FROSCH</Speaker>

<l>How do you mean? Have you so many kinds?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>The choice is free: make up your minds.</l>

<l>ALTMAYER (to FROSCH)</l>

<l>Aha! you lick your chops, from sheer anticipation.</l>

<Speaker>FROSCH</Speaker>

<l>Good! if I have the choice, so let the wine be Rhenish!</l>
<l>Our Fatherland can best the sparkling cup replenish.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>(boring a hole in the edge of the table, at the place where</l>
<Speaker>FROSCH sits</Speaker>

<l>Get me a little wax, to make the stoppers, quick!</l>

<Speaker>ALTMAYER</Speaker>

<l>Ah! I perceive a juggler&apos;s trick.</l>

<l>MEPHISTOPHELES (to BRANDER)</l>

<l>And you?</l>

<Speaker>BRANDER</Speaker>

<l>Champagne shall be my wine,</l>
<l>And let it sparkle fresh and fine!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>(bores: in the meantime one has made the wax stoppers, and</l>
<l>plugged the holes with them.)</l>

<Speaker>BRANDER</Speaker>

<l>What&apos;s foreign one can&apos;t always keep quite clear of,</l>
<l>For good things, oft, are not so near;</l>
<l>A German can&apos;t endure the French to see or hear of,</l>
<l>Yet drinks their wines with hearty cheer.</l>

<Speaker>SIEBEL</Speaker>

<l>(as MEPHISTOPHELES approaches his seat)</l>
<l>For me, I grant, sour wine is out of place;</l>
<l>Fill up my glass with sweetest, will you?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES (boring</Speaker>

<l>Tokay shall flow at once, to fill you!</l>

<Speaker>ALTMAYER</Speaker>

<l>No—look me, Sirs, straight in the face!</l>
<l>I see you have your fun at our expense.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>O no! with gentlemen of such pretence,</l>
<l>That were to venture far, indeed.</l>
<l>Speak out, and make your choice with speed! With what a vintage can I serve you?</l>

<Speaker>ALTMAYER</Speaker>

<l>With any—only satisfy our need.</l>

<l>(After the holes have been bored and plugged)</l>

<l>MEPHISTOPHELES (with singular gestures)</l>

<l>Grapes the vine-stem bears,</l>
<l>Horns the he-goat wears!</l>
<l>The grapes are juicy, the vines are wood,</l>
<l>The wooden table gives wine as good!</l>
<l>Into the depths of Nature peer,—</l>
<l>Only believe there&apos;s a miracle here!</l>
<l>Now draw the stoppers, and drink your fill!</l>

<Speaker>ALL</Speaker>

<l>(as they draw out the stoppers, and the wine which has been</l>
<l>desired flows into the glass of each)</l>

<l>O beautiful fountain, that flows at will!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>But have a care that you nothing spill!</l>

<l>(They drink repeatedly.)</l>

<Speaker>ALL (sing</Speaker>

<l>As &apos;twere five hundred hogs, we feel</l>
<l>So cannibalic jolly!</l>
<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>See, now, the race is happy—it is free!</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>To leave them is my inclination.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Take notice, first! their bestiality</l>
<l>Will make a brilliant demonstration.</l>

<Speaker>SIEBEL</Speaker>

<l>(drinks carelessly: the wine spills upon the earth, and turns to</l>
<Speaker>flame</Speaker>

<l>Help! Fire! Help! Hell-fire is sent!</l>

<l>MEPHISTOPHELES (charming away the flame)</l>

<l>Be quiet, friendly element!</l>

<l>(To the revellers)</l>

<l>A bit of purgatory &apos;twas for this time, merely.</l>

<Speaker>SIEBEL</Speaker>

<l>What mean you? Wait!—you&apos;ll pay for&apos;t dearly!</l>
<l>You&apos;ll know us, to your detriment.</l>

<Speaker>FROSCH</Speaker>

<l>Don&apos;t try that game a second time upon us!</l>

<Speaker>ALTMAYER</Speaker>

<l>I think we&apos;d better send him packing quietly.</l>

<Speaker>SIEBEL</Speaker>

<l>What, Sir! you dare to make so free,</l>
<l>And play your hocus-pocus on us!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Be still, old wine-tub.</l>

<Speaker>SIEBEL</Speaker>

<l>Broomstick, you!</l>
<l>You face it out, impertinent and heady?</l>

<Speaker>BRANDER</Speaker>

<l>Just wait! a shower of blows is ready.</l>

<Speaker>ALTMAYER</Speaker>

<l>(draws a stopper out of the table: fire flies in his face.)</l>
<l>I burn! I burn!</l>

<Speaker>SIEBEL</Speaker>

<l>&apos;Tis magic! Strike—</l>
<l>The knave is outlawed! Cut him as you like!</l>
<l>(They draw their knives, and rush upon MEPHISTOPHELES.)</l>

<l>MEPHISTOPHELES (with solemn gestures)</l>

<l>False word and form of air,</l>
<l>Change place, and sense ensnare!</l>
<l>Be here—and there!</l>
<l>(They stand amazed and look at each other.)</l>

<Speaker>ALTMAYER</Speaker>

<l>Where am I? What a lovely land!</l>

<Speaker>FROSCH</Speaker>

<l>Vines? Can I trust my eyes?</l>

<Speaker>SIEBEL</Speaker>

<l>And purple grapes at hand!</l>

<Speaker>BRANDER</Speaker>

<l>Here, over this green arbor bending,</l>
<l>See what a vine! what grapes depending!</l>

<l>(He takes SIEBEL by the nose: the others do the same reciprocally,</l>
<l>and raise their knives.)</l>

<l>MEPHISTOPHELES (as above)</l>

<l>Loose, Error, from their eyes the band,</l>
<l>And how the Devil jests, be now enlightened!</l>

<l>(He disappears with FAUST: the revellers start and separate.)</l>

<Speaker>SIEBEL</Speaker>

<l>What happened?</l>

<Speaker>ALTMAYER</Speaker>

<Speaker>How</Speaker>

<Speaker>FROSCH</Speaker>

<l>Was that your nose I tightened?</l>

<l>BRANDER (to SIEBEL)</l>

<l>And yours that still I have in hand?</l>

<Speaker>ALTMAYER</Speaker>

<l>It was a blow that went through every limb!</l>
<l>Give me a chair! I sink! my senses swim.</l>

<Speaker>FROSCH</Speaker>

<l>But what has happened, tell me now?</l>

<Speaker>SIEBEL</Speaker>

<l>Where is he? If I catch the scoundrel hiding,</l>
<l>He shall not leave alive, I vow.</l>

<Speaker>ALTMAYER</Speaker>

<l>I saw him with these eyes upon a wine-cask riding</l>
<l>Out of the cellar-door, just now.</l>
<l>Still in my feet the fright like lead is weighing.</l>
<l>(He turns towards the table.)</l>

<l>Why! If the fount of wine should still be playing?</l>

<Speaker>SIEBEL</Speaker>

<l>&apos;Twas all deceit, and lying, false design!</l>

<Speaker>FROSCH</Speaker>

<l>And yet it seemed as I were drinking wine.</l>

<Speaker>BRANDER</Speaker>

<l>But with the grapes how was it, pray?</l>

<Speaker>ALTMAYER</Speaker>

<l>Shall one believe no miracles, just say!</l>

<Scene> VI </Scene>
<l>WITCHES&apos; KITCHEN</l>

<l>(Upon a low hearth stands a great caldron, under which a fire</l>
<l>is burning. Various figures appear in the vapors which</l>
<l>rise from the caldron. An ape sits beside it, skims it, and</l>
<l>watches lest it boil over. The he-ape, with the young</l>
<l>ones, sits near and warms himself. Ceiling and walls are</l>
<l>covered with the most fantastic witch-implements.)</l>

<Speaker>FAUST MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>These crazy signs of witches&apos; craft repel me!</l>
<l>I shall recover, dost thou tell me,</l>
<l>Through this insane, chaotic play?</l>
<l>From an old hag shall I demand assistance?</l>
<l>And will her foul mess take away</l>
<l>Full thirty years from my existence?</l>
<l>Woe&apos;s me, canst thou naught better find!</l>
<l>Another baffled hope must be lamented:</l>
<l>Has Nature, then, and has a noble mind</l>
<l>Not any potent balsam yet invented?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Once more, my friend, thou talkest sensibly.</l>
<l>There is, to make thee young, a simpler mode and apter;</l>
<l>But in another book &apos;tis writ for thee,</l>
<l>And is a most eccentric chapter.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Yet will I know it.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Good! the method is revealed</l>
<l>Without or gold or magic or physician.</l>
<l>Betake thyself to yonder field,</l>
<l>There hoe and dig, as thy condition;</l>
<l>Restrain thyself, thy sense and will</l>
<l>Within a narrow sphere to flourish;</l>
<l>With unmixed food thy body nourish;</l>
<l>Live with the ox as ox, and think it not a theft</l>
<l>That thou manur&apos;st the acre which thou reapest;—</l>
<l>That, trust me, is the best mode left,</l>
<l>Whereby for eighty years thy youth thou keepest!</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>I am not used to that; I cannot stoop to try it—</l>
<l>To take the spade in hand, and ply it.</l>
<l>The narrow being suits me not at all.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Then to thine aid the witch must call.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Wherefore the hag, and her alone?</l>
<l>Canst thou thyself not brew the potion?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>That were a charming sport, I own:</l>
<l>I&apos;d build a thousand bridges meanwhile, I&apos;ve a notion.</l>
<l>Not Art and Science serve, alone;</l>
<l>Patience must in the work be shown.</l>
<l>Long is the calm brain active in creation;</l>
<l>Time, only, strengthens the fine fermentation.</l>
<l>And all, belonging thereunto,</l>
<l>Is rare and strange, howe&apos;er you take it:</l>
<l>The Devil taught the thing, &apos;tis true,</l>
<l>And yet the Devil cannot make it.</l>
<l>(Perceiving the Animals)</l>
<l>See, what a delicate race they be!</l>
<l>That is the maid! the man is he!</l>
<l>(To the Animals)</l>
<l>It seems the mistress has gone away?</l>

<Speaker>THE ANIMALS</Speaker>

<l>Carousing, to-day!</l>
<l>Off and about,</l>
<l>By the chimney out!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>What time takes she for dissipating?</l>

<Speaker>THE ANIMALS</Speaker>

<l>While we to warm our paws are waiting.</l>

<l>MEPHISTOPHELES (to FAUST)</l>

<l>How findest thou the tender creatures?</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Absurder than I ever yet did see.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Why, just such talk as this, for me,</l>
<l>Is that which has the most attractive features!</l>

<l>(To the Animals)</l>

<l>But tell me now, ye cursed puppets,</l>
<l>Why do ye stir the porridge so?</l>

<Speaker>THE ANIMALS</Speaker>

<l>We&apos;re cooking watery soup for beggars.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Then a great public you can show.</l>

<l>THE HE-APE</l>

<l>(comes up and fawns on MEPHISTOPHELES)</l>

<l>O cast thou the dice!</l>
<l>Make me rich in a trice,</l>
<l>Let me win in good season!</l>
<l>Things are badly controlled,</l>
<l>And had I but gold,</l>
<l>So had I my reason.</l>
<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>How would the ape be sure his luck enhances.</l>
<l>Could he but try the lottery&apos;s chances!</l>

<l>(In the meantime the young apes have been playing with a</l>
<l>large ball, which they now roll forward.)</l>

<l>THE HE-APE</l>

<l>The world&apos;s the ball:</l>
<l>Doth rise and fall,</l>
<l>And roll incessant:</l>
<l>Like glass doth ring,</l>
<l>A hollow thing,—</l>
<l>How soon will&apos;t spring,</l>
<l>And drop, quiescent?</l>
<l>Here bright it gleams,</l>
<l>Here brighter seems:</l>
<l>I live at present!</l>
<l>Dear son, I say,</l>
<l>Keep thou away!</l>
<l>Thy doom is spoken!</l>
<l>&apos;Tis made of clay,</l>
<l>And will be broken.</l>
<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>What means the sieve?</l>

<l>THE HE-APE (taking it down)</l>

<l>Wert thou the thief,</l>
<l>I&apos;d know him and shame him.</l>

<l>(He runs to the SHE-APE, and lets her look through it.)</l>

<l>Look through the sieve!</l>
<l>Know&apos;st thou the thief,</l>
<l>And darest not name him?</l>
<l>MEPHISTOPHELES (approaching the fire)</l>

<l>And what&apos;s this pot?</l>

<l>HE-APE AND SHE-APE</l>

<l>The fool knows it not!</l>
<l>He knows not the pot,</l>
<l>He knows not the kettle!</l>
<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Impertinent beast!</l>

<l>THE HE-APE</l>

<l>Take the brush here, at least,</l>
<l>And sit down on the settle!</l>

<l>(He invites MEPHISTOPHELES to sit down.)</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>(who during all this time has been standing before a mirror,</l>
<l>now approaching and now retreating from it)</l>

<l>What do I see? What heavenly form revealed</l>
<l>Shows through the glass from Magic&apos;s fair dominions!</l>
<l>O lend me, Love, the swiftest of thy pinions,</l>
<l>And bear me to her beauteous field!</l>
<l>Ah, if I leave this spot with fond designing,</l>
<l>If I attempt to venture near,</l>
<l>Dim, as through gathering mist, her charms appear!—</l>
<l>A woman&apos;s form, in beauty shining!</l>
<l>Can woman, then, so lovely be?</l>
<l>And must I find her body, there reclining,</l>
<l>Of all the heavens the bright epitome?</l>
<l>Can Earth with such a thing be mated?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Why, surely, if a God first plagues Himself six days,</l>
<l>Then, self-contented, Bravo! says,</l>
<l>Must something clever be created.</l>
<l>This time, thine eyes be satiate!</l>
<l>I&apos;ll yet detect thy sweetheart and ensnare her,</l>
<l>And blest is he, who has the lucky fate,</l>
<l>Some day, as bridegroom, home to bear her.</l>

<l>(FAUST gazes continually in the mirror. MEPHISTOPHELES,</l>
<l>stretching himself out on the settle, and playing with the</l>
<l>brush, continues to speak.)</l>

<l>So sit I, like the King upon his throne:</l>
<l>I hold the sceptre, here,—and lack the crown alone.</l>

<Speaker>THE ANIMALS</Speaker>

<l>(who up to this time have been making all kinds of fantastic</l>
<l>movements together bring a crown to MEPHISTOPHELES</l>
<l>with great noise.)</l>

<l>O be thou so good</l>
<l>With sweat and with blood</l>
<l>The crown to belime!</l>
<l>(They handle the crown awkwardly and break it into two</l>
<l>pieces, with which they spring around.)</l>

<l>&apos;Tis done, let it be!</l>
<l>We speak and we see,</l>
<l>We hear and we rhyme!</l>
<l>FAUST (before the mirror)</l>

<l>Woe&apos;s me! I fear to lose my wits.</l>

<l>MEPHISTOPHELES (pointing to the Animals)</l>

<l>My own head, now, is really nigh to sinking.</l>

<Speaker>THE ANIMALS</Speaker>

<l>If lucky our hits,</l>
<l>And everything fits,</l>
<l>&apos;Tis thoughts, and we&apos;re thinking!</l>
<l>FAUST (as above)</l>

<l>My bosom burns with that sweet vision;</l>
<l>Let us, with speed, away from here!</l>

<l>MEPHISTOPHELES (in the same attitude)</l>

<l>One must, at least, make this admission—</l>
<l>They&apos;re poets, genuine and sincere.</l>

<l>(The caldron, which the SHE-APE has up to this time neglected</l>
<l>to watch, begins to boil over: there ensues a great flame,</l>
<l>which blazes out the chimney. The WITCH comes careering</l>
<l>down through the flame, with terrible cries.)</l>

<Speaker>THE WITCH</Speaker>

<l>Ow! ow! ow! ow!</l>
<l>The damnéd beast—the curséd sow!</l>
<l>To leave the kettle, and singe the Frau!</l>
<l>Accurséd fere!</l>
<l>(Perceiving FAUST and MEPHISTOPHELES.)</l>

<l>What is that here?</l>
<l>Who are you here?</l>
<l>What want you thus?</l>
<l>Who sneaks to us?</l>
<l>The fire-pain</l>
<l>Burn bone and brain!</l>
<l>(She plunges the skimming-ladle into the caldron, and scatters</l>
<l>flames towards FAUST, MEPHISTOPHELES, and the Animals.</l>
<l>The Animals whimper.)</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>(reversing the brush, which he has been holding in his hand,</l>
<l>and striding among the jars and glasses)</l>

<l>In two! in two!</l>
<l>There lies the brew!</l>
<l>There lies the glass!</l>
<l>The joke will pass,</l>
<l>As time, foul ass!</l>
<l>To the singing of thy crew.</l>
<l>(As the WITCH starts back, full of wrath and horror)</l>

<l>Ha! know&apos;st thou me? Abomination, thou!</l>
<l>Know&apos;st thou, at last, thy Lord and Master?</l>
<l>What hinders me from smiting now</l>
<l>Thee and thy monkey-sprites with fell disaster?</l>
<l>Hast for the scarlet coat no reverence?</l>
<l>Dost recognize no more the tall cock&apos;s-feather?</l>
<l>Have I concealed this countenance?—</l>
<l>Must tell my name, old face of leather?</l>

<Speaker>THE WITCH</Speaker>

<l>O pardon, Sir, the rough salute!</l>
<l>Yet I perceive no cloven foot;</l>
<l>And both your ravens, where are they now?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>This time, I&apos;ll let thee &apos;scape the debt;</l>
<l>For since we two together met,</l>
<l>&apos;Tis verily full many a day now.</l>
<l>Culture, which smooth the whole world licks,</l>
<l>Also unto the Devil sticks.</l>
<l>The days of that old Northern phantom now are over:</l>
<l>Where canst thou horns and tail and claws discover?</l>
<l>And, as regards the foot, which I can&apos;t spare, in truth,</l>
<l>&apos;Twould only make the people shun me;</l>
<l>Therefore I&apos;ve worn, like many a spindly youth,</l>
<l>False calves these many years upon me.</l>

<l>THE WITCH (dancing)</l>

<l>Reason and sense forsake my brain,</l>
<l>Since I behold Squire Satan here again!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Woman, from such a name refrain!</l>

<Speaker>THE WITCH</Speaker>

<l>Why so? What has it done to thee?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>It&apos;s long been written in the Book of Fable;</l>
<l>Yet, therefore, no whit better men we see:</l>
<l>The Evil One has left, the evil ones are stable.</l>
<l>Sir Baron call me thou, then is the matter good;</l>
<l>A cavalier am I, like others in my bearing.</l>
<l>Thou hast no doubt about my noble blood:</l>
<l>See, here&apos;s the coat-of-arms that I am wearing!</l>

<l>(He makes an indecent gesture.)</l>

<l>THE WITCH (laughs immoderately)</l>

<l>Ha! ha! That&apos;s just your way, I know:</l>
<l>A rogue you are, and you were always so.</l>

<l>MEPHISTOPHELES (to FAUST)</l>

<l>My friend, take proper heed, I pray!</l>
<l>To manage witches, this is just the way.</l>

<Speaker>THE WITCH</Speaker>

<l>Wherein, Sirs, can I be of use?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Give us a goblet of the well-known juice!</l>
<l>But, I must beg you, of the oldest brewage;</l>
<l>The years a double strength produce.</l>

<Speaker>THE WITCH</Speaker>

<l>With all my heart! Now, here&apos;s a bottle,</l>
<l>Wherefrom, sometimes, I wet my throttle,</l>
<l>Which, also, not the slightest, stinks;</l>
<l>And willingly a glass I&apos;ll fill him.</l>

<Speaker>(Whispering</Speaker>

<l>Yet, if this man without due preparation drinks,</l>
<l>As well thou know&apos;st, within an hour &apos;twill kill him.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>He is a friend of mine, with whom it will agree,</l>
<l>And he deserves thy kitchen&apos;s best potation:</l>
<l>Come, draw thy circle, speak thine adjuration,</l>
<l>And fill thy goblet full and free!</l>

<Speaker>THE WITCH</Speaker>

<l>(with fantastic gestures draws a circle and places mysterious</l>
<l>articles therein; meanwhile the glasses begin to ring, the</l>
<l>caldron to sound, and make a musical accompaniment.</l>
<l>Finally she brings a great book, and stations in the circle</l>
<l>the Apes, who are obliged to serve as reading-desk, and to</l>
<l>hold the torches. She then beckons FAUST to approach.)</l>

<l>FAUST (to MEPHISTOPHELES)</l>

<l>Now, what shall come of this? the creatures antic,</l>
<l>The crazy stuff, the gestures frantic,—</l>
<l>All the repulsive cheats I view,—</l>
<l>Are known to me, and hated, too.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>O, nonsense! That&apos;s a thing for laughter;</l>
<l>Don&apos;t be so terribly severe!</l>
<l>She juggles you as doctor now, that, after,</l>
<l>The beverage may work the proper cheer.</l>

<l>(He persuades FAUST to step into the circle.)</l>

<Speaker>THE WITCH</Speaker>

<l>(begins to declaim, with much emphasis, from the book)</l>

<l>See, thus it&apos;s done!</l>
<l>Make ten of one,</l>
<l>And two let be,</l>
<l>Make even three,</l>
<l>And rich thou &apos;It be.</l>
<l>Cast o&apos;er the four!</l>
<l>From five and six</l>
<l>(The witch&apos;s tricks)</l>
<l>Make seven and eight,</l>
<l>&apos;Tis finished straight!</l>
<l>And nine is one,</l>
<l>And ten is none.</l>
<l>This is the witch&apos;s once-one&apos;s-one!</l>
<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>She talks like one who raves in fever.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Thou&apos;lt hear much more before we leave her.</l>
<l>&apos;Tis all the same: the book I can repeat,</l>
<l>Such time I&apos;ve squandered o&apos;er the history:</l>
<l>A contradiction thus complete</l>
<l>Is always for the wise, no less than fools, a mystery.</l>
<l>The art is old and new, for verily</l>
<l>All ages have been taught the matter,—</l>
<l>By Three and One, and One and Three,</l>
<l>Error instead of Truth to scatter.</l>
<l>They prate and teach, and no one interferes;</l>
<l>All from the fellowship of fools are shrinking.</l>
<l>Man usually believes, if only words he hears,</l>
<l>That also with them goes material for thinking!</l>

<l>THE WITCH (continues)</l>

<l>The lofty skill</l>
<l>Of Science, still</l>
<l>From all men deeply hidden!</l>
<l>Who takes no thought,</l>
<l>To him &apos;tis brought,</l>
<l>&apos;Tis given unsought, unbidden!</l>
<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>What nonsense she declaims before us!</l>
<l>My head is nigh to split, I fear:</l>
<l>It seems to me as if I hear</l>
<l>A hundred thousand fools in chorus.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>O Sibyl excellent, enough of adjuration!</l>
<l>But hither bring us thy potation,</l>
<l>And quickly fill the beaker to the brim!</l>
<l>This drink will bring my friend no injuries:</l>
<l>He is a man of manifold degrees,</l>
<l>And many draughts are known to him.</l>

<l>(The WITCH, with many ceremonies, pours the drink into a</l>
<l>cup; as FAUST sets it to his lips, a light flame arises.)</l>

<l>Down with it quickly! Drain it off!</l>
<l>&apos;Twill warm thy heart with new desire:</l>
<l>Art with the Devil hand and glove,</l>
<l>And wilt thou be afraid of fire?</l>

<l>(The WITCH breaks the circle: FAUST steps forth.)</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>And now, away! Thou dar&apos;st not rest.</l>

<Speaker>THE WITCH</Speaker>

<l>And much good may the liquor do thee!</l>

<l>MEPHISTOPHELES (to the WITCH)</l>

<l>Thy wish be on Walpurgis Night expressed;</l>
<l>What boon I have, shall then be given unto thee.</l>

<Speaker>THE WITCH</Speaker>

<l>Here is a song, which, if you sometimes sing,</l>
<l>You&apos;ll find it of peculiar operation.</l>

<l>MEPHISTOPHELES (to FAUST)</l>

<l>Come, walk at once! A rapid occupation</l>
<l>Must start the needful perspiration,</l>
<l>And through thy frame the liquor&apos;s potence fling.</l>
<l>The noble indolence I&apos;ll teach thee then to treasure,</l>
<l>And soon thou&apos;lt be aware, with keenest thrills of pleasure,</l>
<l>How Cupid stirs and leaps, on light and restless wing.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>One rapid glance within the mirror give me,</l>
<l>How beautiful that woman-form!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>No, no! The paragon of all, believe me,</l>
<l>Thou soon shalt see, alive and warm.</l>

<Speaker>(Aside</Speaker>

<l>Thou&apos;lt find, this drink thy blood compelling,</l>
<l>Each woman beautiful as Helen!</l>

<Scene> VII </Scene>
<Speaker>STREET</Speaker>

<l>FAUST MARGARET (passing by)</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Fair lady, let it not offend you,</l>
<l>That arm and escort I would lend you!</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>I&apos;m neither lady, neither fair,</l>
<l>And home I can go without your care.</l>

<l>[She releases herself, and exit.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>By Heaven, the girl is wondrous fair!</l>
<l>Of all I&apos;ve seen, beyond compare;</l>
<l>So sweetly virtuous and pure,</l>
<l>And yet a little pert, be sure!</l>
<l>The lip so red, the cheek&apos;s clear dawn,</l>

<l>I&apos;ll not forget while the world rolls on!</l>
<l>How she cast down her timid eyes,</l>
<l>Deep in my heart imprinted lies:</l>
<l>How short and sharp of speech was she,</l>
<l>Why, &apos;twas a real ecstasy!</l>

<l>(MEPHISTOPHELES enters)</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Hear, of that girl I&apos;d have possession!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Which, then?</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>The one who just went by.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>She, there? She&apos;s coming from confession,</l>
<l>Of every sin absolved; for I,</l>
<l>Behind her chair, was listening nigh.</l>
<l>So innocent is she, indeed,</l>
<l>That to confess she had no need.</l>
<l>I have no power o&apos;er souls so green.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>And yet, she&apos;s older than fourteen.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>How now! You&apos;re talking like Jack Rake,</l>
<l>Who every flower for himself would take,</l>
<l>And fancies there are no favors more,</l>
<l>Nor honors, save for him in store;</l>
<l>Yet always doesn&apos;t the thing succeed.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Most Worthy Pedagogue, take heed!</l>
<l>Let not a word of moral law be spoken!</l>
<l>I claim, I tell thee, all my right;</l>
<l>And if that image of delight</l>
<l>Rest not within mine arms to-night,</l>
<l>At midnight is our compact broken.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>But think, the chances of the case!</l>
<l>I need, at least, a fortnight&apos;s space,</l>
<l>To find an opportune occasion.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Had I but seven hours for all,</l>
<l>I should not on the Devil call,</l>
<l>But win her by my own persuasion.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>You almost like a Frenchman prate;</l>
<l>Yet, pray, don&apos;t take it as annoyance!</l>
<l>Why, all at once, exhaust the joyance?</l>
<l>Your bliss is by no means so great</l>
<l>As if you&apos;d use, to get control,</l>
<l>All sorts of tender rigmarole,</l>
<l>And knead and shape her to your thought,</l>
<l>As in Italian tales &apos;tis taught.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Without that, I have appetite.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>But now, leave jesting out of sight!</l>
<l>I tell you, once for all, that speed</l>
<l>With this fair girl will not succeed;</l>
<l>By storm she cannot captured be;</l>
<l>We must make use of strategy.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Get me something the angel keeps!</l>
<l>Lead me thither where she sleeps!</l>
<l>Get me a kerchief from her breast,—</l>
<l>A garter that her knee has pressed!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>That you may see how much I&apos;d fain</l>
<l>Further and satisfy your pain,</l>
<l>We will no longer lose a minute;</l>
<l>I&apos;ll find her room to-day, and take you in it.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>And shall I see—possess her?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<Speaker>No</Speaker>
<l>Unto a neighbor she must go,</l>
<l>And meanwhile thou, alone, mayst glow</l>
<l>With every hope of future pleasure,</l>
<l>Breathing her atmosphere in fullest measure.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Can we go thither?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>&apos;Tis too early yet.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>A gift for her I bid thee get!</l>
<stage>[Exit</stage>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Presents at once? That&apos;s good: he&apos;s certain to get at her!</l>
<l>Full many a pleasant place I know,</l>
<l>And treasures, buried long ago:</l>
<l>I must, perforce, look up the matter. [Exit.</l>

<Scene> VIII </Scene>
<l>EVENING A SMALL, NEATLY KEPT CHAMBER</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>(plaiting and binding up the braids of her hair)</l>

<l>I&apos;d something give, could I but say</l>
<l>Who was that gentleman, to-day.</l>
<l>Surely a gallant man was he,</l>
<l>And of a noble family;</l>
<l>And much could I in his face behold,—</l>
<l>And he wouldn&apos;t, else, have been so bold!</l>

<stage>[Exit</stage>
<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES FAUST</Speaker>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Come in, but gently: follow me!</l>

<l>FAUST (after a moment&apos;s silence)</l>

<l>Leave me alone, I beg of thee!</l>

<l>MEPHISTOPHELES (prying about)</l>

<l>Not every girl keeps things so neat.</l>

<l>FAUST (looking around)</l>

<l>O welcome, twilight soft and sweet,</l>
<l>That breathes throughout this hallowed shrine!</l>
<l>Sweet pain of love, bind thou with fetters fleet</l>
<l>The heart that on the dew of hope must pine!</l>
<l>How all around a sense impresses</l>
<l>Of quiet, order, and content!</l>
<l>This poverty what bounty blesses!</l>
<l>What bliss within this narrow den is pent!</l>

<l>(He throws himself into a leathern arm-chair near the bed.)</l>

<l>Receive me, thou, that in thine open arms</l>
<l>Departed joy and pain wert wont to gather!</l>
<l>How oft the children, with their ruddy charms,</l>
<l>Hung here, around this throne, where sat the father!</l>
<l>Perchance my love, amid the childish band,</l>
<l>Grateful for gifts the Holy Christmas gave her,</l>
<l>Here meekly kissed the grandsire&apos;s withered hand.</l>
<l>I feel, O maid! thy very soul</l>
<l>Of order and content around me whisper,—</l>
<l>Which leads thee with its motherly control,</l>
<l>The cloth upon thy board bids smoothly thee unroll,</l>
<l>The sand beneath thy feet makes whiter, crisper.</l>
<l>O dearest hand, to thee &apos;tis given</l>
<l>To change this hut into a lower heaven!</l>
<l>And here!</l>

<l>(He lifts one of the bed-curtains.)</l>

<l>What sweetest thrill is in my blood!</l>
<l>Here could I spend whole hours, delaying:</l>
<l>Here Nature shaped, as if in sportive playing,</l>
<l>The angel blossom from the bud.</l>
<l>Here lay the child, with Life&apos;s warm essence</l>
<l>The tender bosom filled and fair,</l>
<l>And here was wrought, through holier, purer presence,</l>
<l>The form diviner beings wear!</l>

<l>And I? What drew me here with power?</l>
<l>How deeply am I moved, this hour!</l>
<l>What seek I? Why so full my heart, and sore?</l>
<l>Miserable Faust! I know thee now no more.</l>

<l>Is there a magic vapor here?</l>
<l>I came, with lust of instant pleasure,</l>
<l>And lie dissolved in dreams of love&apos;s sweet leisure!</l>
<l>Are we the sport of every changeful atmosphere?</l>

<l>And if, this moment, came she in to me,</l>
<l>How would I for the fault atonement render!</l>
<l>How small the giant lout would be,</l>
<l>Prone at her feet, relaxed and tender!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Be quick! I see her there, returning.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Go! go! I never will retreat.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Here is a casket, not unmeet,</l>
<l>Which elsewhere I have just been earning.</l>
<l>Here, set it in the press, with haste!</l>
<l>I swear, &apos;twill turn her head, to spy it:</l>
<l>Some baubles I therein had placed,</l>
<l>That you might win another by it.</l>
<l>True, child is child, and play is play.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>I know not, should I do it?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Ask you, pray?</l>

<l>Yourself, perhaps, would keep the bubble?</l>
<l>Then I suggest, &apos;twere fair and just</l>
<l>To spare the lovely day your lust,</l>
<l>And spare to me the further trouble.</l>
<l>You are not miserly, I trust?</l>
<l>I rub my hands, in expectation tender—</l>

<l>(He places the casket in the press, and locks it again.)</l>

<l>Now quick, away!</l>
<l>The sweet young maiden to betray,</l>
<l>So that by wish and will you bend her;</l>
<l>And you look as though</l>
<l>To the lecture-hall you were forced to go,—</l>
<l>As if stood before you, gray and loath,</l>
<l>Physics and Metaphysics both!</l>
<l>But away!</l>

<stage>[Exeunt</stage>

<l>MARGARET (with a lamp)</l>

<l>It is so close, so sultry, here!</l>

<l>(She opens the window)</l>

<l>And yet &apos;tis not so warm outside.</l>
<l>I feel, I know not why, such fear!—</l>
<l>Would mother came!—where can she bide?</l>
<l>My body&apos;s chill and shuddering,—</l>
<l>I&apos;m but a silly, fearsome thing!</l>

<l>(She begins to sing while undressing)</l>

<l>There was a King in Thule,</l>
<l>Was faithful till the grave,—</l>
<l>To whom his mistress, dying,</l>
<l>A golden goblet gave.</l>

<l>Naught was to him more precious;</l>
<l>He drained it at every bout:</l>
<l>His eyes with tears ran over,</l>
<l>As oft as he drank thereout.</l>

<l>When came his time of dying,</l>
<l>The towns in his land he told,</l>
<l>Naught else to his heir denying</l>
<l>Except the goblet of gold.</l>

<l>He sat at the royal banquet</l>
<l>With his knights of high degree,</l>
<l>In the lofty hall of his fathers</l>
<l>In the Castle by the Sea.</l>

<l>There stood the old carouser,</l>
<l>And drank the last life-glow;</l>
<l>And hurled the hallowed goblet</l>
<l>Into the tide below.</l>

<l>He saw it plunging and filling,</l>
<l>And sinking deep in the sea:</l>
<l>Then fell his eyelids forever,</l>
<l>And never more drank he!</l>
<l>(She opens the press in order to arrange her clothes, and perceives</l>
<l>the casket of jewels.)</l>

<l>How comes that lovely casket here to me?</l>
<l>I locked the press, most certainly.</l>
<l>&apos;Tis truly wonderful! What can within it be?</l>
<l>Perhaps &apos;twas brought by some one as a pawn,</l>
<l>And mother gave a loan thereon?</l>
<l>And here there hangs a key to fit:</l>
<l>I have a mind to open it.</l>
<l>What is that? God in Heaven! Whence came</l>
<l>Such things? Never beheld I aught so fair!</l>
<l>Rich ornaments, such as a noble dame</l>
<l>On highest holidays might wear!</l>
<l>How would the pearl-chain suit my hair?</l>
<l>Ah, who may all this splendor own?</l>

<l>(She adorns herself with the jewelry, and steps before the</l>
<Speaker>mirror</Speaker>

<l>Were but the ear-rings mine, alone!</l>
<l>One has at once another air.</l>
<l>What helps one&apos;s beauty, youthful blood?</l>
<l>One may possess them, well and good;</l>
<l>But none the more do others care.</l>
<l>They praise us half in pity, sure:</l>
<l>To gold still tends,</l>
<l>On gold depends</l>
<l>All, all! Alas, we poor!</l>

<Scene> IX </Scene>
<Speaker>PROMENADE</Speaker>

<l>(FAUST, walking thoughtfully up and down. To him MEPHISTOPHELES.)</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>By all love ever rejected! By hell-fire hot and unsparing!</l>
<l>I wish I knew something worse, that I might use it for</l>
<Speaker>swearing</Speaker>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>What ails thee? What is&apos;t gripes thee, elf?</l>
<l>A face like thine beheld I never.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>I would myself unto the Devil deliver,</l>
<l>If I were not a Devil myself!</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Thy head is out of order, sadly:</l>
<l>It much becomes thee to be raving madly.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Just think, the pocket of a priest should get</l>
<l>The trinkets left for Margaret!</l>
<l>The mother saw them, and, instanter,</l>
<l>A secret dread began to haunt her.</l>
<l>Keen scent has she for tainted air;</l>
<l>She snuffs within her book of prayer,</l>
<l>And smells each article, to see</l>
<l>If sacred or profane it be;</l>
<l>So here she guessed, from every gem,</l>
<l>That not much blessing came with them.</l>
<l>&quot;My child,&quot; she said, &quot;ill-gotten good</l>
<l>Ensnares the soul, consumes the blood.</l>
<l>Before the Mother of God we&apos;ll lay it;</l>
<l>With heavenly manna she&apos;ll repay it!&quot;</l>
<l>But Margaret thought, with sour grimace,</l>
<l>&quot;A gift-horse is not out of place,</l>
<l>And, truly! godless cannot be</l>
<l>The one who brought such things to me.&quot;</l>
<l>A parson came, by the mother bidden:</l>
<l>He saw, at once, where the game was hidden,</l>
<l>And viewed it with a favor stealthy.</l>
<l>He spake: &quot;That is the proper view,—</l>
<l>Who overcometh, winneth too.</l>
<l>The Holy Church has a stomach healthy:</l>
<l>Hath eaten many a land as forfeit,</l>
<l>And never yet complained of surfeit:</l>
<l>The Church alone, beyond all question,</l>
<l>Has for ill-gotten goods the right digestion.&quot;</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>A general practice is the same,</l>
<l>Which Jew and King may also claim.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Then bagged the spangles, chains, and rings,</l>
<l>As if but toadstools were the things,</l>
<l>And thanked no less, and thanked no more</l>
<l>Than if a sack of nuts he bore,—</l>
<l>Promised them fullest heavenly pay,</l>
<l>And deeply edified were they.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>And Margaret?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Sits unrestful still,</l>
<l>And knows not what she should, or will;</l>
<l>Thinks on the jewels, day and night,</l>
<l>But more on him who gave her such delight.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>The darling&apos;s sorrow gives me pain.</l>
<l>Get thou a set for her again!</l>
<l>The first was not a great display.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>O yes, the gentleman finds it all child&apos;s-play!</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Fix and arrange it to my will;</l>
<l>And on her neighbor try thy skill!</l>
<l>Don&apos;t be a Devil stiff as paste,</l>
<l>But get fresh jewels to her taste!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Yes, gracious Sir, in all obedience!</l>

<l>[Exit FAUST.</l>

<l>Such an enamored fool in air would blow</l>
<l>Sun, moon, and all the starry legions,</l>
<l>To give his sweetheart a diverting show.</l>

<stage>[Exit</stage>

<Scene> X </Scene>
<l>THE NEIGHBOR&apos;S HOUSE</l>

<Speaker>MARTHA (solus</Speaker>

<l>God forgive my husband, yet he</l>
<l>Hasn&apos;t done his duty by me!</l>
<l>Off in the world he went straightway,—</l>
<l>Left me lie in the straw where I lay.</l>
<l>And, truly, I did naught to fret him:</l>
<l>God knows I loved, and can&apos;t forget him!</l>

<l>(She weeps.)</l>

<l>Perhaps he&apos;s even dead! Ah, woe!—</l>
<l>Had I a certificate to show!</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET (comes</Speaker>

<l>Dame Martha!</l>

<Speaker>MARTHA</Speaker>

<l>Margaret! what&apos;s happened thee?</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>I scarce can stand, my knees are trembling!</l>
<l>I find a box, the first resembling,</l>
<l>Within my press! Of ebony,—</l>
<l>And things, all splendid to behold,</l>
<l>And richer far than were the old.</l>

<Speaker>MARTHA</Speaker>

<l>You mustn&apos;t tell it to your mother!</l>
<l>&apos;Twould go to the priest, as did the other.</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>Ah, look and see—just look and see!</l>

<l>MARTHA (adorning her)</l>

<l>O, what a blessed luck for thee!</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>But, ah! in the streets I dare not bear them,</l>
<l>Nor in the church be seen to wear them.</l>

<Speaker>MARTHA</Speaker>

<l>Yet thou canst often this way wander,</l>
<l>And secretly the jewels don,</l>
<l>Walk up and down an hour, before the mirror yonder,—</l>
<l>We&apos;ll have our private joy thereon.</l>
<l>And then a chance will come, a holiday,</l>
<l>When, piece by piece, can one the things abroad display,</l>
<l>A chain at first, then other ornament:</l>
<l>Thy mother will not see, and stories we&apos;ll invent.</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>Whoever could have brought me things so precious?</l>
<l>That something&apos;s wrong, I feel suspicious.</l>

<l>(A knock)</l>

<l>Good Heaven! My mother can that have been?</l>

<l>MARTHA (peeping through the blind)</l>

<l>&apos;Tis some strange gentleman.—Come in!</l>

<l>(MEPHISTOPHELES enters.)</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>That I so boldly introduce me,</l>
<l>I beg you, ladies, to excuse me.</l>

<l>(Steps back reverently, on seeing MARGARET.)</l>

<l>For Martha Schwerdtlein I&apos;d inquire!</l>

<Speaker>MARTHA</Speaker>

<l>I&apos;m she: what does the gentleman desire?</l>

<l>MEPHISTOPHELES (aside to her)</l>

<l>It is enough that you are she:</l>
<l>You&apos;ve a visitor of high degree.</l>
<l>Pardon the freedom I have ta&apos;en,—</l>
<l>Will after noon return again.</l>

<Speaker>MARTHA (aloud</Speaker>

<l>Of all things in the world! Just hear—</l>
<l>He takes thee for a lady, dear!</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>I am a creature young and poor:</l>
<l>The gentleman&apos;s too kind, I&apos;m sure.</l>
<l>The jewels don&apos;t belong to me.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Ah, not alone the jewelry!</l>
<l>The look, the manner, both betray—</l>
<l>Rejoiced am I that I may stay!</l>

<Speaker>MARTHA</Speaker>

<l>What is your business? I would fain—</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>I would I had a more cheerful strain!</l>
<l>Take not unkindly its repeating:</l>
<l>Your husband&apos;s dead, and sends a greeting.</l>

<Speaker>MARTHA</Speaker>

<l>Is dead? Alas, that heart so true!</l>
<l>My husband dead! Let me die, too!</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>Ah, dearest dame, let not your courage fail!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Hear me relate the mournful tale!</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>Therefore I&apos;d never love, believe me!</l>
<l>A loss like this to death would grieve me.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Joy follows woe, woe after joy comes flying.</l>

<Speaker>MARTHA</Speaker>

<l>Relate his life&apos;s sad close to me!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>In Padua buried, he is lying</l>
<l>Beside the good Saint Antony,</l>
<l>Within a grave well consecrated,</l>
<l>For cool, eternal rest created.</l>

<Speaker>MARTHA</Speaker>

<l>He gave you, further, no commission?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Yes, one of weight, with many sighs:</l>
<l>Three hundred masses buy, to save him from perdition!</l>
<l>My hands are empty, otherwise.</l>

<Speaker>MARTHA</Speaker>

<l>What! Not a pocket-piece? no jewelry?</l>
<l>What every journeyman within his wallet spares,</l>
<l>And as a token with him bears,</l>
<l>And rather starves or begs, than loses?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Madam, it is a grief to me;</l>
<l>Yet, on my word, his cash was put to proper uses.</l>
<l>Besides, his penitence was very sore,</l>
<l>And he lamented his ill fortune all the more.</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>Alack, that men are so unfortunate!</l>
<l>Surely for his soul&apos;s sake full many a prayer I&apos;ll proffer.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>You well deserve a speedy marriage-offer:</l>
<l>You are so kind, compassionate.</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>O, no! As yet, it would not do.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>If not a husband, then a beau for you!</l>
<l>It is the greatest heavenly blessing,</l>
<l>To have a dear thing for one&apos;s caressing.</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>The country&apos;s custom is not so.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Custom, or not! It happens, though.</l>

<Speaker>MARTHA</Speaker>

<l>Continue, pray!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>I stood beside his bed of dying.</l>
<l>&apos;Twas something better than manure,—</l>
<l>Half-rotten straw: and yet, he died a Christian, sure,</l>
<l>And found that heavier scores to his account were lying.</l>
<l>He cried: &quot;I find my conduct wholly hateful!</l>
<l>To leave my wife, my trade, in manner so ungrateful!</l>
<l>Ah, the remembrance makes me die!</l>
<l>Would of my wrong to her I might be shriven!&quot;</l>

<Speaker>MARTHA (weeping</Speaker>

<l>The dear, good man! Long since was he forgiven.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>&quot;Yet she, God knows! was more to blame than I.&quot;</l>

<Speaker>MARTHA</Speaker>

<l>He lied! What! On the brink of death he slandered?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>In the last throes his senses wandered,</l>
<l>If I such things but half can judge.</l>
<l>He said: &quot;I had no time for play, for gaping freedom:</l>
<l>First children, and then work for bread to feed &apos;em,—</l>
<l>For bread, in the widest sense, to drudge,</l>
<l>And could not even eat my share in peace and quiet!&quot;</l>

<Speaker>MARTHA</Speaker>

<l>Had he all love, all faith forgotten in his riot?</l>
<l>My work and worry, day and night?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Not so: the memory of it touched him quite.</l>
<l>Said he: &quot;When I from Malta went away</l>
<l>My prayers for wife and little ones were zealous,</l>
<l>And such a luck from Heaven befell us,</l>
<l>We made a Turkish merchantman our prey,</l>
<l>That to the Soldan bore a mighty treasure.</l>
<l>Then I received, as was most fit,</l>
<l>Since bravery was paid in fullest measure,</l>
<l>My well-apportioned share of it.&quot;</l>

<Speaker>MARTHA</Speaker>

<l>Say, how? Say, where? If buried, did he own it?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Who knows, now, whither the four winds have blown it?</l>
<l>A fair young damsel took him in her care,</l>
<l>As he in Naples wandered round, unfriended;</l>
<l>And she much love, much faith to him did bear,</l>
<l>So that he felt it till his days were ended.</l>

<Speaker>MARTHA</Speaker>

<l>The villain! From his children thieving!</l>
<l>Even all the misery on him cast</l>
<l>Could not prevent his shameful way of living!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>But see! He&apos;s dead therefrom, at last.</l>
<l>Were I in your place, do not doubt me,</l>
<l>I&apos;d mourn him decently a year,</l>
<l>And for another keep, meanwhile, my eyes about me.</l>

<Speaker>MARTHA</Speaker>

<l>Ah, God! another one so dear</l>
<l>As was my first, this world will hardly give me.</l>
<l>There never was a sweeter fool than mine,</l>
<l>Only he loved to roam and leave me,</l>
<l>And foreign wenches and foreign wine,</l>
<l>And the damned throw of dice, indeed.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Well, well! That might have done, however,</l>
<l>If he had only been as clever,</l>
<l>And treated your slips with as little heed.</l>
<l>I swear, with this condition, too,</l>
<l>I would, myself, change rings with you.</l>

<Speaker>MARTHA</Speaker>

<l>The gentleman is pleased to jest.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>I&apos;ll cut away, betimes, from here:</l>
<l>She&apos;d take the Devil at his word, I fear.</l>

<l>(To MARGARET)</l>

<l>How fares the heart within your breast?</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>What means the gentleman?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES (aside</Speaker>

<l>Sweet innocent, thou art!</l>

<Speaker>(Aloud</Speaker>

<l>Ladies, farewell!</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<Speaker>Farewell</Speaker>

<Speaker>MARTHA</Speaker>

<l>A moment, ere we part!</l>
<l>I&apos;d like to have a legal witness,</l>
<l>Where, how, and when he died, to certify his fitness.</l>
<l>Irregular ways I&apos;ve always hated;</l>
<l>I want his death in the weekly paper stated.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Yes, my good dame, a pair of witnesses</l>
<l>Always the truth establishes.</l>
<l>I have a friend of high condition,</l>
<l>Who&apos;ll also add his deposition.</l>
<l>I&apos;ll bring him here.</l>

<Speaker>MARTHA</Speaker>

<l>Good Sir, pray do!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>And this young lady will be present, too?</l>
<l>A gallant youth! has travelled far:</l>
<l>Ladies with him delighted are.</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>Before him I should blush, ashamed.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Before no king that could be named!</l>

<Speaker>MARTHA</Speaker>

<l>Behind the house, in my garden, then,</l>
<l>This eve we&apos;ll expect the gentlemen.</l>

<Scene> XI </Scene>
<Speaker>A STREET</Speaker>

<Speaker>FAUST MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>How is it? under way? and soon complete?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Ah, bravo! Do I find you burning?</l>
<l>Well, Margaret soon will still your yearning:</l>
<l>At Neighbor Martha&apos;s you&apos;ll this evening meet.</l>
<l>A fitter woman ne&apos;er was made</l>
<l>To ply the pimp and gypsy trade!</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Tis well.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Yet something is required from us.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>One service pays the other thus.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>We&apos;ve but to make a deposition valid</l>
<l>That now her husband&apos;s limbs, outstretched and pallid,</l>
<l>At Padua rest, in consecrated soil.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Most wise! And first, of course, we&apos;ll make the journey</l>
<Speaker>thither</Speaker>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Sancta simplicitas! no need of such a toil;</l>
<l>Depose, with knowledge or without it, either!</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>If you&apos;ve naught better, then, I&apos;ll tear your pretty plan!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Now, there you are! O holy man!</l>
<l>Is it the first time in your life you&apos;re driven</l>
<l>To bear false witness in a case?</l>
<l>Of God, the world and all that in it has a place,</l>
<l>Of Man, and all that moves the being of his race,</l>
<l>Have you not terms and definitions given</l>
<l>With brazen forehead, daring breast?</l>
<l>And, if you&apos;ll probe the thing profoundly,</l>
<l>Knew you so much—and you&apos;ll confess it roundly!—</l>
<l>As here of Schwerdtlein&apos;s death and place of rest?</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Thou art, and thou remain&apos;st, a sophist, liar.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Yes, knew I not more deeply thy desire.</l>
<l>For wilt thou not, no lover fairer,</l>
<l>Poor Margaret flatter, and ensnare her,</l>
<l>And all thy soul&apos;s devotion swear her?</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>And from my heart.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>&apos;Tis very fine!</l>
<l>Thine endless love, thy faith assuring,</l>
<l>The one almighty force enduring,—</l>
<l>Will that, too, prompt this heart of thine?</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Hold! hold! It will!—If such my flame,</l>
<l>And for the sense and power intense</l>
<l>I seek, and cannot find, a name;</l>
<l>Then range with all my senses through creation,</l>
<l>Craving the speech of inspiration,</l>
<l>And call this ardor, so supernal,</l>
<l>Endless, eternal and eternal,—</l>
<l>Is that a devilish lying game?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>And yet I&apos;m right!</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Mark this, I beg of thee!</l>
<l>And spare my lungs henceforth: whoever</l>
<l>Intends to have the right, if but his</l>
<l>tongue be clever,</l>
<l>Will have it, certainly.</l>
<l>But come: the further talking brings</l>
<Speaker>disgust</Speaker>
<l>For thou art right, especially since I</l>
<Speaker>must</Speaker>

<Scene> XII </Scene>
<Speaker>GARDEN</Speaker>

<l>(MARGARET on FAUST&apos;S arm. MARTHA and MEPHISTOPHELES walking up and down.)</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>I feel, the gentleman allows for me,</l>
<l>Demeans himself, and shames me by it;</l>
<l>A traveller is so used to be</l>
<l>Kindly content with any diet.</l>
<l>I know too well that my poor gossip can</l>
<l>Ne&apos;er entertain such an experienced man.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>A look from thee, a word, more entertains</l>
<l>Than all the lore of wisest brains.</l>

<l>(He kisses her hand.)</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>Don&apos;t incommode yourself! How could you ever kiss it!</l>
<l>It is so ugly, rough to see!</l>
<l>What work I do,—how hard and steady is it!</l>
<l>Mother is much too close with me.</l>

<l>[They pass.</l>

<Speaker>MARTHA</Speaker>

<l>And you, Sir, travel always, do you not?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Alas, that trade and duty us so harry!</l>
<l>With what a pang one leaves so many a spot,</l>
<l>And dares not even now and then to tarry!</l>

<Speaker>MARTHA</Speaker>

<l>In young, wild years it suits your ways,</l>
<l>This round and round the world in freedom sweeping;</l>
<l>But then come on the evil days,</l>
<l>And so, as bachelor, into his grave a-creeping,</l>
<l>None ever found a thing to praise.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>I dread to see how such a fate advances.</l>

<Speaker>MARTHA</Speaker>

<l>Then, worthy Sir, improve betimes your chances!</l>

<l>[They pass.</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>Yes, out of sight is out of mind!</l>
<l>Your courtesy an easy grace is;</l>
<l>But you have friends in other places,</l>
<l>And sensibler than I, you&apos;ll find.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Trust me, dear heart! what men call sensible</l>
<l>Is oft mere vanity and narrowness.</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>How so?</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Ah, that simplicity and innocence ne&apos;er know</l>
<l>Themselves, their holy value, and their spell!</l>
<l>That meekness, lowliness, the highest graces</l>
<l>Which Nature portions out so lovingly—</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>So you but think a moment&apos;s space on me,</l>
<l>All times I&apos;ll have to think on you, all places!</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>No doubt you&apos;re much alone?</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>Yes, for our household small has grown,</l>
<l>Yet must be cared for, you will own.</l>
<l>We have no maid: I do the knitting, sewing, sweeping,</l>
<l>The cooking, early work and late, in fact;</l>
<l>And mother, in her notions of housekeeping,</l>
<l>Is so exact!</l>
<l>Not that she needs so much to keep expenses down:</l>
<l>We, more than others, might take comfort, rather:</l>
<l>A nice estate was left us by my father,</l>
<l>A house, a little garden near the town.</l>
<l>But now my days have less of noise and hurry;</l>
<l>My brother is a soldier,</l>
<l>My little sister&apos;s dead.</l>
<l>True, with the child a troubled life I led,</l>
<l>Yet I would take again, and willing, all the worry,</l>
<l>So very dear was she.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>An angel, if like thee!</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>I brought it up, and it was fond of me.</l>
<l>Father had died before it saw the light,</l>
<l>And mother&apos;s case seemed hopeless quite,</l>
<l>So weak and miserable she lay;</l>
<l>And she recovered, then, so slowly, day by day.</l>
<l>She could not think, herself, of giving</l>
<l>The poor wee thing its natural living;</l>
<l>And so I nursed it all alone</l>
<l>With milk and water: &apos;twas my own.</l>
<l>Lulled in my lap with many a song,</l>
<l>It smiled, and tumbled, and grew strong.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>The purest bliss was surely then thy dower.</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>But surely, also, many a weary hour.</l>
<l>I kept the baby&apos;s cradle near</l>
<l>My bed at night: if &apos;t even stirred, I&apos;d guess it,</l>
<l>And waking, hear.</l>
<l>And I must nurse it, warm beside me press it,</l>
<l>And oft, to quiet it, my bed forsake,</l>
<l>And dandling back and forth the restless creature take,</l>
<l>Then at the wash-tub stand, at morning&apos;s break;</l>
<l>And then the marketing and kitchen-tending,</l>
<l>Day after day, the same thing, never-ending.</l>
<l>One&apos;s spirits, Sir, are thus not always good,</l>
<l>But then one learns to relish rest and food.</l>

<l>[They pass.</l>

<Speaker>MARTHA</Speaker>

<l>Yes, the poor women are bad off, &apos;tis true:</l>
<l>A stubborn bachelor there&apos;s no converting.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>It but depends upon the like of you,</l>
<l>And I should turn to better ways than flirting.</l>

<Speaker>MARTHA</Speaker>

<l>Speak plainly, Sir, have you no one detected?</l>
<l>Has not your heart been anywhere subjected?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>The proverb says: One&apos;s own warm hearth</l>
<l>And a good wife, are gold and jewels worth.</l>

<Speaker>MARTHA</Speaker>

<l>I mean, have you not felt desire, though ne&apos;er so slightly?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>I&apos;ve everywhere, in fact, been entertained politely.</l>

<Speaker>MARTHA</Speaker>

<l>I meant to say, were you not touched in earnest, ever?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>One should allow one&apos;s self to jest with ladies never.</l>

<l>MARTHA Ah, you don&apos;t understand!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>I&apos;m sorry I&apos;m so blind: But I am sure—that you are very kind.</l>

<l>[They pass.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>And me, thou angel! didst thou recognize,</l>
<l>As through the garden-gate I came?</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>Did you not see it? I cast down my eyes.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>And thou forgiv&apos;st my freedom, and the blame</l>
<l>To my impertinence befitting,</l>
<l>As the Cathedral thou wert quitting?</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>I was confused, the like ne&apos;er happened me;</l>
<l>No one could ever speak to my discredit.</l>
<l>Ah, thought I, in my conduct has he read it—</l>
<l>Something immodest or unseemly free?</l>
<l>He seemed to have the sudden feeling</l>
<l>That with this wench &apos;twere very easy dealing.</l>
<l>I will confess, I knew not what appeal</l>
<l>On your behalf, here, in my bosom grew;</l>
<l>But I was angry with myself, to feel</l>
<l>That I could not be angrier with you.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Sweet darling!</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>Wait a while!</l>

<l>(She plucks a star-flower, and pulls off the leaves, one after</l>
<l>the other.)</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Shall that a nosegay be?</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>No, it is just in play.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<Speaker>How</Speaker>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>Go! you&apos;ll laugh at me.</l>
<l>(She pulls off the leaves and murmurs.)</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>What murmurest thou?</l>

<l>MARGARET (half aloud)</l>

<l>He loves me—loves me not.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Thou sweet, angelic soul!</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET (continues</Speaker>

<l>Loves me—not—loves me—not—</l>
<l>(plucking the last leaf, she cries with frank delight:)</l>

<l>He loves me!</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Yes, child! and let this blossom-word</l>
<l>For thee be speech divine! He loves thee!</l>
<l>Ah, know&apos;st thou what it means? He loves thee!</l>

<l>(He grasps both her hands.)</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>I&apos;m all a-tremble!</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>O tremble not! but let this look,</l>
<l>Let this warm clasp of hands declare thee</l>
<l>What is unspeakable!</l>
<l>To yield one wholly, and to feel a rapture</l>
<l>In yielding, that must be eternal!</l>
<l>Eternal!—for the end would be despair.</l>
<l>No, no,—no ending! no ending!</l>

<l>MARTHA (coming forward)</l>

<l>The night is falling.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Ay! we must away.</l>

<Speaker>MARTHA</Speaker>

<l>I&apos;d ask you, longer here to tarry,</l>
<l>But evil tongues in this town have full play.</l>
<l>It&apos;s as if nobody had nothing to fetch and carry,</l>
<l>Nor other labor,</l>
<l>But spying all the doings of one&apos;s neighbor:</l>
<l>And one becomes the talk, do whatsoe&apos;er one may.</l>
<l>Where is our couple now?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Flown up the alley yonder,</l>
<l>The wilful summer-birds!</l>

<Speaker>MARTHA</Speaker>

<l>He seems of her still fonder.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>And she of him. So runs the world away!</l>

<Scene> XIII </Scene>
<l>A GARDEN-ARBOR</l>

<l>(MARGARET comes in, conceals herself behind the door, puts her</l>
<l>finger to her lips, and peeps through the crack.)</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>He comes!</l>

<Speaker>FAUST (entering</Speaker>

<l>Ah, rogue! a tease thou art:</l>
<l>I have thee! (He kisses her.)</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>(clasping him, and returning the kiss)</l>

<l>Dearest man! I love thee from my heart.</l>
<l>(MEPHISTOPHELES knocks)</l>

<l>FAUST (stamping his foot)</l>

<l>Who&apos;s there?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<Speaker>A friend</Speaker>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<Speaker>A beast</Speaker>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Tis time to separate.</l>

<Speaker>MARTHA (coming</Speaker>

<l>Yes, Sir, &apos;tis late.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>May I not, then, upon you wait?</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>My mother would—farewell!</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Ah, can I not remain?</l>
<Speaker>Farewell</Speaker>

<Speaker>MARTHA</Speaker>

<Speaker>Adieu</Speaker>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>And soon to meet again!</l>

<l>[Exeunt FAUST and MEPHISTOPHELES.</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>Dear God! However is it, such</l>
<l>A man can think and know so much?</l>
<l>I stand ashamed and in amaze,</l>
<l>And answer &quot;Yes&quot; to all he says,</l>
<l>A poor, unknowing child! and he—</l>
<l>I can&apos;t think what he finds in me!      [Exit.</l>

<Scene> XIV </Scene>
<l>FOREST AND CAVERN</l>

<Speaker>FAUST (solus</Speaker>

<l>Spirit sublime, thou gav&apos;st me, gav&apos;st me all</l>
<l>For which I prayed. Not unto me in vain</l>
<l>Hast thou thy countenance revealed in fire.</l>
<l>Thou gav&apos;st me Nature as a kingdom grand,</l>
<l>With power to feel and to enjoy it. Thou</l>
<l>Not only cold, amazed acquaintance yield&apos;st,</l>
<l>But grantest, that in her profoundest breast</l>
<l>I gaze, as in the bosom of a friend.</l>
<l>The ranks of living creatures thou dost lead</l>
<l>Before me, teaching me to know my brothers</l>
<l>In air and water and the silent wood.</l>
<l>And when the storm in forests roars and grinds,</l>
<l>The giant firs, in falling, neighbor boughs</l>
<l>And neighbor trunks with crushing weight bear down,</l>
<l>And falling, fill the hills with hollow thunders,—</l>
<l>Then to the cave secure thou leadest me,</l>
<l>Then show&apos;st me mine own self, and in my breast</l>
<l>The deep, mysterious miracles unfold.</l>
<l>And when the perfect moon before my gaze</l>
<l>Comes up with soothing light, around me float</l>
<l>From every precipice and thicket damp</l>
<l>The silvery phantoms of the ages past,</l>
<l>And temper the austere delight of thought.</l>

<l>That nothing can be perfect unto Man</l>
<l>I now am conscious. With this ecstasy,</l>
<l>Which brings me near and nearer to the Gods,</l>
<l>Thou gav&apos;st the comrade, whom I now no more</l>
<l>Can do without, though, cold and scornful, he</l>
<l>Demeans me to myself, and with a breath,</l>
<l>A word, transforms thy gifts to nothingness.</l>
<l>Within my breast he fans a lawless fire,</l>
<l>Unwearied, for that fair and lovely form:</l>
<l>Thus in desire I hasten to enjoyment,</l>
<l>And in enjoyment pine to feel desire.</l>

<l>(MEPHISTOPHELES enters.)</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Have you not led this life quite long enough?</l>
<l>How can a further test delight you?</l>
<l>&apos;Tis very well, that once one tries the stuff,</l>
<l>But something new must then requite you.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Would there were other work for thee!</l>
<l>To plague my day auspicious thou returnest.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Well! I&apos;ll engage to let thee be:</l>
<l>Thou darest not tell me so in earnest.</l>
<l>The loss of thee were truly very slight,—</l>
<l>comrade crazy, rude, repelling:</l>

<l>One has one&apos;s hands full all the day and night;</l>
<l>If what one does, or leaves undone, is right,</l>
<l>From such a face as thine there is no telling.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>


<l>There is, again, thy proper tone!—</l>
<l>That thou hast bored me, I must thankful be!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Poor Son of Earth, how couldst thou thus alone</l>
<l>Have led thy life, bereft of me?</l>
<l>I, for a time, at least, have worked thy cure;</l>
<l>Thy fancy&apos;s rickets plague thee not at all:</l>
<l>Had I not been, so hadst thou, sure,</l>
<l>Walked thyself off this earthly ball</l>
<l>Why here to caverns, rocky hollows slinking,</l>
<l>Sit&apos;st thou, as &apos;twere an owl a-blinking?</l>
<l>Why suck&apos;st, from sodden moss and dripping stone,</l>
<l>Toad-like, thy nourishment alone?</l>
<l>A fine way, this, thy time to fill!</l>
<l>The Doctor&apos;s in thy body still.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>What fresh and vital forces, canst thou guess,</l>
<l>Spring from my commerce with the wilderness?</l>
<l>But, if thou hadst the power of guessing,</l>
<l>Thou wouldst be devil enough to grudge my soul the blessing.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>A blessing drawn from supernatural fountains!</l>
<l>In night and dew to lie upon the mountains;</l>
<l>All Heaven and Earth in rapture penetrating;</l>
<l>Thyself to Godhood haughtily inflating;</l>
<l>To grub with yearning force through Earth&apos;s dark marrow,</l>
<l>Compress the six days&apos; work within thy bosom narrow,—</l>
<l>To taste, I know not what, in haughty power,</l>
<l>Thine own ecstatic life on all things shower,</l>
<l>Thine earthly self behind thee cast,</l>
<l>And then the lofty instinct, thus—</l>

<l>(With a gesture:)</l>

<l>at last,—</l>

<l>I daren&apos;t say how—to pluck the final flower!</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Shame on thee!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Yes, thou findest that unpleasant!</l>
<l>Thou hast the moral right to cry me &quot;shame!&quot; at present.</l>
<l>One dares not that before chaste ears declare,</l>
<l>Which chaste hearts, notwithstanding, cannot spare;</l>
<l>And, once for all, I grudge thee not the pleasure</l>
<l>Of lying to thyself in moderate measure.</l>
<l>But such a course thou wilt not long endure;</l>
<l>Already art thou o&apos;er-excited,</l>
<l>And, if it last, wilt soon be plighted</l>
<l>To madness and to horror, sure.</l>
<l>Enough of that! Thy love sits lonely yonder,</l>
<l>By all things saddened and oppressed;</l>
<l>Her thoughts and yearnings seek thee, tenderer, fonder,—</l>
<l>mighty love is in her breast.</l>
<l>First came thy passion&apos;s flood and poured around her</l>
<l>As when from melted snow a streamlet overflows;</l>
<l>Thou hast therewith so filled and drowned her,</l>
<l>That now thy stream all shallow shows.</l>
<l>Methinks, instead of in the forests lording,</l>
<l>The noble Sir should find it good,</l>
<l>The love of this young silly blood</l>
<l>At once to set about rewarding.</l>
<l>Her time is miserably long;</l>
<l>She haunts her window, watching clouds that stray</l>
<l>O&apos;er the old city-wall, and far away.</l>
<l>&quot;Were I a little bird!&quot; so runs her song,</l>
<l>Day long, and half night long.</l>
<l>Now she is lively, mostly sad,</l>
<l>Now, wept beyond her tears;</l>
<l>Then again quiet she appears,—Always</l>
<l>love-mad.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Serpent! Serpent!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES (aside</Speaker>

<l>Ha! do I trap thee!</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Get thee away with thine offences,</l>
<l>Reprobate! Name not that fairest thing,</l>
<l>Nor the desire for her sweet body bring</l>
<l>Again before my half-distracted senses!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>What wouldst thou, then? She thinks that thou art flown;</l>
<l>And half and half thou art, I own.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Yet am I near, and love keeps watch and ward;</l>
<l>Though I were ne&apos;er so far, it cannot falter:</l>
<l>I envy even the Body of the Lord</l>
<l>The touching of her lips, before the altar.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>&apos;Tis very well! My envy oft reposes</l>
<l>On your twin-pair, that feed among the roses.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Away, thou pimp!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>You rail, and it is fun to me.</l>
<l>The God, who fashioned youth and maid,</l>
<l>Perceived the noblest purpose of His trade,</l>
<l>And also made their opportunity.</l>
<l>Go on! It is a woe profound!</l>
<l>&apos;Tis for your sweetheart&apos;s room you&apos;re bound,</l>
<l>And not for death, indeed.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>What are, within her arms, the heavenly blisses?</l>
<l>Though I be glowing with her kisses,</l>
<l>Do I not always share her need?</l>
<l>I am the fugitive, all houseless roaming,</l>
<l>The monster without air or rest,</l>
<l>That like a cataract, down rocks and gorges foaming,</l>
<l>Leaps, maddened, into the abyss&apos;s breast!</l>
<l>And side-wards she, with young unwakened senses,</l>
<l>Within her cabin on the Alpine field</l>
<l>Her simple, homely life commences,</l>
<l>Her little world therein concealed.</l>
<l>And I, God&apos;s hate flung o&apos;er me,</l>
<l>Had not enough, to thrust</l>
<l>The stubborn rocks before me</l>
<l>And strike them into dust!</l>
<l>She and her peace I yet must undermine:</l>
<l>Thou, Hell, hast claimed this sacrifice as thine!</l>
<l>Help, Devil! through the coming pangs to push me;</l>
<l>What must be, let it quickly be!</l>
<l>Let fall on me her fate, and also crush me,—</l>
<l>One ruin whelm both her and me!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Again it seethes, again it glows!</l>
<l>Thou fool, go in and comfort her!</l>
<l>When such a head as thine no outlet knows,</l>
<l>It thinks the end must soon occur.</l>
<l>Hail him, who keeps a steadfast mind!</l>
<l>Thou, else, dost well the devil-nature wear:</l>
<l>Naught so insipid in the world I find</l>
<l>As is a devil in despair.</l>

<Scene> XV </Scene>
<Speaker>MARGARET&apos;S ROOM</Speaker>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>(at the spinning-wheel, alone)</l>

<l>My peace is gone,</l>
<l>My heart is sore:</l>
<l>I never shall find it,</l>
<l>Ah, nevermore!</l>

<l>Save I have him near.</l>
<l>The grave is here;</l>
<l>The world is gall</l>
<l>And bitterness all.</l>

<l>My poor weak head</l>
<l>Is racked and crazed;</l>
<l>My thought is lost,</l>
<l>My senses mazed.</l>

<l>My peace is gone,</l>
<l>My heart is sore:</l>
<l>I never shall find it,</l>
<l>Ah, nevermore!</l>

<l>To see him, him only,</l>
<l>At the pane I sit;</l>
<l>To meet him, him only,</l>
<l>The house I quit.</l>

<l>His lofty gait,</l>
<l>His noble size,</l>
<l>The smile of his mouth,</l>
<l>The power of his eyes,</l>

<l>And the magic flow</l>
<l>Of his talk, the bliss</l>
<l>In the clasp of his hand,</l>
<l>And, ah! his kiss!</l>

<l>My peace is gone,</l>
<l>My heart is sore:</l>
<l>I never shall find it,</l>
<l>Ah, nevermore!</l>

<l>My bosom yearns</l>
<l>For him alone;</l>
<l>Ah, dared I clasp him,</l>
<l>And hold, and own!</l>

<l>And kiss his mouth,</l>
<l>To heart&apos;s desire,</l>
<l>And on his kisses</l>
<l>At last expire!</l>

<Scene> XVI </Scene>
<Speaker>MARTHA&apos;S GARDEN</Speaker>

<Speaker>MARGARET FAUST</Speaker>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>Promise me, Henry!—</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>What I can!</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>How is&apos;t with thy religion, pray?</l>
<l>Thou art a dear, good-hearted man,</l>
<l>And yet, I think, dost not incline that way.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Leave that, my child! Thou know&apos;st my love is tender;</l>
<l>For love, my blood and life would I surrender,</l>
<l>And as for Faith and Church, I grant to each his own.</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>That&apos;s not enough: we must believe thereon.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Must we?</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>Would that I had some influence!</l>

<l>Then, too, thou honorest not the Holy Sacraments.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>I honor them.</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>Desiring no possession</l>
<l>&apos;Tis long since thou hast been to mass or to confession.</l>
<l>Believest thou in God?</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>My darling, who shall dare</l>
<l>&quot;I believe in God!&quot; to say?</l>
<l>Ask priest or sage the answer to declare,</l>
<l>And it will seem a mocking play,</l>
<l>A sarcasm on the asker.</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>Then thou believest not!</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Hear me not falsely, sweetest countenance!</l>
<l>Who dare express Him?</l>
<l>And who profess Him,</l>
<l>Saying: I believe in Him!</l>
<l>Who, feeling, seeing,</l>
<l>Deny His being,</l>
<l>Saying: I believe Him not!</l>
<l>The All-enfolding,</l>
<l>The All-upholding,</l>
<l>Folds and upholds he not</l>
<l>Thee, me, Himself?</l>
<l>Arches not there the sky above us?</l>
<l>Lies not beneath us, firm, the earth?</l>
<l>And rise not, on us shining,</l>
<l>Friendly, the everlasting stars?</l>
<l>Look I not, eye to eye, on thee,</l>
<l>And feel&apos;st not, thronging</l>
<l>To head and heart, the force,</l>
<l>Still weaving its eternal secret,</l>
<l>Invisible, visible, round thy life?</l>
<l>Vast as it is, fill with that force thy heart,</l>
<l>And when thou in the feeling wholly blessed art,</l>
<l>Call it, then, what thou wilt,—</l>
<l>Call it Bliss! Heart! Love! God!</l>
<l>I have no name to give it!</l>
<l>Feeling is all in all:</l>
<l>The Name is sound and smoke,</l>
<l>Obscuring Heaven&apos;s clear glow.</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>All that is fine and good, to hear it so:</l>
<l>Much the same way the preacher spoke,</l>
<l>Only with slightly different phrases.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>The same thing, in all places,</l>
<l>All hearts that beat beneath the heavenly day—</l>
<l>Each in its language—say;</l>
<l>Then why not I, in mine, as well?</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>To hear it thus, it may seem passable;</l>
<l>And yet, some hitch in&apos;t there must be</l>
<l>For thou hast no Christianity.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Dear love!</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>I&apos;ve long been grieved to see</l>
<l>That thou art in such company.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>How so?</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>The man who with thee goes, thy mate,</l>
<l>Within my deepest, inmost soul I hate.</l>
<l>In all my life there&apos;s nothing</l>
<l>Has given my heart so keen a pang of loathing,</l>
<l>As his repulsive face has done.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Nay, fear him not, my sweetest one!</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>I feel his presence like something ill.</l>
<l>I&apos;ve else, for all, a kindly will,</l>
<l>But, much as my heart to see thee yearneth,</l>
<l>The secret horror of him returneth;</l>
<l>And I think the man a knave, as I live!</l>
<l>If I do him wrong, may God forgive!</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>There must be such queer birds, however.</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>Live with the like of him, may I never!</l>
<l>When once inside the door comes he,</l>
<l>He looks around so sneeringly,</l>
<l>And half in wrath:</l>
<l>One sees that in nothing no interest he hath:</l>
<l>&apos;Tis written on his very forehead</l>
<l>That love, to him, is a thing abhorréd.</l>
<l>I am so happy on thine arm,</l>
<l>So free, so yielding, and so warm,</l>
<l>And in his presence stifled seems my heart.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Foreboding angel that thou art!</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>It overcomes me in such degree,</l>
<l>That wheresoe&apos;er he meets us, even,</l>
<l>I feel as though I&apos;d lost my love for thee.</l>
<l>When he is by, I could not pray to Heaven.</l>
<l>That burns within me like a flame,</l>
<l>And surely, Henry, &apos;tis with thee the same.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>There, now, is thine antipathy!</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>But I must go.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Ah, shall there never be</l>
<l>A quiet hour, to see us fondly plighted,</l>
<l>With breast to breast, and soul to soul united?</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>Ah, if I only slept alone!</l>
<l>I&apos;d draw the bolts to-night, for thy desire;</l>
<l>But mother&apos;s sleep so light has grown,</l>
<l>And if we were discovered by her,</l>
<l>&apos;Twould be my death upon the spot!</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Thou angel, fear it not!</l>
<l>Here is a phial: in her drink</l>
<l>But three drops of it measure,</l>
<l>And deepest sleep will on her senses sink.</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>What would I not, to give thee pleasure?</l>
<l>It will not harm her, when one tries it?</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>If &apos;twould, my love, would I advise it?</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>Ah, dearest man, if but thy face I see,</l>
<l>I know not what compels me to thy will:</l>
<l>So much have I already done for thee,</l>
<l>That scarcely more is left me to fulfil.</l>

<l>(Enter MEPHISTOPHELES.)    [Exit.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>The monkey! Is she gone?</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Hast played the spy again?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>I&apos;ve heard, most fully, how she drew thee.</l>
<l>The Doctor has been catechised, &apos;tis plain;</l>
<l>Great good, I hope, the thing will do thee.</l>
<l>The girls have much desire to ascertain</l>
<l>If one is prim and good, as ancient rules compel:</l>
<l>If there he&apos;s led, they think, he&apos;ll follow them as well.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Thou, monster, wilt nor see nor own</l>
<l>How this pure soul, of faith so lowly,</l>
<l>So loving and ineffable,—</l>
<l>The faith alone</l>
<l>That her salvation is,—with scruples holy</l>
<l>Pines, lest she hold as lost the man she loves so well!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Thou, full of sensual, super-sensual desire,</l>
<l>A girl by the nose is leading thee.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Abortion, thou, of filth and fire!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>And then, how masterly she reads physiognomy!</l>
<l>When I am present she&apos;s impressed, she knows not how;</l>
<l>She in my mask a hidden sense would read:</l>
<l>She feels that surely I&apos;m a genius now,—</l>
<l>Perhaps the very Devil, indeed!</l>
<l>Well, well,—to-night—?</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>What&apos;s that to thee?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Yet my delight &apos;twill also be!</l>

<Scene> XVII </Scene>
<l>AT THE FOUNTAIN</l>

<l>MARGARET and LISBETH With pitchers.</l>

<Speaker>LISBETH</Speaker>

<l>Hast nothing heard of Barbara?</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>No, not a word. I go so little out.</l>

<Speaker>LISBETH</Speaker>

<l>It&apos;s true, Sibylla said, to-day.</l>
<l>She&apos;s played the fool at last, there&apos;s not a doubt.</l>
<l>Such taking-on of airs!</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>How so?</l>


<Speaker>LISBETH</Speaker>

<l>It stinks!</l>
<l>She&apos;s feeding two, whene&apos;er she eats and drinks.</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<Speaker>Ah</Speaker>

<Speaker>LISBETH</Speaker>

<l>And so, at last, it serves her rightly.</l>
<l>She clung to the fellow so long and tightly!</l>
<l>That was a promenading!</l>
<l>At village and dance parading!</l>
<l>As the first they must everywhere shine,</l>
<l>And he treated her always to pies and wine,</l>
<l>And she made a to-do with her face so fine;</l>
<l>So mean and shameless was her behavior,</l>
<l>She took all the presents the fellow gave her.</l>
<l>&apos;Twas kissing and coddling, on and on!</l>
<l>So now, at the end, the flower is gone.</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>The poor, poor thing!</l>

<Speaker>LISBETH</Speaker>

<l>Dost pity her, at that?</l>
<l>When one of us at spinning sat,</l>
<l>And mother, nights, ne&apos;er let us out the door</l>
<l>She sported with her paramour.</l>
<l>On the door-bench, in the passage dark,</l>
<l>The length of the time they&apos;d never mark.</l>
<l>So now her head no more she&apos;ll lift,</l>
<l>But do church-penance in her sinner&apos;s shift!</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>He&apos;ll surely take her for his wife.</l>

<Speaker>LISBETH</Speaker>

<l>He&apos;d be a fool! A brisk young blade</l>
<l>Has room, elsewhere, to ply his trade.</l>
<l>Besides, he&apos;s gone.</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>That is not fair!</l>


<Speaker>LISBETH</Speaker>

<l>If him she gets, why let her beware!</l>
<l>The boys shall dash her wreath on the floor,</l>
<l>And we&apos;ll scatter chaff before her door!</l>
<stage>[Exit</stage>

<l>MARGARET (returning home)</l>

<l>How scornfully I once reviled,</l>
<l>When some poor maiden was beguiled!</l>
<l>More speech than any tongue suffices</l>
<l>I craved, to censure others&apos; vices.</l>
<l>Black as it seemed, I blackened still,</l>
<l>And blacker yet was in my will;</l>
<l>And blessed myself, and boasted high,—</l>
<l>And now—a living sin am I!</l>
<l>Yet—all that drove my heart thereto,</l>
<l>God! was so good, so dear, so true!</l>

<Scene> XVIII </Scene>
<Speaker>DONJON</Speaker>

<l>(In a niche of the wall a shrine, with an image of the Mater</l>
<l>Dolorosa. Pots of flowers before it.)</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>(putting fresh flowers in the pots)</l>

<l>Incline, O Maiden,</l>
<l>Thou sorrow-laden,</l>
<l>Thy gracious countenance upon my pain!</l>

<l>The sword Thy heart in,</l>
<l>With anguish smarting,</l>
<l>Thou lookest up to where Thy Son is slain!</l>

<l>Thou seest the Father;</l>
<l>Thy sad sighs gather,</l>
<l>And bear aloft Thy sorrow and His pain!</l>

<l>Ah, past guessing,</l>
<l>Beyond expressing,</l>
<l>The pangs that wring my flesh and bone!</l>
<l>Why this anxious heart so burneth,</l>
<l>Why it trembleth, why it yearneth,</l>
<l>Knowest Thou, and Thou alone!</l>

<l>Where&apos;er I go, what sorrow,</l>
<l>What woe, what woe and sorrow</l>
<l>Within my bosom aches!</l>
<l>Alone, and ah! unsleeping,</l>
<l>I&apos;m weeping, weeping, weeping,</l>
<l>The heart within me breaks.</l>

<l>The pots before my window,</l>
<l>Alas! my tears did wet,</l>
<l>As in the early morning</l>
<l>For thee these flowers I set.</l>

<l>Within my lonely chamber</l>
<l>The morning sun shone red:</l>
<l>I sat, in utter sorrow,</l>
<l>Already on my bed.</l>

<l>Help! rescue me from death and stain!</l>
<Speaker>O Maiden</Speaker>
<l>Thou sorrow-laden,</l>
<l>Incline Thy countenance upon my pain!</l>

<Scene> XIX </Scene>
<Speaker>NIGHT</Speaker>

<l>STREET BEFORE MARGARET&apos;S DOOR</l>

<l>VALENTINE (a soldier, MARGARET&apos;S brother)</l>

<l>When I have sat at some carouse.</l>
<l>Where each to each his brag allows,</l>
<l>And many a comrade praised to me</l>
<l>His pink of girls right lustily,</l>
<l>With brimming glass that spilled the toast,</l>
<l>And elbows planted as in boast:</l>
<l>I sat in unconcerned repose,</l>
<l>And heard the swagger as it rose.</l>
<l>And stroking then my beard, I&apos;d say,</l>
<l>Smiling, the bumper in my hand:</l>
<l>&quot;Each well enough in her own way.</l>
<l>But is there one in all the land</l>
<l>Like sister Margaret, good as gold,—</l>
<l>One that to her can a candle hold?&quot;</l>
<l>Cling! clang! &quot;Here&apos;s to her!&quot; went around</l>
<l>The board: &quot;He speaks the truth!&quot; cried some;</l>
<l>&quot;In her the flower o&apos; the sex is found!&quot;</l>
<l>And all the swaggerers were dumb.</l>
<l>And now!—I could tear my hair with vexation.</l>
<l>And dash out my brains in desperation!</l>
<l>With turned-up nose each scamp may face me,</l>
<l>With sneers and stinging taunts disgrace me,</l>
<l>And, like a bankrupt debtor sitting,</l>
<l>A chance-dropped word may set me sweating!</l>
<l>Yet, though I thresh them all together,</l>
<l>I cannot call them liars, either.</l>

<l>But what comes sneaking, there, to view?</l>
<l>If I mistake not, there are two.</l>
<l>If he&apos;s one, let me at him drive!</l>
<l>He shall not leave the spot alive.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>How from the window of the sacristy</l>
<l>Upward th&apos;eternal lamp sends forth a glimmer,</l>
<l>That, lessening side-wards, fainter grows and dimmer,</l>
<l>Till darkness closes from the sky!</l>
<l>The shadows thus within my bosom gather.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>I&apos;m like a sentimental tom-cat, rather,</l>
<l>That round the tall fire-ladders sweeps,</l>
<l>And stealthy, then, along the coping creeps:</l>
<l>Quite virtuous, withal, I come,</l>
<l>A little thievish and a little frolicsome.</l>
<l>I feel in every limb the presage</l>
<l>Forerunning the grand Walpurgis-Night:</l>
<l>Day after to-morrow brings its message,</l>
<l>And one keeps watch then with delight.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Meanwhile, may not the treasure risen be,</l>
<l>Which there, behind, I glimmering see?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Shalt soon experience the pleasure,</l>
<l>To lift the kettle with its treasure.</l>
<l>I lately gave therein a squint—</l>
<l>Saw splendid lion-dollars in &apos;t.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Not even a jewel, not a ring,</l>
<l>To deck therewith my darling girl?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>I saw, among the rest, a thing</l>
<l>That seemed to be a chain of pearl.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>That&apos;s well, indeed! For painful is it</l>
<l>To bring no gift when her I visit.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Thou shouldst not find it so annoying,</l>
<l>Without return to be enjoying.</l>
<l>Now, while the sky leads forth its starry throng,</l>
<l>Thou&apos;lt hear a masterpiece, no work completer:</l>
<l>I&apos;ll sing her, first, a moral song,</l>
<l>The surer, afterwards, to cheat her.</l>

<l>(Sings to the cither.)</l>

<l>What dost thou here</l>
<l>In daybreak clear,</l>
<l>Kathrina dear,</l>
<l>Before thy lover&apos;s door?</l>
<l>Beware! the blade</l>
<l>Lets in a maid.</l>
<l>That out a maid</l>
<l>Departeth nevermore!</l>

<l>The coaxing shun</l>
<l>Of such an one!</l>
<l>When once &apos;tis done</l>
<l>Good-night to thee, poor thing!</l>
<l>Love&apos;s time is brief:</l>
<l>Unto no thief</l>
<l>Be warm and lief,</l>
<l>But with the wedding-ring!</l>
<l>VALENTINE (comes forward)</l>

<l>Whom wilt thou lure? God&apos;s-element!</l>
<l>Rat-catching piper, thou!—perdition!</l>
<l>To the Devil, first, the instrument!</l>
<l>To the Devil, then, the curst musician!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>The cither&apos;s smashed! For nothing more &apos;tis fitting.</l>

<Speaker>VALENTINE</Speaker>

<l>There&apos;s yet a skull I must be splitting!</l>

<l>MEPHISTOPHELES (to FAUST)</l>

<l>Sir Doctor, don&apos;t retreat, I pray!</l>
<l>Stand by: I&apos;ll lead, if you&apos;ll but tarry:</l>
<l>Out with your spit, without delay!</l>
<l>You&apos;ve but to lunge, and I will parry.</l>

<Speaker>VALENTINE</Speaker>

<l>Then parry that!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Why not? &apos;tis light.</l>

<Speaker>VALENTINE</Speaker>

<l>That, too!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Of course.</l>

<Speaker>VALENTINE</Speaker>

<l>I think the Devil must fight!</l>
<l>How is it, then? my hand&apos;s already lame:</l>

<l>MEPHISTOPHELES (to FAUST)</l>

<l>Thrust home!</l>

<Speaker>VALENTINE (jails</Speaker>

<Speaker>O God</Speaker>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Now is the lubber tame!</l>
<l>But come, away! &apos;Tis time for us to fly;</l>
<l>For there arises now a murderous cry.</l>
<l>With the police &apos;twere easy to compound it,</l>
<l>But here the penal court will sift and sound it.</l>

<l>[Exit with FAUST.</l>

<l>MARTHA (at the window)</l>

<l>Come out! Come out!</l>

<l>MARGARET (at the window)</l>

<l>Quick, bring a light!</l>

<l>MARTHA (as above)</l>

<l>They swear and storm, they yell and fight!</l>

<Speaker>PEOPLE</Speaker>

<l>Here lies one dead already—see!</l>

<l>MARTHA (coming from the house)</l>

<l>The murderers, whither have they run?</l>

<l>MARGARET (coming out)</l>

<l>Who lies here?</l>

<Speaker>PEOPLE</Speaker>

<l>&apos;Tis thy mother&apos;s son!</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>Almighty God! what misery!</l>

<Speaker>VALENTINE</Speaker>

<l>I&apos;m dying! That is quickly said,</l>
<l>And quicker yet &apos;tis done.</l>
<l>Why howl, you women there? Instead,</l>
<l>Come here and listen, every one!</l>

<l>(All gather around him)</l>

<l>My Margaret, see! still young thou art,</l>
<l>But not the least bit shrewd or smart,</l>
<l>Thy business thus to slight:</l>
<l>So this advice I bid thee heed—</l>
<l>Now that thou art a whore indeed,</l>
<l>Why, be one then, outright!</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>My brother! God! such words to me?</l>

<Speaker>VALENTINE</Speaker>

<l>In this game let our Lord God be!</l>
<l>What&apos;s done&apos;s already done, alas!</l>
<l>What follows it, must come to pass.</l>
<l>With one begin&apos;st thou secretly,</l>
<l>Then soon will others come to thee,</l>
<l>And when a dozen thee have known,</l>
<l>Thou&apos;rt also free to all the town.</l>
<l>When Shame is born and first appears,</l>
<l>She is in secret brought to light,</l>
<l>And then they draw the veil of night</l>
<l>Over her head and ears;</l>
<l>Her life, in fact, they&apos;re loath to spare her.</l>
<l>But let her growth and strength display,</l>
<l>She walks abroad unveiled by day,</l>
<l>Yet is not grown a whit the fairer.</l>
<l>The uglier she is to sight,</l>
<l>The more she seeks the day&apos;s broad light.</l>
<l>The time I verily can discern</l>
<l>When all the honest folk will turn</l>
<l>From thee, thou jade! and seek protection</l>
<l>As from a corpse that breeds infection.</l>
<l>Thy guilty heart shall then dismay thee.</l>
<l>When they but look thee in the face:—</l>
<l>Shalt not in a golden chain array thee,</l>
<l>Nor at the altar take thy place!</l>
<l>Shalt not, in lace and ribbons flowing,</l>
<l>Make merry when the dance is going!</l>
<l>But in some corner, woe betide thee!</l>
<l>Among the beggars and cripples hide thee;</l>
<l>And so, though even God forgive,</l>
<l>On earth a damned existence live!</l>

<Speaker>MARTHA</Speaker>

<l>Commend your soul to God for pardon,</l>
<l>That you your heart with slander harden!</l>

<Speaker>VALENTINE</Speaker>

<l>Thou pimp most infamous, be still!</l>
<l>Could I thy withered body kill,</l>
<l>&apos;Twould bring, for all my sinful pleasure,</l>
<l>Forgiveness in the richest measure.</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>My brother! This is Hell&apos;s own pain!</l>

<Speaker>VALENTINE</Speaker>

<l>I tell thee, from thy tears refrain!</l>
<l>When thou from honor didst depart</l>
<l>It stabbed me to the very heart.</l>
<l>Now through the slumber of the grave</l>
<l>I go to God as a soldier brave.</l>

<Speaker>(Dies</Speaker>

<Scene> XX </Scene>
<Speaker>CATHEDRAL</Speaker>

<l>SERVICE, ORGAN and ANTHEM.</l>

<l>(MARGARET among much people: the EVIL SPIRIT behind</l>
<Speaker>MARGARET.</Speaker>

<Speaker>EVIL SPIRIT</Speaker>

<l>HOW otherwise was it, Margaret,</l>
<l>When thou, still innocent,</l>
<l>Here to the altar cam&apos;st,</l>
<l>And from the worn and fingered book</l>
<l>Thy prayers didst prattle,</l>
<l>Half sport of childhood,</l>
<l>Half God within thee!</l>
<Speaker>Margaret</Speaker>
<l>Where tends thy thought?</l>
<l>Within thy bosom</l>
<l>What hidden crime?</l>
<l>Pray&apos;st thou for mercy on thy mother&apos;s soul,</l>
<l>That fell asleep to long, long torment, and through thee?</l>
<l>Upon thy threshold whose the blood?</l>
<l>And stirreth not and quickens</l>
<l>Something beneath thy heart,</l>
<l>Thy life disquieting</l>
<l>With most foreboding presence?</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>Woe! woe!</l>
<l>Would I were free from the thoughts</l>
<l>That cross me, drawing hither and thither</l>
<l>Despite me!</l>

<Speaker>CHORUS</Speaker>

<l>Diesira, dies illa,</l>
<l>Solvet soeclum in favilla!</l>
<l>(Sound of the organ.)</l>
<Speaker>EVIL SPIRIT</Speaker>

<l>Wrath takes thee!</l>
<l>The trumpet peals!</l>
<l>The graves tremble!</l>
<l>And thy heart</l>
<l>From ashy rest</l>
<l>To fiery torments</l>
<l>Now again requickened,</l>
<l>Throbs to life!</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>Would I were forth!</l>
<l>I feel as if the organ here</l>
<l>My breath takes from me,</l>
<l>My very heart</l>
<l>Dissolved by the anthem!</l>

<Speaker>CHORUS</Speaker>

<l>Judex ergo cum sedebit,</l>
<l>Quidquid latet, ad parebit,</l>
<l>Nil inultum remanebit.</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>I cannot breathe!</l>
<l>The massy pillars</l>
<l>Imprison me!</l>
<l>The vaulted arches</l>
<l>Crush me!—Air!</l>

<Speaker>EVIL SPIRIT</Speaker>

<l>Hide thyself! Sin and shame</l>
<l>Stay never hidden.</l>
<l>Air? Light?</l>
<l>Woe to thee!</l>

<Speaker>CHORUS</Speaker>

<l>Quid sum miser tunc dicturus,</l>
<l>Quem patronem rogaturus,</l>
<l>Cum vix Justus sit securus</l>
<Speaker>EVIL SPIRIT</Speaker>

<l>They turn their faces,</l>
<l>The glorified, from thee:</l>
<l>The pure, their hands to offer,</l>
<l>Shuddering, refuse thee!</l>
<Speaker>Woe</Speaker>

<Speaker>CHORUS</Speaker>

<l>Quid sum miser tune dicturus?</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>Neighbor! your cordial!        (She falls in a swoon.)</l>

<Scene> XXI </Scene>
<Speaker>WALPURGIS-NIGHT</Speaker>

<l>THE HARTZ MOUNTAINS.</l>

<l>District of Schierke and Elend.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>DOST thou not wish a broomstick-steed&apos;s assistance?</l>
<l>The sturdiest he-goat I would gladly see:</l>
<l>The way we take, our goal is yet some distance.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>So long as in my legs I feel the fresh existence.</l>
<l>This knotted staff suffices me.</l>
<l>What need to shorten so the way?</l>
<l>Along this labyrinth of vales to wander,</l>
<l>Then climb the rocky ramparts yonder,</l>
<l>Wherefrom the fountain flings eternal spray,</l>
<l>Is such delight, my steps would fain delay.</l>
<l>The spring-time stirs within the fragrant birches,</l>
<l>And even the fir-tree feels it now:</l>
<l>Should then our limbs escape its gentle searches?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>I notice no such thing, I vow!</l>
<l>&apos;Tis winter still within my body:</l>
<l>Upon my path I wish for frost and snow.</l>
<l>How sadly rises, incomplete and ruddy,</l>
<l>The moon&apos;s lone disk, with its belated glow,</l>
<l>And lights so dimly, that, as one advances,</l>
<l>At every step one strikes a rock or tree!</l>
<l>Let us, then, use a Jack-o&apos;-lantern&apos;s glances:</l>
<l>I see one yonder, burning merrily.</l>
<l>Ho, there! my friend! I&apos;ll levy thine attendance:</l>
<l>Why waste so vainly thy resplendence?</l>
<l>Be kind enough to light us up the steep!</l>

<l>WILL-O&apos;-THE-WISP</l>

<l>My reverence, I hope, will me enable</l>
<l>To curb my temperament unstable;</l>
<l>For zigzag courses we are wont to keep.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Indeed? he&apos;d like mankind to imitate!</l>
<l>Now, in the Devil&apos;s name, go straight,</l>
<l>Or I&apos;ll blow out his being&apos;s flickering spark!</l>

<l>WILL-O&apos;-THE-WISP</l>

<l>You are the master of the house, I mark,</l>
<l>And I shall try to serve you nicely.</l>
<l>But then, reflect: the mountain&apos;s magic-mad to-day,</l>
<l>And if a will-o&apos;-the-wisp must guide you on the way,</l>
<l>You mustn&apos;t take things too precisely.</l>

<l>FAUST, MEPHISTOPHELES, WILL-O&apos;-THE-WISP</l>

<l>(in alternating song)</l>

<l>We, it seems, have entered newly</l>
<l>In the sphere of dreams enchanted.</l>
<l>Do thy bidding, guide us truly,</l>
<l>That our feet be forwards planted</l>
<l>In the vast, the desert spaces!</l>
<l>See them swiftly changing places,</l>
<l>Trees on trees beside us trooping,</l>
<l>And the crags above us stooping,</l>
<l>And the rocky snouts, outgrowing,—</l>
<l>Hear them snoring, hear them blowing!</l>
<l>O&apos;er the stones, the grasses, flowing</l>
<l>Stream and streamlet seek the hollow.</l>
<l>Hear I noises? songs that follow?</l>
<l>Hear I tender love-petitions?</l>
<l>Voices of those heavenly visions?</l>
<l>Sounds of hope, of love undying!</l>
<l>And the echoes, like traditions</l>
<l>Of old days, come faint and hollow.</l>

<l>Hoo-hoo! Shoo-hoo! Nearer hover</l>
<l>Jay and screech-owl, and the plover,—</l>
<l>Are they all awake and crying?</l>
<l>Is&apos;t the salamander pushes,</l>
<l>Bloated-bellied, through the bushes?</l>
<l>And the roots, like serpents twisted,</l>
<l>Through the sand and boulders toiling,</l>
<l>Fright us, weirdest links uncoiling</l>
<l>To entrap us, unresisted:</l>
<l>Living knots and gnarls uncanny</l>
<l>Feel with polypus-antennae</l>
<l>For the wanderer. Mice are flying,</l>
<l>Thousand-colored, herd-wise hieing</l>
<l>Through the moss and through the heather!</l>

<l>And the fire-flies wink and darkle,</l>
<l>Crowded swarms that soar and sparkle,</l>
<l>And in wildering escort gather!</l>

<l>Tell me, if we still are standing,</l>
<l>Or if further we&apos;re ascending?</l>
<l>All is turning, whirling, blending,</l>
<l>Trees and rocks with grinning faces,</l>
<l>Wandering lights that spin in mazes,</l>
<l>Still increasing and expanding!</l>
<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Grasp my skirt with heart undaunted!</l>
<l>Here a middle-peak is planted,</l>
<l>Whence one seeth, with amaze,</l>
<l>Mammon in the mountain blaze.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>How strangely glimmers through the hollows</l>
<l>A dreary light, like that of dawn!</l>
<l>Its exhalation tracks and follows</l>
<l>The deepest gorges, faint and wan.</l>
<l>Here steam, there rolling vapor sweepeth;</l>
<l>Here burns the glow through film and haze:</l>
<l>Now like a tender thread it creepeth,</l>
<l>Now like a fountain leaps and plays.</l>
<l>Here winds away, and in a hundred</l>
<l>Divided veins the valley braids:</l>
<l>There, in a corner pressed and sundered,</l>
<l>Itself detaches, spreads and fades.</l>
<l>Here gush the sparkles incandescent</l>
<l>Like scattered showers of golden sand;—</l>
<l>But, see! in all their height, at present,</l>
<l>The rocky ramparts blazing stand.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Has not Sir Mammon grandly lighted</l>
<l>His palace for this festal night?</l>
<l>&apos;Tis lucky thou hast seen the sight;</l>
<l>The boisterous guests approach that were invited.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>How raves the tempest through the air!</l>
<l>With what fierce blows upon my neck &apos;tis beating!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Under the old ribs of the rock retreating,</l>
<l>Hold fast, lest thou be hurled down the abysses there!</l>
<l>The night with the mist is black;</l>
<l>Hark! how the forests grind and crack!</l>
<l>Frightened, the owlets are scattered:</l>
<l>Hearken! the pillars are shattered.</l>
<l>The evergreen palaces shaking!</l>
<l>Boughs are groaning and breaking,</l>
<l>The tree-trunks terribly thunder,</l>
<l>The roots are twisting asunder!</l>
<l>In frightfully intricate crashing</l>
<l>Each on the other is dashing,</l>
<l>And over the wreck-strewn gorges</l>
<l>The tempest whistles and surges!</l>
<l>Hear&apos;st thou voices higher ringing?</l>
<l>Far away, or nearer singing?</l>
<l>Yes, the mountain&apos;s side along,</l>
<l>Sweeps an infuriate glamouring song!</l>

<l>WITCHES (in chorus)</l>

<l>The witches ride to the Brocken&apos;s top,</l>
<l>The stubble is yellow, and green the crop.</l>
<l>There gathers the crowd for carnival:</l>
<l>Sir Urian sits over all.</l>

<l>And so they go over stone and stock;</l>
<l>The witch she——-s, and——-s the buck.</l>

<Speaker>A VOICE</Speaker>

<l>Alone, old Baubo&apos;s coming now;</l>
<l>She rides upon a farrow-sow.</l>

<Speaker>CHORUS</Speaker>

<l>Then honor to whom the honor is due!</l>
<l>Dame Baubo first, to lead the crew!</l>
<l>A tough old sow and the mother thereon,</l>
<l>Then follow the witches, every one.</l>
<Speaker>A VOICE</Speaker>

<l>Which way com&apos;st thou hither?</l>

<Speaker>VOICE</Speaker>

<l>O&apos;er the Ilsen-stone.</l>
<l>I peeped at the owl in her nest alone:</l>
<l>How she stared and glared!</l>

<Speaker>VOICE</Speaker>

<l>Betake thee to Hell!</l>
<l>Why so fast and so fell?</l>

<Speaker>VOICE</Speaker>

<l>She has scored and has flayed me:</l>
<l>See the wounds she has made me!</l>

<Speaker>WITCHES (chorus</Speaker>

<l>The way is wide, the way is long:</l>
<l>See, what a wild and crazy throng!</l>
<l>The broom it scratches, the fork it thrusts,</l>
<l>The child is stifled, the mother bursts.</l>
<Speaker>WIZARDS (semichorus</Speaker>

<l>As doth the snail in shell, we crawl:</l>
<l>Before us go the women all.</l>
<l>When towards the Devil&apos;s House we tread,</l>
<l>Woman&apos;s a thousand steps ahead.</l>

<Speaker>OTHER SEMICHORUS</Speaker>

<l>We do not measure with such care:</l>
<l>Woman in thousand steps is theft.</l>
<l>But howsoe&apos;er she hasten may,</l>
<l>Man in one leap has cleared the way.</l>
<l>VOICE (from above)</l>

<l>Come on, come on, from Rocky Lake!</l>

<l>VOICE (from below)</l>

<l>Aloft we&apos;d fain ourselves betake.</l>
<l>We&apos;ve washed, and are bright as ever you will,</l>
<l>Yet we&apos;re eternally sterile still.</l>

<Speaker>BOTH CHORUSES</Speaker>

<l>The wind is hushed, the star shoots by.</l>
<l>The dreary moon forsakes the sky;</l>
<l>The magic notes, like spark on spark,</l>
<l>Drizzle, whistling through the dark.</l>
<l>VOICE (from below)</l>

<l>Halt, there! Ho, there!</l>

<l>VOICE (from above)</l>

<l>Who calls from the rocky cleft below there?</l>

<Speaker>VOICE (below</Speaker>

<l>Take me, too! take me, too!</l>
<l>I&apos;m climbing now three hundred years,</l>
<l>And yet the summit cannot see:</l>
<l>Among my equals I would be.</l>

<Speaker>BOTH CHORUSES</Speaker>

<l>Bears the broom and bears the stock,</l>
<l>Bears the fork and bears the buck:</l>
<l>Who cannot raise himself to-night</l>
<l>Is evermore a ruined wight.</l>
<l>HALF-WITCH (below)</l>

<l>So long I stumble, ill bestead,</l>
<l>And the others are now so far ahead!</l>
<l>At home I&apos;ve neither rest nor cheer,</l>
<l>And yet I cannot gain them here.</l>

<l>CHORUS OF WITCHES</l>

<l>To cheer the witch will salve avail;</l>
<l>A rag will answer for a sail;</l>
<l>Each trough a goodly ship supplies;</l>
<l>He ne&apos;er will fly, who now not flies.</l>
<Speaker>BOTH CHORUSES</Speaker>

<l>When round the summit whirls our flight,</l>
<l>Then lower, and on the ground alight;</l>
<l>And far and wide the heather press</l>
<l>With witchhood&apos;s swarms of wantonness!</l>
<l>(They settle down.)</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>They crowd and push, they roar and clatter!</l>
<l>They whirl and whistle, pull and chatter!</l>
<l>They shine, and spirt, and stink, and burn!</l>
<l>The true witch-element we learn.</l>
<l>Keep close! or we are parted, in our turn,</l>
<l>Where art thou?</l>

<l>FAUST (in the distance)</l>

<Speaker>Here</Speaker>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>What! whirled so far astray?</l>
<l>Then house-right I must use, and clear the way.</l>
<l>Make room! Squire Voland comes! Room, gentle rabble,</l>
<Speaker>room</Speaker>

<l>Here, Doctor, hold to me: in one jump we&apos;ll resume</l>
<l>An easier space, and from the crowd be free:</l>
<l>It&apos;s too much, even for the like of me.</l>
<l>Yonder, with special light, there&apos;s something shining clearer</l>
<l>Within those bushes; I&apos;ve a mind to see.</l>
<l>Come on! we&apos;ll slip a little nearer.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Spirit of Contradiction! On! I&apos;ll follow straight.</l>
<l>&apos;Tis planned most wisely, if I judge aright:</l>
<l>We climb the Brocken&apos;s top in the Walpurgis-Night,</l>
<l>That arbitrarily, here, ourselves we isolate.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>But see, what motley flames among the heather!</l>
<l>There is a lively club together:</l>
<l>In smaller circles one is not alone.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Better the summit, I must own:</l>
<l>There fire and whirling smoke I see.</l>
<l>They seek the Evil One in wild confusion:</l>
<l>Many enigmas there might find solution.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>But there enigmas also knotted be.</l>
<l>Leave to the multitude their riot!</l>
<l>Here will we house ourselves in quiet.</l>
<l>It is an old, transmitted trade,</l>
<l>That in the greater world the little worlds are made.</l>
<l>I see stark-nude young witches congregate,</l>
<l>And old ones, veiled and hidden shrewdly:</l>
<l>On my account be kind, nor treat them rudely!</l>
<l>The trouble&apos;s small, the fun is great.</l>
<l>I hear the noise of instruments attuning,—</l>
<l>Vile din! yet one must learn to bear the crooning.</l>
<l>Come, come along! It must be, I declare!</l>
<l>I&apos;ll go ahead and introduce thee there,</l>
<l>Thine obligation newly earning.</l>
<l>That is no little space: what say&apos;st thou, friend?</l>
<l>Look yonder! thou canst scarcely see the end:</l>
<l>A hundred fires along the ranks are burning.</l>
<l>They dance, they chat, they cook, they drink, they court:</l>
<l>Now where, just tell me, is there better sport?</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Wilt thou, to introduce us to the revel,</l>
<l>Assume the part of wizard or of devil?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>I&apos;m mostly used, &apos;tis true, to go incognito,</l>
<l>But on a gala-day one may his orders show.</l>
<l>The Garter does not deck my suit,</l>
<l>But honored and at home is here the cloven foot.</l>
<l>Perceiv&apos;st thou yonder snail? It cometh, slow and steady;</l>
<l>So delicately its feelers pry,</l>
<l>That it hath scented me already:</l>
<l>I cannot here disguise me, if I try.</l>
<l>But come! we&apos;ll go from this fire to a newer:</l>
<l>I am the go-between, and thou the wooer.</l>

<l>(To some, who are sitting around dying embers:)</l>

<l>Old gentlemen, why at the outskirts? Enter!</l>
<l>I&apos;d praise you if I found you snugly in the centre,</l>
<l>With youth and revel round you like a zone:</l>
<l>You each, at home, are quite enough alone.</l>

<Speaker>GENERAL</Speaker>

<l>Say, who would put his trust in nations,</l>
<l>Howe&apos;er for them one may have worked and planned?</l>
<l>For with the people, as with women,</l>
<l>Youth always has the upper hand.</l>

<Speaker>MINISTER</Speaker>

<l>They&apos;re now too far from what is just and sage.</l>
<l>I praise the old ones, not unduly:</l>
<l>When we were all-in-all, then, truly,</l>
<l>Then was the real golden age.</l>

<Speaker>PARVENU</Speaker>

<l>We also were not stupid, either,</l>
<l>And what we should not, often did;</l>
<l>But now all things have from their bases slid,</l>
<l>Just as we meant to hold them fast together.</l>

<Speaker>AUTHOR</Speaker>

<l>Who, now, a work of moderate sense will read?</l>
<l>Such works are held as antiquate and mossy;</l>
<l>And as regards the younger folk, indeed,</l>
<l>They never yet have been so pert and saucy.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>(who all at once appears very old)</l>

<l>I feel that men are ripe for Judgment-Day,</l>
<l>Now for the last time I&apos;ve the witches&apos;-hill ascended:</l>
<l>Since to the lees my cask is drained away,</l>
<l>The world&apos;s, as well, must soon be ended.</l>

<Speaker>HUCKSTER-WITCH</Speaker>

<l>Ye gentlemen, don&apos;t pass me thus!</l>
<l>Let not the chance neglected be!</l>
<l>Behold my wares attentively:</l>
<l>The stock is rare and various.</l>
<l>And yet, there&apos;s nothing I&apos;ve collected—</l>
<l>No shop, on earth, like this you&apos;ll find!—</l>
<l>Which has not, once, sore hurt inflicted</l>
<l>Upon the world, and on mankind.</l>
<l>No dagger&apos;s here, that set not blood to flowing;</l>
<l>No cup, that hath not once, within a healthy frame</l>
<l>Poured speedy death, in poison glowing:</l>
<l>No gems, that have not brought a maid to shame;</l>
<l>No sword, but severed ties for the unwary,</l>
<l>Or from behind struck down the adversary.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Gossip! the times thou badly comprehendest:</l>
<l>What&apos;s done has happed—what haps, is done!</l>
<l>&apos;Twere better if for novelties thou sendest:</l>
<l>By such alone can we be won.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Let me not lose myself in all this pother!</l>
<l>This is a fair, as never was another!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>The whirlpool swirls to get above:</l>
<l>Thou&apos;rt shoved thyself, imagining to shove.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>But who is that?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Note her especially,</l>
<l>Tis Lilith.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<Speaker>Who</Speaker>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Adam&apos;s first wife is she.</l>
<l>Beware the lure within her lovely tresses,</l>
<l>The splendid sole adornment of her hair!</l>
<l>When she succeeds therewith a youth to snare,</l>
<l>Not soon again she frees him from her jesses.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Those two, the old one with the young one sitting,</l>
<l>They&apos;ve danced already more than fitting.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>No rest to-night for young or old!</l>
<l>They start another dance: come now, let us take hold!</l>

<l>FAUST (dancing with the young witch)</l>

<l>A lovely dream once came to me;</l>
<l>I then beheld an apple-tree,</l>
<l>And there two fairest apples shone:</l>
<l>They lured me so, I climbed thereon.</l>

<l>THE FAIR ONE</l>

<l>Apples have been desired by you,</l>
<l>Since first in Paradise they grew;</l>
<l>And I am moved with joy, to know</l>
<l>That such within my garden grow.</l>

<l>MEPHISTOPHELES (dancing with the old one)</l>

<l>A dissolute dream once came to me:</l>
<l>Therein I saw a cloven tree,</l>
<l>Which had a————————;</l>
<l>Yet,——as &apos;twas, I fancied it.</l>
<l>THE OLD ONE</l>

<l>I offer here my best salute</l>
<l>Unto the knight with cloven foot!</l>
<l>Let him a—————prepare,</l>
<l>If him—————————does not scare.</l>
<Speaker>PROKTOPHANTASMIST</Speaker>

<l>Accurséd folk! How dare you venture thus?</l>
<l>Had you not, long since, demonstration</l>
<l>That ghosts can&apos;t stand on ordinary foundation?</l>
<l>And now you even dance, like one of us!</l>

<l>THE FAIR ONE (dancing)</l>

<l>Why does he come, then, to our ball?</l>

<Speaker>FAUST (dancing</Speaker>

<l>O, everywhere on him you fall!</l>
<l>When others dance, he weighs the matter:</l>
<l>If he can&apos;t every step bechatter,</l>
<l>Then &apos;tis the same as were the step not made;</l>
<l>But if you forwards go, his ire is most displayed.</l>
<l>If you would whirl in regular gyration</l>
<l>As he does in his dull old mill,</l>
<l>He&apos;d show, at any rate, good-will,—</l>
<l>Especially if you heard and heeded his hortation.</l>

<Speaker>PROKTOPHANTASMIST</Speaker>

<l>You still are here? Nay, &apos;tis a thing unheard!</l>
<l>Vanish, at once! We&apos;ve said the enlightening word.</l>
<l>The pack of devils by no rules is daunted:</l>
<l>We are so wise, and yet is Tegel haunted.</l>
<l>To clear the folly out, how have I swept and stirred!</l>
<l>Twill ne&apos;er be clean: why, &apos;tis a thing unheard!</l>

<l>THE FAIR ONE</l>

<l>Then cease to bore us at our ball!</l>

<Speaker>PROKTOPHANTASMIST</Speaker>

<l>I tell you, spirits, to your face,</l>
<l>I give to spirit-despotism no place;</l>
<l>My spirit cannot practise it at all.</l>

<l>(The dance continues)</l>

<l>Naught will succeed, I see, amid such revels;</l>
<l>Yet something from a tour I always save,</l>
<l>And hope, before my last step to the grave,</l>
<l>To overcome the poets and the devils.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>He now will seat him in the nearest puddle;</l>
<l>The solace this, whereof he&apos;s most assured:</l>
<l>And when upon his rump the leeches hang and fuddle,</l>
<l>He&apos;ll be of spirits and of Spirit cured.</l>

<l>(To FAUST, who has left the dance:)</l>

<l>Wherefore forsakest thou the lovely maiden,</l>
<l>That in the dance so sweetly sang?</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Ah! in the midst of it there sprang</l>
<l>A red mouse from her mouth—sufficient reason.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>That&apos;s nothing! One must not so squeamish be;</l>
<l>So the mouse was not gray, enough for thee.</l>
<l>Who&apos;d think of that in love&apos;s selected season?</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Then saw I—.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<Speaker>What</Speaker>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Mephisto, seest thou there,</l>
<l>Alone and far, a girl most pale and fair?</l>
<l>She falters on, her way scarce knowing,</l>
<l>As if with fettered feet that stay her going.</l>
<l>I must confess, it seems to me</l>
<l>As if my kindly Margaret were she.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Let the thing be! All thence have evil drawn:</l>
<l>It is a magic shape, a lifeless eidolon.</l>
<l>Such to encounter is not good:</l>
<l>Their blank, set stare benumbs the human blood,</l>
<l>And one is almost turned to stone.</l>
<l>Medusa&apos;s tale to thee is known.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Forsooth, the eyes they are of one whom, dying,</l>
<l>No hand with loving pressure closed;</l>
<l>That is the breast whereon I once was lying,—</l>
<l>The body sweet, beside which I reposed!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Tis magic all, thou fool, seduced so easily!</l>
<l>Unto each man his love she seems to be.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>The woe, the rapture, so ensnare me,</l>
<l>That from her gaze I cannot tear me!</l>
<l>And, strange! around her fairest throat</l>
<l>A single scarlet band is gleaming,</l>
<l>No broader than a knife-blade seeming!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Quite right! The mark I also note.</l>
<l>Her head beneath her arm she&apos;ll sometimes carry;</l>
<l>Twas Perseus lopped it, her old adversary.</l>
<l>Thou crav&apos;st the same illusion still!</l>
<l>Come, let us mount this little hill;</l>
<l>The Prater shows no livelier stir,</l>
<l>And, if they&apos;ve not bewitched my sense,</l>
<l>I verily see a theatre.</l>
<l>What&apos;s going on?</l>

<Speaker>SERVIBILIS</Speaker>

<l>&apos;Twill shortly recommence:</l>
<l>A new performance—&apos;tis the last of seven.</l>
<l>To give that number is the custom here:</l>
<l>&apos;Twas by a Dilettante written,</l>
<l>And Dilettanti in the parts appear.</l>
<l>That now I vanish, pardon, I entreat you!</l>
<l>As Dilettante I the curtain raise.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>When I upon the Blocksberg meet you,</l>
<l>I find it good: for that&apos;s your proper place.</l>

<Scene> XXII </Scene>
<l>WALPURGIS-NIGHT&apos;S DREAM</l>

<l>OBERON AND TITANIA&apos;s GOLDEN WEDDING</l>

<Speaker>INTERMEZZO</Speaker>

<Speaker>MANAGER</Speaker>

<l>Sons of Mieding, rest to-day!</l>
<l>Needless your machinery:</l>
<l>Misty vale and mountain gray,</l>
<l>That is all the scenery.</l>

<Speaker>HERALD</Speaker>

<l>That the wedding golden be.</l>
<l>Must fifty years be rounded:</l>
<l>But the Golden give to me,</l>
<l>When the strife&apos;s compounded.</l>

<Speaker>OBERON</Speaker>

<l>Spirits, if you&apos;re here, be seen—</l>
<l>Show yourselves, delighted!</l>
<l>Fairy king and fairy queen,</l>
<l>They are newly plighted.</l>

<Speaker>PUCK</Speaker>

<l>Cometh Puck, and, light of limb,</l>
<l>Whisks and whirls in measure:</l>
<l>Come a hundred after him,</l>
<l>To share with him the pleasure.</l>

<Speaker>ARIEL</Speaker>

<l>Ariel&apos;s song is heavenly-pure,</l>
<l>His tones are sweet and rare ones:</l>
<l>Though ugly faces he allure,</l>
<l>Yet he allures the fair ones.</l>

<Speaker>OBERON</Speaker>

<l>Spouses, who would fain agree,</l>
<l>Learn how we were mated!</l>
<l>If your pairs would loving be,</l>
<l>First be separated!</l>

<Speaker>TITANIA</Speaker>

<l>If her whims the wife control,</l>
<l>And the man berate her,</l>
<l>Take him to the Northern Pole,</l>
<l>And her to the Equator!</l>

<l>ORCHESTRA. TUTTI.</l>

<Speaker>Fortissimo</Speaker>

<l>Snout of fly, mosquito-bill,</l>
<l>And kin of all conditions,</l>
<l>Frog in grass, and cricket-trill,—</l>
<l>These are the musicians!</l>

<Speaker>SOLO</Speaker>

<l>See the bagpipe on our track!</l>
<l>&apos;Tis the soap-blown bubble:</l>
<l>Hear the schnecke-schnicke-schnack</l>
<l>Through his nostrils double!</l>

<l>SPIRIT, JUST GROWING INTO FORM</l>

<l>Spider&apos;s foot and paunch of toad,</l>
<l>And little wings—we know &apos;em!</l>
<l>A little creature &apos;twill not be,</l>
<l>But yet, a little poem.</l>

<l>A LITTLE COUPLE</l>

<l>Little step and lofty leap</l>
<l>Through honey-dew and fragrance:</l>
<l>You&apos;ll never mount the airy steep</l>
<l>With all your tripping vagrance.</l>

<Speaker>INQUISITIVE TRAVELLER</Speaker>

<l>Is&apos;t but masquerading play?</l>
<l>See I with precision?</l>
<l>Oberon, the beauteous fay,</l>
<l>Meets, to-night, my vision!</l>

<Speaker>ORTHODOX</Speaker>

<l>Not a claw, no tail I see!</l>
<l>And yet, beyond a cavil,</l>
<l>Like &quot;the Gods of Greece,&quot; must he</l>
<l>Also be a devil.</l>

<Speaker>NORTHERN ARTIST</Speaker>

<l>I only seize, with sketchy air,</l>
<l>Some outlines of the tourney;</l>
<l>Yet I betimes myself prepare</l>
<l>For my Italian journey.</l>

<Speaker>PURIST</Speaker>

<l>My bad luck brings me here, alas!</l>
<l>How roars the orgy louder!</l>
<l>And of the witches in the mass,</l>
<l>But only two wear powder.</l>

<Speaker>YOUNG WITCH</Speaker>

<l>Powder becomes, like petticoat,</l>
<l>A gray and wrinkled noddy;</l>
<l>So I sit naked on my goat,</l>
<l>And show a strapping body.</l>

<Speaker>MATRON</Speaker>

<l>We&apos;ve too much tact and policy</l>
<l>To rate with gibes a scolder;</l>
<l>Yet, young and tender though you be,</l>
<l>I hope to see you moulder.</l>

<l>LEADER OF THE BAND</l>

<l>Fly-snout and mosquito-bill,</l>
<l>Don&apos;t swarm so round the Naked!</l>
<l>Frog in grass and cricket-trill,</l>
<l>Observe the time, and make it!</l>

<l>WEATHERCOCK (towards one side)</l>

<l>Society to one&apos;s desire!</l>
<l>Brides only, and the sweetest!</l>
<l>And bachelors of youth and fire.</l>
<l>And prospects the completest!</l>

<l>WEATHERCOCK (towards the other side)</l>

<l>And if the Earth don&apos;t open now</l>
<l>To swallow up each ranter,</l>
<l>Why, then will I myself, I vow,</l>
<l>Jump into hell instanter!</l>

<Speaker>XENIES</Speaker>

<l>Us as little insects see!</l>
<l>With sharpest nippers flitting,</l>
<l>That our Papa Satan we</l>
<l>May honor as is fitting.</l>

<Speaker>HENNINGS</Speaker>

<l>How, in crowds together massed,</l>
<l>They are jesting, shameless!</l>
<l>They will even say, at last,</l>
<l>That their hearts are blameless.</l>

<Speaker>MUSAGETES</Speaker>

<l>Among this witches&apos; revelry</l>
<l>His way one gladly loses;</l>
<l>And, truly, it would easier be</l>
<l>Than to command the Muses.</l>

<l>CI-DEVANT GENIUS OF THE AGE</l>

<l>The proper folks one&apos;s talents laud:</l>
<l>Come on, and none shall pass us!</l>
<l>The Blocksberg has a summit broad,</l>
<l>Like Germany&apos;s Parnassus.</l>

<Speaker>INQUISITIVE TRAVELLER</Speaker>

<l>Say, who&apos;s the stiff and pompous man?</l>
<l>He walks with haughty paces:</l>
<l>He snuffles all he snuffle can:</l>
<l>&quot;He scents the Jesuits&apos; traces.&quot;</l>

<Speaker>CRANE</Speaker>

<l>Both clear and muddy streams, for me</l>
<l>Are good to fish and sport in:</l>
<l>And thus the pious man you see</l>
<l>With even devils consorting.</l>

<Speaker>WORLDLING</Speaker>

<l>Yes, for the pious, I suspect,</l>
<l>All instruments are fitting;</l>
<l>And on the Blocksberg they erect</l>
<l>Full many a place of meeting.</l>

<Speaker>DANCER</Speaker>

<l>A newer chorus now succeeds!</l>
<l>I hear the distant drumming.</l>
<l>&quot;Don&apos;t be disturbed! &apos;tis, in the reeds,</l>
<l>The bittern&apos;s changeless booming.&quot;</l>

<Speaker>DANCING-MASTER</Speaker>

<l>How each his legs in nimble trip</l>
<l>Lifts up, and makes a clearance!</l>
<l>The crooked jump, the heavy skip,</l>
<l>Nor care for the appearance.</l>

<Speaker>GOOD FELLOW</Speaker>

<l>The rabble by such hate are held,</l>
<l>To maim and slay delights them:</l>
<l>As Orpheus&apos; lyre the brutes compelled,</l>
<l>The bagpipe here unites them.</l>

<Speaker>DOGMATIST</Speaker>

<l>I&apos;ll not be led by any lure</l>
<l>Of doubts or critic-cavils:</l>
<l>The Devil must be something, sure,—</l>
<l>Or how should there be devils?</l>

<Speaker>IDEALIST</Speaker>

<l>This once, the fancy wrought in me</l>
<l>Is really too despotic:</l>
<l>Forsooth, if I am all I see,</l>
<l>I must be idiotic!</l>

<Speaker>REALIST</Speaker>

<l>This racking fuss on every hand,</l>
<l>It gives me great vexation;</l>
<l>And, for the first time, here I stand</l>
<l>On insecure foundation.</l>

<Speaker>SUPERNATURALIST</Speaker>

<l>With much delight I see the play,</l>
<l>And grant to these their merits,</l>
<l>Since from the devils I also may</l>
<l>Infer the better spirits.</l>

<Speaker>SCEPTIC</Speaker>

<l>The flame they follow, on and on,</l>
<l>And think they&apos;re near the treasure:</l>
<l>But Devil rhymes with Doubt alone,</l>
<l>So I am here with pleasure.</l>

<l>LEADER OF THE BAND</l>

<l>Frog in green, and cricket-trill.</l>
<l>Such dilettants!—perdition!</l>
<l>Fly-snout and mosquito-bill,—</l>
<l>Each one&apos;s a fine musician!</l>

<Speaker>THE ADROIT</Speaker>

<l>Sans souci, we call the clan</l>
<l>Of merry creatures so, then;</l>
<l>Go a-foot no more we can,</l>
<l>And on our heads we go, then.</l>

<Speaker>THE AWKWARD</Speaker>

<l>Once many a bit we sponged, but now,</l>
<l>God help us! that is done with:</l>
<l>Our shoes are all danced out, we trow,</l>
<l>We&apos;ve but naked soles to run with.</l>

<l>WILL-O&apos;-THE WISPS</l>

<l>From the marshes we appear,</l>
<l>Where we originated;</l>
<l>Yet in the ranks, at once, we&apos;re here</l>
<l>As glittering gallants rated.</l>

<Speaker>SHOOTING-STAR</Speaker>

<l>Darting hither from the sky,</l>
<l>In star and fire light shooting,</l>
<l>Cross-wise now in grass I lie:</l>
<l>Who&apos;ll help me to my footing?</l>

<l>THE HEAVY FELLOWS</l>

<l>Room! and round about us, room!</l>
<l>Trodden are the grasses:</l>
<l>Spirits also, spirits come,</l>
<l>And they are bulky masses.</l>

<Speaker>PUCK</Speaker>

<l>Enter not so stall-fed quite,</l>
<l>Like elephant-calves about one!</l>
<l>And the heaviest weight to-night</l>
<l>Be Puck, himself, the stout one!</l>

<Speaker>ARIEL</Speaker>

<l>If loving Nature at your back,</l>
<l>Or Mind, the wings uncloses,</l>
<l>Follow up my airy track</l>
<l>To the mount of roses!</l>

<Speaker>ORCHESTRA</Speaker>

<Speaker>pianissimo</Speaker>
<l>Cloud and trailing mist o&apos;erhead</l>
<l>Are now illuminated:</l>
<l>Air in leaves, and wind in reed,</l>
<l>And all is dissipated.</l>

<Scene> XXIII </Scene>
<Speaker>DREARY DAY</Speaker>

<Speaker>A FIELD</Speaker>

<Speaker>FAUST MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>In misery! In despair! Long wretchedly astray on the face</l>
<l>of the earth, and now imprisoned! That gracious, ill-starred</l>
<l>creature shut in a dungeon as a criminal, and given</l>
<l>up to fearful torments! To this has it come! to this!—Treacherous,</l>
<l>contemptible spirit, and thou hast concealed it from</l>
<l>me!—Stand, then,—stand! Roll the devilish eyes wrathfully in</l>
<l>thy head! Stand and defy me with thine intolerable presence!</l>
<l>Imprisoned! In irretrievable misery! Delivered up to evil</l>
<l>spirits, and to condemning, unfeeling Man! And thou hast</l>
<l>lulled me, meanwhile, with the most insipid dissipations, hast</l>
<l>concealed from me her increasing wretchedness, and suffered</l>
<l>her to go helplessly to ruin!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>She is not the first.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Dog! Abominable monster! Transform him, thou Infinite</l>
<l>Spirit! transform the reptile again into his dog-shape? in which</l>
<l>it pleased him often at night to scamper on before me, to roll</l>
<l>himself at the feet of the unsuspecting wanderer, and hang</l>
<l>upon his shoulders when he fell! Transform him again into</l>
<l>his favorite likeness, that he may crawl upon his belly in the</l>
<l>dust before me,—that I may trample him, the outlawed, under</l>
<l>foot! Not the first! O woe! woe which no human soul can</l>
<l>grasp, that more than one being should sink into the depths</l>
<l>of this misery,—that the first, in its writhing death-agony</l>
<l>under the eyes of the Eternal Forgiver, did not expiate the</l>
<l>guilt of all others! The misery of this single one pierces to the</l>
<l>very marrow of my life; and thou art calmly grinning at the</l>
<l>fate of thousands!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Now we are already again at the end of our wits, where the</l>
<l>understanding of you men runs wild. Why didst thou enter</l>
<l>into fellowship with us, if thou canst not carry it out? Wilt fly,</l>
<l>and art not secure against dizziness? Did we thrust ourselves</l>
<l>upon thee, or thou thyself upon us?</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Gnash not thus thy devouring teeth at me? It fills me with</l>
<l>horrible disgust. Mighty, glorious Spirit, who hast vouchsafed</l>
<l>to me Thine apparition, who knowest my heart and my soul,</l>
<l>why fetter me to the felon-comrade, who feeds on mischief and</l>
<l>gluts himself with ruin?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>Hast thou done?</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Rescue her, or woe to thee! The fearfullest curse be upon</l>
<l>thee for thousands of ages!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>I cannot loosen the bonds of the Avenger, nor undo his bolts.</l>
<l>Rescue her? Who was it that plunged her into ruin? I, or thou?</l>

<l>(FAUST looks around wildly.)</l>

<l>Wilt thou grasp the thunder? Well that it has not been</l>
<l>given to you, miserable mortals! To crush to pieces the innocent</l>
<l>respondent—that is the tyrant-fashion of relieving one&apos;s</l>
<l>self in embarrassments.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Take me thither! She shall be free!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>And the danger to which thou wilt expose thyself? Know</l>
<l>that the guilt of blood, from thy hand, still lies upon the town!</l>
<l>Avenging spirits hover over the spot where the victim fell, and</l>
<l>lie in wait for the returning murderer.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>That, too, from thee? Murder and death of a world upon</l>
<l>thee, monster! Take me thither, I say, and liberate her!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>I will convey thee there; and hear, what I can do! Have I</l>
<l>all the power in Heaven and on Earth? I will becloud the</l>
<l>jailer&apos;s senses: get possession of the key, and lead her forth with</l>
<l>human hand! I will keep watch: the magic steeds are ready,</l>
<l>I will carry you off. So much is in my power.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Up and away!</l>

<Scene> XXIV </Scene>
<Speaker>NIGHT</Speaker>

<Speaker>OPEN FIELD</Speaker>

<l>(FAUST and MEPHISTOPHELES speeding onward on black horses.)</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>What weave they there round the raven-stone?</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>I know not what they are brewing and doing.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Soaring up, sweeping down, bowing and bending!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>A witches&apos;-guild.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>They scatter, devote and doom!</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>On! on!</l>

<Scene> XXV </Scene>
<Speaker>DUNGEON</Speaker>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>(with a bunch of keys and a lamp, before an iron door)</l>

<l>A shudder, long unfelt, comes o&apos;er me;</l>
<l>Mankind&apos;s collected woe o&apos;erwhelms me, here.</l>
<l>She dwells within the dark, damp walls before me,</l>
<l>And all her crime was a delusion dear!</l>
<l>What! I delay to free her?</l>
<l>I dread, once again to see her?</l>
<l>On! my shrinking but lingers Death more near.</l>

<l>(He grasps the lock: the sound of singing is heard inside.)</l>

<l>My mother, the harlot,</l>
<l>Who put me to death;</l>
<l>My father, the varlet,</l>
<l>Who eaten me hath!</l>
<l>Little sister, so good,</l>
<l>Laid my bones in the wood,</l>
<l>In the damp moss and clay:</l>
<l>Then was I a beautiful bird o&apos; the wood;</l>
<l>Fly away! Fly away!</l>
<Speaker>FAUST (unlocking</Speaker>

<l>She does not dream her lover listens near;</l>
<l>That he the rattling chain, the rustling straw, can hear.</l>

<l>(He enters.)</l>

<l>MARGARET (hiding herself on the pallet)</l>
<l>Woe! woe! They come. O death of bitterness!</l>

<Speaker>FAUST (whispering</Speaker>
<l>Hush! hush! The hour is come that frees thee.</l>

<l>MARGARET (throwing herself before him)</l>
<l>Art thou a man, then pity my distress!</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>
<l>Thy cries will wake the guards, and they will seize thee!</l>
<l>(He takes hold of the fetters to unlock them.)</l>

<l>MARGARET (on her knees)</l>

<l>Who, headsman! unto thee such power</l>
<l>Over me could give?</l>
<l>Thou&apos;rt come for me at midnight-hour:</l>
<l>Have mercy on me, let me live!</l>
<l>Is&apos;t not soon enough when morning chime has run?</l>

<l>(She rises.)</l>

<l>And I am yet so young, so young!</l>
<l>And now Death comes, and ruin!</l>
<l>I, too, was fair, and that was my undoing.</l>
<l>My love was near, but now he&apos;s far;</l>
<l>Torn lies the wreath, scattered the blossoms are.</l>
<l>Seize me not thus so violently!</l>
<l>Spare me! What have I done to thee?</l>
<l>Let me not vainly entreat thee!</l>
<l>I never chanced, in all my days, to meet thee!</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Shall I outlive this misery?</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>Now am I wholly in thy might.</l>
<l>But let me suckle, first, my baby!</l>
<l>I blissed it all this livelong night;</l>
<l>They took &apos;t away, to vex me, maybe,</l>
<l>And now they say I killed the child outright.</l>
<l>And never shall I be glad again.</l>
<l>They sing songs about me! &apos;tis bad of the folk to do it!</l>
<l>There&apos;s an old story has the same refrain;</l>
<l>Who bade them so construe it?</l>

<l>FAUST (falling upon his knees)</l>

<l>Here lieth one who loves thee ever,</l>
<l>The thraldom of thy woe to sever.</l>

<l>MARGARET (flinging herself beside him)</l>

<l>O let us kneel, and call the Saints to hide us!</l>
<l>Under the steps beside us,</l>
<l>The threshold under,</l>
<l>Hell heaves in thunder!</l>
<l>The Evil One</l>
<l>With terrible wrath</l>
<l>Seeketh a path</l>
<l>His prey to discover!</l>

<Speaker>FAUST (aloud</Speaker>

<l>Margaret! Margaret!</l>

<l>MARGARET (attentively listening)</l>

<l>That was the voice of my lover!</l>

<l>(She springs to her feet: the fetters fall off.)</l>

<l>Where is he? I heard him call me.</l>
<l>I am free! No one shall enthrall me.</l>
<l>To his neck will I fly,</l>
<l>On his bosom lie!</l>
<l>On the threshold he stood, and Margaret! calling,</l>
<l>Midst of Hell&apos;s howling and noises appalling,</l>
<l>Midst of the wrathful, infernal derision,</l>
<l>I knew the sweet sound of the voice of the vision!</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>&apos;Tis I!</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>&apos;Tis thou! O, say it once again!</l>

<l>(Clasping him.)</l>

<l>&apos;Tis he! &apos;tis he! Where now is all my pain?</l>
<l>The anguish of the dungeon, and the chain?</l>
<l>&apos;Tis thou! Thou comest to save me,</l>
<l>And I am saved!—</l>
<l>Again the street I see</l>
<l>Where first I looked on thee;</l>
<l>And the garden, brightly blooming,</l>
<l>Where I and Martha wait thy coming.</l>

<l>FAUST (struggling to leave)</l>

<l>Come! Come with me!</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>Delay, now!</l>
<l>So fain I stay, when thou delayest!</l>

<l>(Caressing him.)</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Away, now!</l>
<l>If longer here thou stayest,</l>
<l>We shall be made to dearly rue it.</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>Kiss me!—canst no longer do it?</l>
<l>My friend, so short a time thou&apos;rt missing,</l>
<l>And hast unlearned thy kissing?</l>
<l>Why is my heart so anxious, on thy breast?</l>
<l>Where once a heaven thy glances did create me,</l>
<l>A heaven thy loving words expressed,</l>
<l>And thou didst kiss, as thou wouldst suffocate me—</l>
<l>Kiss me!</l>
<l>Or I&apos;ll kiss thee!</l>

<l>(She embraces him.)</l>

<l>Ah, woe! thy lips are chill,</l>
<l>And still.</l>
<l>How changed in fashion</l>
<l>Thy passion!</l>
<l>Who has done me this ill?</l>

<l>(She turns away from him.)</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Come, follow me! My darling, be more bold:</l>
<l>I&apos;ll clasp thee, soon, with warmth a thousand-fold;</l>
<l>But follow now! &apos;Tis all I beg of thee.</l>

<l>MARGARET (turning to him)</l>

<l>And is it thou? Thou, surely, certainly?</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>&apos;Tis I! Come on!</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>Thou wilt unloose my chain,</l>
<l>And in thy lap wilt take me once again.</l>
<l>How comes it that thou dost not shrink from me?—</l>
<l>Say, dost thou know, my friend, whom thou mak&apos;st free?</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Come! come! The night already vanisheth.</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>My mother have I put to death;</l>
<l>I&apos;ve drowned the baby born to thee.</l>
<l>Was it not given to thee and me?</l>
<l>Thee, too!—&apos;Tis thou! It scarcely true doth seem—</l>
<l>Give me thy hand! &apos;Tis not a dream!</l>
<l>Thy dear, dear hand!—But, ah, &apos;tis wet!</l>
<l>Why, wipe it off! Methinks that yet</l>
<l>There&apos;s blood thereon.</l>
<l>Ah, God! what hast thou done?</l>
<l>Nay, sheathe thy sword at last!</l>
<l>Do not affray me!</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>O, let the past be past!</l>
<l>Thy words will slay me!</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>No, no! Thou must outlive us.</l>
<l>Now I&apos;ll tell thee the graves to give us:</l>
<l>Thou must begin to-morrow</l>
<l>The work of sorrow!</l>
<l>The best place give to my mother,</l>
<l>Then close at her side my brother,</l>
<l>And me a little away,</l>
<l>But not too very far, I pray!</l>
<l>And here, on my right breast, my baby lay!</l>
<l>Nobody else will lie beside me!—</l>
<l>Ah, within thine arms to hide me,</l>
<l>That was a sweet and a gracious bliss,</l>
<l>But no more, no more can I attain it!</l>
<l>I would force myself on thee and constrain it,</l>
<l>And it seems thou repellest my kiss:</l>
<l>And yet &apos;tis thou, so good, so kind to see!</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>If thou feel&apos;st it is I, then come with me!</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>Out yonder?</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>To freedom.</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>If the grave is there,</l>
<l>Death lying in wait, then come!</l>
<l>From here to eternal rest:</l>
<l>No further step—no, no!</l>
<l>Thou goest away! O Henry, if I could go!</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Thou canst! Just will it! Open stands the door.</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>I dare not go: there&apos;s no hope any more.</l>
<l>Why should I fly? They&apos;ll still my steps waylay!</l>
<l>It is so wretched, forced to beg my living,</l>
<l>And a bad conscience sharper misery giving!</l>
<l>It is so wretched, to be strange, forsaken,</l>
<l>And I&apos;d still be followed and taken!</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>I&apos;ll stay with thee.</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>Be quick! Be quick!</l>
<l>Save thy perishing child!</l>
<l>Away! Follow the ridge</l>
<l>Up by the brook,</l>

<l>Over the bridge,</l>
<l>Into the wood,</l>
<l>To the left, where the plank is placed</l>
<l>In the pool!</l>
<l>Seize it in haste!</l>
<l>&apos;Tis trying to rise,</l>
<l>&apos;Tis struggling still!</l>
<l>Save it! Save it!</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Recall thy wandering will!</l>
<l>One step, and thou art free at last!</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>If the mountain we had only passed!</l>
<l>There sits my mother upon a stone,—</l>
<l>I feel an icy shiver!</l>
<l>There sits my mother upon a stone,</l>
<l>And her head is wagging ever.</l>
<l>She beckons, she nods not, her heavy head falls o&apos;er;</l>
<l>She slept so long that she wakes no more.</l>
<l>She slept, while we were caressing:</l>
<l>Ah, those were the days of blessing!</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Here words and prayers are nothing worth;</l>
<l>I&apos;ll venture, then, to bear thee forth.</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>No—let me go! I&apos;ll suffer no force!</l>
<l>Grasp me not so murderously!</l>
<l>I&apos;ve done, else, all things for the love of thee.</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>The day dawns: Dearest! Dearest!</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>Day? Yes, the day comes,—the last day breaks for me!</l>
<l>My wedding-day it was to be!</l>
<l>Tell no one thou has been with Margaret!</l>
<l>Woe for my garland! The chances</l>
<l>Are over—&apos;tis all in vain!</l>
<l>We shall meet once again,</l>
<l>But not at the dances!</l>
<l>The crowd is thronging, no word is spoken:</l>
<l>The square below</l>
<l>And the streets overflow:</l>
<l>The death-bell tolls, the wand is broken.</l>
<l>I am seized, and bound, and delivered—</l>
<l>Shoved to the block—they give the sign!</l>
<l>Now over each neck has quivered</l>
<l>The blade that is quivering over mine.</l>
<l>Dumb lies the world like the grave!</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>O had I ne&apos;er been born!</l>

<l>MEPHISTOPHELES (appears outside)</l>

<l>Off! or you&apos;re lost ere morn.</l>
<l>Useless talking, delaying and praying!</l>
<l>My horses are neighing:</l>
<l>The morning twilight is near.</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>What rises up from the threshold here?</l>
<l>He! he! suffer him not!</l>
<l>What does he want in this holy spot?</l>
<l>He seeks me!</l>

<Speaker>FAUST</Speaker>

<l>Thou shalt live.</l>

<Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker>

<l>Judgment of God! myself to thee I give.</l>

<l>MEPHISTOPHELES (to FAUST)</l>

<l>Come! or I&apos;ll leave her in the lurch, and thee!</l>

<l><Speaker>MARGARET</Speaker></l>

<l>Thine am I, Father! rescue me!</l>
<l>Ye angels, holy cohorts, guard me,</l>
<l>Camp around, and from evil ward me!</l>
<l>Henry! I shudder to think of thee.</l>

<Speaker>MEPHISTOPHELES</Speaker>

<l>She is judged!</l>

<l>VOICE (from above)</l>

<l>She is saved!</l>

<l>MEPHISTOPHELES (to FAUST)</l>

<l>Hither to me!</l>

<l>(He disappears with FAUST.)</l>

<l>VOICE (from within, dying away)</l>

<l>Henry! Henry!</l>


</Play>